. GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE JULY 22ND 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENTS SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO
ENGARDIO PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL
SHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT MR.
PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF
THE ROMITA SALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW
MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOME LAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA OWNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE AND PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH STANDS ONE
NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR
ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT US OF GOTV TODAY
PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE
. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? YES.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO
ATTEND THIS MEETING HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER
LOCATED WITHIN CITY HALL ON THE SECOND FLOOR IN ROOM 250.
IF YOU CANNOT MAKE IT DOWN TO THE CHAMBER YOU CAN ALWAYS
WATCH THE BOARD MEETING ON S.F. GOVEE TVS CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW
THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GOVEE TV DAWG.
IF YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT YOU CAN SEND AN EMAIL
TO BOSS AT S.F. GOV.ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE.
JUST ADDRESS YOUR ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA
94102. >> IF YOU ARE INTENDING ON
SPEAKING DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT LATER ON IN THE MEETING
NOTE THAT ITEMS FIVE THROUGH 25 THAT THOSE ITEMS COMPRISE THE
CITY'S BUDGET AS WELL AS ITEM 26 THE LARGE AND COMMERCIAL
VEHICLE PARKING RESTRICTIONS. >> THE PUBLIC COMMENT TIME
FRAME FOR THOSE ITEMS HAS CLOSED.
YOU WILL BE REDIRECTED IF YOU SPEAK ON ANY OF THOSE ITEMS
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT TODAY.
SO PLEASE DON'T. >> IF YOU'D LIKE TO MAKE A
FUTURE REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION REQUEST UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. MEMBERS.
THANK YOU, MADAME CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO THE APPROVAL OF
OUR MEETING MINUTES. APPROVAL OF THE JUNE 17TH 2025
REGULAR BOARD MEETING MINUTES AND THE JUNE 18TH, 20TH
AND 23RD 2025 SPECIAL MEETING MINUTES AT THE BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATIONS COMMITTEE MEETING WHICH CONSTITUTED A
QUORUM OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVE BY CHERYL SECONDED BY CHAN
AND MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR ITEMS ONE
THROUGH FOUR ARE ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. ALL RIGHT.
I DON'T SEE ANYONE ON THE ROSTER.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE
THROUGH FOUR SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL MIN I MANDEL
MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY
PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS AND THE
FINAL READING OF THE BUDGET AND CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEMS
FIVE THROUGH 24 TOGETHER? ITEM FIVE THIS IS A BUT THIS IS
THE BUDGET AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE ALL
ESTIMATED RECEIPTS AND EXPENDITURES FOR THE CITY
AND COUNTY DEPARTMENTS AS OF MAY 30TH 2025 AND FOR THE
FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH 2026 AND 2027.
ITEM SIX THIS IS THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE THAT
ENUMERATES POSITIONS AND FIXES COMPENSATION IN THE ANNUAL
BUDGET AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR THE FISCAL YEARS
ENDING JUNE 30TH, 2026 AND JUNE 30TH 2027.
ITEM SEVEN THIS ORDINANCE AMENDING THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE THAT MODIFIES THE SHORT TERM LICENSE FEES FOR THE USE
OF CITY HALL ITEM EIGHT THIS ORDINANCE AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO TRANSFER RESPONSIBILITIES FOR OVERSIGHT
OF THE COLLECTION OF SEXUAL ORIENTATION AND GENDER IDENTITY
DATA FROM THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO THE HUMAN
RIGHTS COMMISSION. ITEM NINE THIS ORDINANCE
AMENDING THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CLARIFY THE STATUS OF
THE TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY AS A CITY DEPARTMENT.
ITEM TEN THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO
ELIMINATE THE BUDGET SAVINGS INCENTIVE FUND.
ITEM 11 THIS ORDINANCE ADOPTS THE NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION
AND GRAFFITI CLEANUP FUND TAX DESIGNATION CEILING FOR TAX
YEAR 2025 ITEM 12 THIS ORDINANCE MODIFIES THE BASELINE
FUNDING REQUIREMENTS FOR EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION PROGRAMS
AND ENABLES THE CITY TO USE THE INTEREST EARNED FROM THE EARLY
CARE AND EDUCATION COMMERCIAL RENTS TAX FOR THOSE BASELINE
PROGRAMS. ITEM 13 THIS ORDINANCE
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC DEFENDERS
OFFICE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $3.4 MILLION GRANT FROM THE
KROENKE START FOUNDATION TO EXPAND THE CAPACITY OF THE
IMMIGRATION DEFENSE UNIT MARCH 1ST, 2025 THROUGH MARCH 1ST,
2029 AND AMEND THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE FOR FISCAL
YEARS 2024 THROUGH 25 AND 2025 THROUGH 26 TO PROVIDE FOR THE
ADDITION OF FOUR GRANT FUNDED POSITIONS THREE CLASS 8177
ATTORNEYS AND ONE FTE 8173 LEGAL ASSISTANT IN THE PUBLIC
DEFENDERS OFFICE. ITEM 14 THIS ORDINANCE
APPROPRIATES AND APPROPRIATES FOR A TOTAL NET THE
APPROPRIATION AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 87,000 FOR THE
SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION CAPITAL PROJECTS
BUDGET ITEM 15 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE
AND SALE OF TAX EXEMPT OR TAXABLE WATER REVENUE BONDS
AND OTHER FORMS OF INDEBTEDNESS BY THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC
UTILITIES COMMISSION IN AN AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 1.1
BILLION TO FINANCE THE COSTS OF VARIOUS CAPITAL WATER AND HETCH
HETCHY WATER PROJECTS AND TO AUTHORIZE THE ISSUANCE OF WATER
REVENUE REFUNDING BONDS AND THE RETIREMENT OF OUTSTANDING WATER
ENTERPRISE COMMERCIAL PAPER ITEM 16 THIS ORDINANCE
APPROPRIATES A 12.9 MILLION APPROXIMATELY IN THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION BENEFITING THE WATER
ENTERPRISE CAPITAL IMPROVEMENTS IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 26
ITEM 17 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE. THE HEALTH CODE, THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AND THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO AMEND THE
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH PERMIT FEE AND PENALTIES REVISIONS ITEM 18
THIS ORDINANCE AMENDING THE HEALTH CODE TO SET PATIENT
RATES FOR SERVICES PROVIDED BY THE TO THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH AND TO AUTHORIZE TO WAIVE OR REDUCE FEES TO MEET
THE NEEDS OF LOW INCOME PATIENTS EACH ITEM 19 THIS
ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PUBLIC WORKS AND SUBDIVISION CODES TO
MODIFY CERTAIN PERMIT FEES INCLUDING WAIVING FEES FOR CAFE
TABLES AND CHAIRS AND DISPLAY MERCHANDISE, REGISTRANTS
AND CERTAIN MINOR SIDEWALK ENCROACHMENTS THAT ARE A
PERTINENT BUILDING FEATURES AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION. ITEM 20 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE BUILDINGS SUBDIVISION AND ADMINISTRATIVE CODES TO
ADJUST FEES CHARGED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION AND TO ESTABLISH SUB FUNDS WITHIN THE BUILDING
INSPECTION FUND AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
AND ITEM 21 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PART CODE TO
AUTHORIZE THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT TO ADD A
COST RECOVERY SURCHARGE TO THE FEES FOR THE USE OF CITY GOLF
COURSES, OUTDOOR EVENT FACILITIES, PICNIC AREAS
AND ATHLETIC FIELDS AND INCREASES GOLF COURSE FEES
AND REQUIRES THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO POST AN
UPDATE ON ITS WEBSITE THE GOLF COURSE FEES AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION ITEM 22 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO AUTHORIZE FEES FOR VEHICLES TO
FUND LAW ENFORCEMENT PROGRAMS AND TO ESTABLISH THE POLICE
FINGERPRINT IDENTIFICATION FUND ITEM 23 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE PARK CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE RECREATION
AND PARK DEPARTMENTS TO CHARGE FEES FOR RESERVING TENNIS
AND PICKLEBALL COURTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SCORING
DETERMINATION AND ITEM 24 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PARK CODE TO ALLOW THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT
TO SET FEES FOR RECREATION PROGRAMS BASED ON THE
DEPARTMENT'S OPERATING COSTS. DIRECTING THE COMMISSION TO
UPDATE ITS SCHOLARSHIP POLICY TO PROVIDE FOR FURTHER
DISCOUNTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SEQUOYAH DETERMINATION.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. ALTHOUGH WE CALLED ALL OF THESE
TOGETHER WE'RE GOING TO BE VOTING ON THEM.
I BELIEVE IN TWO BATCHES THE FIRST BEING SIX THROUGH 21
AND THE SECOND BATCH BEING FIVE, 22, 23 AND 24 IF THAT
SOUNDS RIGHT TO EVERYBODY I'LL ASK THE CLERK TO CALL THE TWO.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS SIX THROUGH 21 ON ITEMS SIX
THROUGH 21 SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EITHER
LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED
AND THEN MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
FIVE 2223 AND 24 ON ITEMS FIVE 2223 AND 24 SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO
WITH SUPERVISOR FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY
PASSED MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 25 ITEM 25
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO
REALLOCATE APPROXIMATELY 34.8 MILLION IN PRIOR APPROPRIATED
REVENUE AND UNAPPROPRIATED EARNED INTEREST TO ALLOW THE
CITY TO USE REVENUES FROM THE HOMELESSNESS GROSS RECEIPTS TAX
THROUGH FISCAL YEAR 2026 THROUGH 27 FOR CERTAIN TYPES OF
SERVICES TO ADDRESS HOMELESSNESS WHERE FUTURE
REVENUE AND INTEREST TO THE ALCOHOL FUND EXCEEDS AMOUNTS
APPROPRIATED IN THE ADOPTED BUDGET FOR FISCAL YEARS 20 2526
AND 20 2627 TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO EXPEND UP TO 19.1
MILLION OF SUCH ADDITIONAL REVENUES AND INTEREST ON ANY
PROGRAMS TO ADDRESS HOMELESSNESS TO TEMPORARILY
SUSPEND THE LIMIT ON FUNDING FOR THE SHORT TERM RENTAL
SUBSIDIES AND TO AND FINDING THAT THESE REALLOCATIONS ARE
NECESSARY TO ACHIEVE THE PURPOSES OF THE OUR CITY, OUR
HOME FUND THIS ITEM PURSUANT TO THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE REQUIRES A SUPERMAJORITY VOTE OF AT LEAST
EIGHT MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO PASS.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. AND AS WE VOTED ON THIS IS A
DIVIDED QUESTION LAST TIME WE WILL AGAIN SUPERVISOR FIELDER
THANK YOU. >> I JUST WANTED TO MAKE SURE
THAT THAT WAS GOING TO HAPPEN AGAIN.
THANKS. SO MADAM CLERK, FIRST ON THE ON
THE DIVIDE QUESTION, I BELIEVE WE WILL VOTE FIRST ON SECTION
FOUR OF THE ORDINANCE. CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> YES. WE ARE VOTING ON THE DIVIDED
PORTION WHICH IS SECTION FOUR PAGES I BELIEVE PAGE FIVE, LINE
22 THROUGH THROUGH PAGE SIX, LINE SIX SUPERVISE HER DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN
I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND THREE
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER WALTON AND CHIN VOTING NO
SECTION FOUR OF THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED ON THE
REMAINING BALANCE OF THE QUESTION OF THE REMAINING
BALANCE OF THE ORDINANCE. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF ITEM 25 SUPERVISOR
DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO AND GAUDIO I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHENNAI THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY
PASSED AND WITH PASSAGE OF BOTH THE DIVIDED PORTION AND THE
BALANCE THE ORDINANCE AS A WHOLE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 26?
>> ITEM 26 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE DIVISION ONE OF
THE TRANSPORTATION CODE TO REDUCE THE TIME THAT LARGE
VEHICLES MAY BE PARKED ON CITY STREETS FROM OVERNIGHT TO TWO
HOURS AND TO MODIFY THE TIME THAT COMMERCIAL VEHICLES MAY BE
PARKED ON CITY STREETS AMONG OTHER REQUIREMENTS.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 26 SUPERVISOR
DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND GUARD
AND GUARDIAN EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT MANDEL MAN
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER
AND WALTON VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 27 MR. PRESIDENT, BEFORE I DO I'LL
JUST REMIND THE AUDIENCE THAT THERE ARE NO AUDIBLE SIGNS OF
BEING AGAINST AN ITEM OR BEING SUPPORTIVE OF AN ITEM.
IF YOU ARE INTERESTED IN SUPPORTING SOMETHING YOU CAN
JUST WAIVE YOUR WAIVE. >> YOUR HANDS IS SUCH ITEM 27
MR. PRESIDENT? YES PLEASE MADAM ITEM 20 SEVEN
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO
EXPAND THE SCOPE OF EMERGENCY PROCUREMENT PROVISIONS FOR
GOODS AND SERVICES AND TO ALLOW CITY DEPARTMENTS TO MODIFY
AGREEMENTS AND WAYS NOT CONTEMPLATED IN THE ORIGINAL
SOLICITATIONS. >> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT THE DEPARTMENT AS THE OFFICE OF
CONTRACT MINISTRATION IS REQUESTING A TECHNICAL
AMENDMENT TO REFERENCE VOTER APPROVED CONTRACT PROVISION
AND ADDITIONAL LANGUAGE IS ON PAGE SIX LINE 24 THROUGH SIX.
MY APOLOGIES ON PAGE SIX LINE 24 THROUGH PAGE SEVEN LINE TWO
AND LANGUAGE ARE NOTWITHSTANDING THE FOREGOING
SENTENCE EMERGENCY CONTRACTS ARE SUBJECT TO CHAPTER 12 G
AND 12 A.M. OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
AND RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE CAMPAIGN AND GOVERNMENTAL
CONDUCT CODE. THIS IS REALLY FOR CLARIFYING
JUST MAKING SURE THAT WE ARE CLEAR OF WHAT CONSTITUTES
EMERGENCY SINCE WE'RE EXPANDING THE EMERGENCY DEFINITION
AND WHAT IS WHAT ACTUALLY DIDN'T QUALIFY AS WELL.
>> AND THANK YOU. SO I MOVE MOVE TO AMEND THANK
YOU FOR THE MOTION CHAIR CHAN IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
CHEN AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION
AND MADAME CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED
ORDINANCE ON ITEM 27 AS AMENDED SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I'M SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
THE ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 28 ITEM 28 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE THAT APPROVES
AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO ACQUIRE CERTAIN
REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 601 THROUGH 617 LAGUNA STREET TO
AUTHORIZE AN AGREEMENT OF PURCHASE AND SALE FOR REAL
ESTATE FOR THE ACQUISITION OF THE PROPERTY FROM PACIFICA LLC
FOR A TOTAL ANTICIPATED NOT TO EXCEED PROJECT COST OF 20
MILLION TO AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO MAKE
CERTAIN MODIFICATIONS TO THE PURCHASE AGREEMENT TO EXEMPT
THE PROJECT FROM CONTRACTING REQUIREMENTS AND ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE CHAPTER SIX AND CHAPTER 14 B AND TO APPROVE THE SELLER
WITHOUT COMPETITIVE BIDDING TO PLACE THE PROPERTY UNDER THE
JURISDICTION OF THE REAL ESTATE DIVISION AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 29 ITEM 29 PURSUANT TO CHARTER SECTION
8.4 22 THIS MATTER SHALL REQUIRE A VOTE OF THREE FOURTHS
OR NINE AFFIRMATIVE VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TO
APPROVE PASSAGE OF THIS ORDINANCE ON FIRST READING ITEM
20 NINE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE HEALTH SERVICES SYSTEM
PLANS AND CONTRIBUTION RATES FOR CALENDAR YEAR 2026 AND WE
WILL TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAME CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 30. >> ITEM 30 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF TECHNOLOGY TO ENTER INTO A
FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE ENTERPRISE AGREEMENT WITH KARA
SOFT TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION TO PURCHASE SERVICE NOW SOFTWARE
PRODUCTS TO INCREASE THE TERM FOR AN ADDITIONAL FOUR YEARS
NOW THROUGH AUGUST 31ST 2029 AND TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT
AMOUNT FOR A NEW NOT TO EXCEED AMOUNT OF 28.3 MILLION AND WE
CAN TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 31. >> ITEM 31 RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE THE THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE DOMESTIC TERMINAL THREE
COMMON USE CLUB LEASE BETWEEN AMERICAN EXPRESS TRAVEL RELATED
SERVICES COMPANY AND THE AIRPORT COMMISSION TO
TEMPORARILY RELOCATE THE AMERICAN EXPRESS CENTURION
LOUNGE FROM ITS TERMINAL THREE PREMISE TO TERMINAL TWO WITH A
TEMPORARY DECREASE OF THE MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE AMOUNT
TO APPROXIMATELY 2 MILLION AND OF THE ANNUAL PROMOTIONAL
CHARGE TO APPROXIMATELY 9000 AND A DAY TO DAY EXTENSION OF
THE LEASE TERM THROUGH NOVEMBER 5TH, 2031.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL ITEM 32. >> ITEM 32 RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE OFFICE OF
CONTRACT ADMINISTRATION WITH THE DUTRA GROUP FOR A CUSTOM
CRANE BARGE FOR THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR AN INITIAL TERM
OF APPROXIMATELY TWO YEARS TO JULY 14TH 2027 FOR A NEW AMOUNT
OF 16.7 MILLION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 33.
>> ITEM 33 THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A GRANT OF
626,000 FROM THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION
SUSTAINABLE TRANSPORTATION PLANNING GRANT FOR A
PERFORMANCE PERIOD NOVEMBER 4TH, 2020 FOR THROUGH JUNE 30TH
2027 TO FUND THE PLANNING OF THE SOUTH OF MARKET UNDER
FREEWAY PARK SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 34.
>> ITEM 34 RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE
AND APPROVE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY ON BEHALF OF THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING TO
NEGOTIATE AND ENTER INTO A NEW SUBLEASE AGREEMENT A PROPERTY
THAT HAS BEEN OWNED BY THE CALIFORNIA STATE LANDS
COMMISSION FOR THE CITY'S USE AS THE BAY VIEW VEHICLE TRIAGE
CENTER AT CANDLESTICK POINT STATE RECREATION AREA JANUARY
13TH, 2024 THROUGH APRIL 11TH 2025 FOR A BASE RENT OF 312,000
PER YEAR TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDING. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS 35 AND 36 TOGETHER.
>> ITEMS 35 AND 36 PERTAIN TO TEPHRA HEARINGS.
ITEM 35 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE ISSUANCE AND SALE
OF REVENUE OBLIGATIONS BY THE CALIFORNIA ENTERPRISE
DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT NOT
TO EXCEED 10 MILLION. >> TO FINANCE OR REFINANCE THE
COST OF ACQUISITION, CONSTRUCTION IMPROVEMENT
AND EQUIPPING OF VARIOUS EDUCATIONAL FACILITIES OWNED
AND OPERATED BY LA SCOLA INTERNATIONAL SCHOOL.
ITEM 36 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE
OF REVENUE OBLIGATIONS BY THE CALIFORNIA NEW ENTERPRISE
DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IN AN AMOUNT OF 80 MILLION TO
FINANCE, REFINANCE OR REIMBURSE THE COST OF ACQUISITION
CONSTRUCTION, INSTALLATION, REHABILITATION, EQUIPPING
AND OR FURNISHING OF VARIOUS CAPITAL FACILITIES TO BE OWNED
AND OPERATED BY NATIONAL CENTER FOR INTERNATIONAL SCHOOLS.
>> AND SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. MADAME CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL ITEM 37 ITEM 37 RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
OFFICE OF THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO ACCEPT AN
EXPENDED GRANT AWARD UP TO 5 MILLION THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028
FROM THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA ENERGY COMMISSION FOR ELECTRIC
VEHICLE CHARGING INFRASTRUCTURE FOR GOVERNMENT FLEETS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 38. ITEM 38 RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
THE THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN ABODE
SERVICES AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING FOR PROBLEM SOLVING FISCAL AGENT SERVICES EXTENDING
THE TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND TO INCREASE THE AGREEMENT
FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT NOT TO EXCEED 17.1 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
39. >> ITEM 30 NINE RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND VARIOUS
GIFTS VALUED AT APPROXIMATELY 867,000 FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE COMMUNITY FOUNDATION TO SUPPORT OFFICER WELLNESS EVENTS
AND INITIATIVES TO SUPPORT COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT EVENTS
AND PROVIDE EQUIPMENT FOR THE POLICE DEPARTMENT DISTRICT
STATIONS. >> TO THAT SAME HOUSE SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 40.
>> ITEM 40 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO ACCEPT IRREVOCABLE OFFERS OF
PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE ASSOCIATED WITH THE POTRERO
HOPE S.F. PROJECT PHASE TWO TO DEDICATE THIS PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE FOR PUBLIC USE TO DESIGNATE THE PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE FOR PUBLIC STREET AND ROADWAY PURPOSES.
TO ACCEPT FOR THE PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE FOR CITY
MAINTENANCE AND LIABILITY PURPOSES TO ESTABLISH THE
OFFICIAL OFFICIAL PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY WIDTH AND STREET GRADES
TO ESTABLISH THE OFFICIAL SIDEWALK WIDTHS ON 25TH 26TH
OUR ARKANSAS, US, CONNECTICUT AND WISCONSIN STREETS TO ACCEPT
A PUBLIC WORKS ORDER AND TO AFFIRM THE SCORE DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 41
ITEM 41 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ADOPT THE 2025 HAZARDS
AND CLIMATE RESILIENCE PLAN AS SAN FRANCISCO'S UPDATE TO THE
2020 LOCAL HAZARD MITIGATION PLAN AND WE'LL TAKE THAT SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR 230
SPECIAL ORDER. >> IT IS NOW TIME TO RECOGNIZE
THOSE WHO DESERVE WHO DESERVE RECOGNITION FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WE WILL BEGIN WITH DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT MANDOLIN COLLEAGUES.
>> IT IS WITH IMMENSE GRATITUDE AND ADMIRATION THAT I TODAY
RECOGNIZE SOMEONE WHO HAS MADE AN INDELIBLE IMPACT ON THE
NEIGHBORHOODS OF DISTRICT SIX IN OUR CITY AS A WHOLE.
>> COMMANDER LUKE MARTIN UNTIL RECENTLY CAPTAIN LUKE MARTIN ON
HIS WELL-EARNED PROMOTION WITHIN THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT. >> FOR THOSE OF US WHO WORK
CLOSELY WITH HIM, THIS IS BOTH A PROUD AND BITTERSWEET MOMENT
. COMMANDER MARTIN STEPPED INTO
HIS LEADERSHIP AT SOUTHERN STATION DURING ONE OF THE MOST
CHALLENGING TIMES IN RECENT MEMORY FOR NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE
SOMA, THE EAST CUT AND RINCON HILL.
IN FACT, HIS TENURE AS SOUTHERN DISTRICT CAPTAIN CLOSELY
MATCHED MY OWN TENURE AS SUPERVISOR FROM DISTRICT SIX
WHICH ACCOUNTS FOR MOST OF THE SOUTHERN POLICE DISTRICT.
FROM DAY ONE, CAPTAIN MARTIN LED WITH PROFESSIONALISM,
INTEGRITY AND A RELENTLESS COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY
ENGAGEMENT AND PUBLIC SAFETY. HE DIDN'T JUST SHOW UP.
HE WAS PRESENT WHETHER IT WAS AN EARLY MORNING CHECK
IN FOLLOWING AN OVERNIGHT INCIDENT OR A CALL FROM A
CONCERNED CONSTITUENT. HE MADE SURE MY OFFICE NEVER
FACED CHALLENGES ALONE OR UNINFORMED AND HE BROUGHT WITH
HIM NOT JUST RESPONSIVENESS BUT HIS DEEP EXPERIENCE.
COMMANDER MARTIN HAS SERVED IN THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT SINCE 1998, FOLLOWING IN HIS FATHER'S
FOOTSTEPS AND CARRYING FORWARD A LEGACY OF SERVICE.
OVER THE YEARS HE'S WORKED TO PATROL IN THE MISSION
IN BAYVIEW. HE LED GANG INVESTIGATIONS
AND HE SERVED IN NIGHT INVESTIGATIONS AND THE TRAFFIC
COMPANY. HIS BREADTH OF EXPERIENCE IS
MATCHED ONLY BY HIS DEDICATION .
NOW I FIRST WORKED WITH LUKE WHEN HE WAS LIEUTENANT BUT IT
WAS AS CAPTAIN OF SOUTHERN STATION BEGINNING IN 2022 THAT
COMMANDER MARTIN'S LEADERSHIP TRULY BECAME PERSONAL FOR SO
MANY OF US AS RESIDENTS OF NEIGHBORHOODS THAT WERE BESET
BY DRUG DRIVEN LAWLESSNESS AND ASSOCIATED CHALLENGES.
AT LEVELS WE HAD NEVER SEEN BEFORE IN SOMA IN THE EAST CUT
IN MISSION BAY IN RINCON HILL AND ACROSS DISTRICT SIX HE
DIDN'T JUST ENFORCE THE LAW HE WAS A WELL-INFORMED AND HIGHLY
RESPONSIVE PUBLIC SAFETY LEADER.
HE EARNED THE COMMUNITY'S TRUST THROUGH HIS PATIENT AND CALM
DEMEANOR. HIS GENUINE EMPATHY AND HIS
GOOD HEART AND HE NEVER WAITED TO BE ASKED.
HE CALLED US. HE ASKED HOW HE COULD HELP
AND HE ALWAYS SHOWED UP QUIETLY, RELIABLY AND WITHOUT
FANFARE. HE WAS A FAMILIAR FAMILIAR FACE
AT COMMUNITY MEETINGS, A TRUSTED PARTNER TO LOCAL
BUSINESSES AND A STEADY HAND DURING SOME OF THE MOST
DIFFICULT PUBLIC SAFETY CHALLENGES MY DISTRICT FACED.
HE LISTENED. HE FOLLOWED THROUGH AND IN
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT TOO OFTEN FEEL NEGLECTED.
>> HE MADE SURE THAT THE RESIDENTS OF DISTRICT SIX FEEL
SEEN, HEARD AND PROTECTED. HE REMINDED SO MANY OF US AS
SAN FRANCISCANS THAT SAN FRANCISCO'S POLICE DEPARTMENT
HAS OUR BACK. NOW AS AN ELECTED POLITICIAN I
WILL CONFESS I AM NOT ALWAYS COMFORTABLE WITH PEOPLE WHO ARE
MORE POPULAR IN MY DISTRICT THAN I AM.
BUT WHEN THAT PERSON IS CAPTAIN LUKE BARTON NOW COMMANDER LUKE
MARTIN, I'M OKAY WITH IT. AS HE STEPS INTO HIS NEW ROLE
AS COMMANDER OF THE SPECIAL OPERATIONS BUREAU, I HAVE EVERY
CONFIDENCE THAT HE WILL CARRY FORWARD THE SAME VALUES THAT
DEFINED HIS LEADERSHIP IN SOUTHERN COMPASSION
ACCOUNTABILITY, RESPONSIBILITY, RESPONSIVENESS AND INTEGRITY.
AND I'M CONFIDENT HE WILL BE EVERY BIT AS POPULAR CITYWIDE
AS HE WAS IN DISTRICT SIX. COMMANDER MARTIN, ON BEHALF OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HEARS AND TOO FROM
ALL OF YOUR FANS IN DISTRICT SIX WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP, YOUR PARTNERSHIP AND YOUR EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE.
WE CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR NEXT CHAPTER.
>> WE WE AND WE JUST GOT IT DONE AND WE BESTOW UPON YOU
THAT PRESTIGIOUS AND UNIVERSALLY ACKNOWLEDGED
AWARD FOR EXCELLENCE IN THE FIELD OF POLICING.
DONUTS. >> NOW BEFORE YOU SPEAK, I
UNDERSTAND THAT MICHELLE DELANEY FROM MALONE LEVIN
MILLER WOULD ALSO LIKE TO SPEAK.
SO MICHELLE, WHY DON'T YOU TAKE THE FLOOR?
>> LET'S START. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. HELLO.
MY NAME IS MICHELLE DELANEY REPRESENTING THE COMMUNITY
POLICE ADVISORY BOARD TO HONOR AND SUPPORT THE PROMOTION OF
CAPTAIN LUKE, MARK AND MARTIN. A LEADER A PARTNER AND A TRUE
PILLAR OF OUR COMMUNITY. FOR THOSE OF US WHO HAVE HAD
THE PRIVILEGE OF WORKING ALONGSIDE HIM WHETHER THROUGH
THE POLICE ADVISORY BOARD, LOCAL BUSINESSES OR
NEIGHBORHOOD ESTABLISHMENTS ONE THING IS ABUNDANTLY CLEAR
CAPTAIN MARTIN EMBODIES WHAT IT MEANS TO SERVE WITH INTEGRITY,
COMPASSION AND UNWAVERING DEDICATION.
FROM THE VERY BEGINNING, CAPTAIN MARTIN APPROACHED EVERY
CONVERSATION, EVERY CHALLENGE AND EVERY COLLABORATION WITH
MUTUAL RESPECT. HE DIDN'T JUST LISTEN.
HE ENGAGED. HE DIDN'T JUST ACKNOWLEDGE
DIVERSE PERSPECTIVES. HE VALUED THEM IN A CITY AS
DYNAMIC AND COMPLEX IN SAN FRANCISCO.
HIS ABILITY TO OFFER REAL DIALOG EVEN ON TOUGH ISSUES
HELPED BUILD BRIDGES WHERE OTHERS MIGHT HAVE SEEN DIVIDES.
CAPTAIN MARTIN'S LEADERSHIP GAVE PROFOUND MEANING TO THE
PHRASE CIVIL SERVICE. HE UNDERSTOOD THAT TRUST ISN'T
GIVEN BUT EARNED THROUGH CONSTANT ACTION AND TIME AGAIN
FOLLOWED THROUGH WHETHER IT WAS STRENGTHENING THE NEIGHBORHOOD
POLICE RELATIONS ADVOCATING FOR EQUITABLE SOLUTIONS OR SIMPLY
SHOWING UP WITH AN OPEN MIND. HE MADE A LASTING IMPACT.
THE CPR RECOMMENDS THAT CAPTAIN MARTIN IS REWARDED WITH A
WELL-DESERVED PROMOTION TO COMMANDER.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU, MICHEL.
AND COMMANDER MARTIN. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
GOOD AFTERNOON, EVERYBODY. SO I MUST SAY I REALLY DIDN'T
KNOW WHAT TO EXPECT COMING IN HERE.
IT STARTED WITH ME WALKING DOWN THE HALL.
I SAW A LOT OF FAMILIAR FACES THERE ON THE BACK.
I THINK NOW WHETHER IT'S PEOPLE I'VE WORKED WITH WORKED FOR.
THEY ALL SHOWED UP IN SUPPORT. >> SO I WAS A LITTLE CAUGHT OFF
GUARD RIGHT NOW. YOU KNOW, SO I'M VERY
APPRECIATIVE. I THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR ALL
THOSE KIND WORDS. YOU KNOW, WORKING AS THE
CAPTAIN AT SOUTHERN STATION HAS DEFINITELY BEEN ONE OF THE
HIGHLIGHTS OF MY CAREER. >> I JUST IT.
YOU NEVER KNOW WHAT TO EXPECT WITH WORKING WITH EITHER THE
POLITICIAN SIDE, THE COMMUNITY SIDE AND I JUST GOT TO SAY
THAT'S IT'S BEEN JUST A LOT OF FUN CONNECTING WITH THE
DIFFERENT COMMUNITY MEMBERS, THE DIFFERENT GROUPS.
SOUTHERN IS SUCH AN AMAZING DISTRICT OR DISTRICT SIX JUST
SO MANY UNIQUE DIFFERENT SUB NEIGHBORHOODS AND JUST GETTING
TO KNOW EVERYBODY HAS BEEN JUST A BLAST.
I LOVED EVERY EVERY MINUTE OF IT AND YOU KNOW I DON'T KNOW IF
IT'S LIKE THIS FOR EVERYBODY SUPERVISOR DORSEY BUT IT
DEFINITELY FELT LIKE WE WERE A TEAM.
WE'RE ON THE SAME PAGE JUST WORKING TOGETHER.
IT NEVER FELT CONTENTIOUS OR WE WERE WITH DIFFERENT VIEWS.
WE WERE JUST KIND OF ALWAYS EASILY TEAMING UP AT DIFFERENT
COMMUNITY EVENTS OR PROBLEM SOLVING DIFFERENT THINGS AND I
JUST REALLY TREASURED THAT WORKING WITH YOU AND YOUR TEAM
MOHANA IS WHO I DEFINITELY OWE A LOT OF THANKS TO FOR HELPING
SET SET THIS UP TODAY AND I PLAN ON GETTING HER BACK
SOMEHOW. JUST AMAZING WHETHER IT'S BRIAN
OR DAVID FROM BEFORE AND DOMENICA I MEAN JUST WHAT A
GREAT STAFF AND A PLEASURE TO WORK WITH.
>> AND THEN I'D LOVE TO THANK THE REST OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, YOU KNOW THE POLICE DEPARTMENT HASN'T ALWAYS
HAD A LOT OF SUPPORT HERE IN THE CITY BUT WE'RE
DEFINITELY FEELING IT NOW AND IT'S MADE SUCH A DIFFERENCE
AND I THINK YOU CAN REALLY SEE IT WITH WHAT'S HAPPENING IN THE
CITY DESPITE STAFFING CHALLENGES WE'RE GETTING SO
MUCH DONE AS A POLICE DEPARTMENT TO TRY TO MAKE THIS
CITY BETTER, SAFER AND JUST MORE ENJOYABLE FOR ALL THE
WHETHER THEY LIVE HERE, WORK HERE, TRAVEL HERE.
SO I REALLY THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR SUPPORT FOR THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT. WE TRULY NEED IT AND I THINK
TOGETHER WE CAN JUST KEEP MAKING ALL THOSE STRIDES TO
MAKE THIS CITY AMAZING. >> I GOT TO THANK ALL MY
BROTHERS AND SISTERS FROM THE POLICE DEPARTMENT WHO SHOWED
UP. WE GOT OUR ALL OF OUR DEPUTY
CHIEFS HERE I DON'T KNOW IF CHEAP CHIEF YAP IS IN A MEETING
ALL BY HIMSELF RIGHT NOW BUT SOMEHOW THEY THEY ARE HERE
WITHOUT A MEETING. I SO HARD TO BELIEVE THAT YOU
GOT ALL THE DEPUTY CHIEF THERE SO I WANT TO THANK ALL THE
COMMAND STAFF MEMBERS I HAVE MY FORMER STAFF FROM SOUTHERN
STATION THE LIEUTENANTS, THE CAPTAINS STAFF THAT WERE ABLE
TO BREAK FREE AND SURPRISE ME. COME IN HERE A FEW OF OUR
FRIENDS FROM THE COMMUNITY ALSO SHOWED UP.
THANK YOU EVERYBODY. I REALLY APPRECIATE IT.
AND THEN JUST LASTLY, I'D LIKE TO THANK MY FAMILY, MY WIFE
AND MY CHILDREN HERE. THEY'RE JUST BEEN A HUGE
SUPPORT. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THEY'RE RIGHT BEHIND ME SO YEAH, THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
JUST SUPPORTING ME WITH ALL THE CRAZY SCHEDULE CHANGES
AND STRESSES AND THINGS LIKE THAT.
>> THEY'VE BEEN AMAZING SO I LOVE YOU ALL.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. ONE MORE.
LET'S GO. >> DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR
FIELDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN I WOULD LIKE TO
WELCOME TO THE PODIUM THE STAFF AND OWNER AT JOLENE'S.
>> PLEASE COME UP. >> TODAY I HAVE THE PRIVILEGE
OF RECOGNIZING AN INSTITUTION THAT HAS CREATED AN
EXTRAORDINARY CULTURE AND COMMUNITY IN DISTRICT NINE
THAT IS A VIBRANT AND VITAL PART OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
AND CULTURE NIGHTLIFE. >> JOLENE'S BAR AND JOLENE
LOCATED IN THE MISSION DISTRICT, A NEIGHBORHOOD LONG
KNOWN FOR RESILIENCE AND CULTURAL PRIDE.
JOLENE'S HAS BECOME A SANCTUARY A PLACE FOR COMMUNITY
CELEBRATION AND LIBERATION. JOLENE ISN'T JUST A BAR.
IT'S A HOME. IT HAS IT'S A HOME FOR SAN
FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY FOR WOMEN, FOR PEOPLE
OF COLOR AND FOR EVERYONE WHO VALUES INCLUSIVE JOYFUL SPACES.
AT A TIME WHEN VENUES ACROSS THE COUNTRY ARE DISAPPEARING
DUE TO RISING RENTS AND THE LASTING IMPACTS OF THE
PANDEMIC, JOLENE'S CONTINUES TO THRIVE.
JOLENE IS NOT JUST A NIGHTLIFE VENUE IT IS A BEACON OF WHAT
COMMUNITY CAN BE. A SPACE FOR DRAG, FOR MUSIC,
FOR MUTUAL AID AND BEST OF ALL FOR ACTIVISM.
>> JOLENE HAS CREATED A SPACE THAT REMINDS US THAT VENUES
AREN'T JUST PLACES TO GATHER. THERE ARE PLACES TO ORGANIZE,
TO HEAL, TO EXPRESS JOY AND TO RESIST BECAUSE OF JOLENE'S
PASSIONATE LEADERSHIP. AS A WOMAN AND SMALL BUSINESS
OWNER, SHE HAS BUILT A GATHERING SPACE THAT HAS
CREATED JOBS UPLIFTED LOCAL TALENT AND OPENED DOORS TO ALL.
ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD AND SUPERVISORS, WE THANK
YOU JOLENE, FOR WHAT YOU'VE BUILT FOR ALL THE STAFF AND FOR
THE COMMUNITY YOU CONTINUED TO NURTURE.
>> PLEASE GO AHEAD. >> THANK YOU.
I WAS EARLY PREPARED FOR THIS EITHER BUT LIKE THEY SAID, IT
TAKES A IT TAKES A VILLAGE SO I'M REALLY HAPPY THAT MY STAFF
IS HERE. FEW MISSING BUT WE LOVE THEM
AND I REALLY CAN'T DO WHAT I DO FOR WORK WITHOUT MY ENTIRE
TEAM. SO THANK YOU FOR FOR
RECOGNIZING THAT OUR OUR SPACES SO MUCH TO US AND OUR ENTIRE
COMMUNITY. SO THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING US
. >> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND CAN I HAVE THE
FIRST CLASS OF WOMEN POLICE OFFICERS PLEASE COME IN LINE UP
BY THE PODIUM AND AS THEY COME UP.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM HONORING A POWERFUL AND LONG
OVERDUE MILESTONE IN THE HISTORY OF OUR CITY AND THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT. WE ARE RECOGNIZING THE
COURAGEOUS WOMEN OF THE 126TH PRECINCT RECRUIT CLASS 126
RECRUIT CLASS THE VERY FIRST WOMEN IN THE SAN FRANCISCO
HISTORY TO BE SWORN IN ASSIGNED TO FULL PATROL DUTIES IN OUR
POLICE DEPARTMENT. >> I WOULD LIKE TO FORMALLY
RECOGNIZE THOSE WHO ARE IN ATTENDANCE WITH US TODAY.
VICKY QUINN, MAUREEN D'AMICO, PAMELA MEADS, TERRY IVY ARLENE,
DRUMMER JACKIE JOE MARY PETRIE .
>> GLADYS JACKSON. ON JULY ON JULY 28TH, 1975 50
YEARS AGO TODAY, WOMEN JOINED THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT AS FULLY EMPOWERED PATROL OFFICERS.
>> THIS WAS NOT JUST A POLICY CHANGE.
IT WAS A BOLD HISTORY MAKING MOMENT IN THE FIGHT FOR GENDER
EQUITY IN LAW ENFORCEMENT. THESE WOMEN STEPPED INTO THE
SAME ROLES FACED THE SAME RISKS AND CARRIED THE SAME
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THEIR MALE COUNTERPARTS SOMETHING THAT HAD
NEVER HAPPENED BEFORE IN OUR CITY.
BUT THIS MOMENT DIDN'T HAPPEN BY CHANCE.
IT HAPPENED BECAUSE OF YEARS OF ADVOCACY AND COURAGE MOST
NOTABLY BY OFFICERS FOR JUSTICE ,A GROUP OF MOSTLY BLACK
OFFICERS WHO IN 1968 STOOD UP AND FILED A FORMAL DISCRIMINATE
ACTION LAWSUIT AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THEIR FIGHT FOR FAIRNESS WAS JOINED BY POWERFUL ALLIES LIKE
THE NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN.
EILEEN HERNANDEZ AND ASSOCIATES THE NATIONAL ADVANCEMENT
ORGANIZATION OF COLORED PEOPLE CHINESE FOR AFFIRMATIVE ACTION
AND OTHER COMMUNITY ADVOCATES WHO KNEW THIS WAS BIGGER THAN
ONE DEPARTMENT. IT WAS ABOUT EQUITY AND PUBLIC
SERVICE ACROSS THE BOARD TO THE WOMEN OF THE 126TH RECRUIT
CLASS. YOUR PRESENCE CHANGED THE
CULTURE OF THE DEPARTMENT. YOUR STRENGTH AND PERSISTENCE
HELPED MOVE OUR CITY FORWARD AND YOUR LEGACY LIVES ON
IN EVERY WOMAN WHO NOW WEARS THE BADGE AND SERVES OUR
COMMUNITIES WITH HONOR. >> SAN FRANCISCO THANKS YOU.
WE SEE YOU. WE UPLIFT YOU AND WE CELEBRATE
THIS 50 YEAR MILESTONE WITH DEEP PRIDE AND GRATITUDE.
>> THANK YOU
. >> AND I AND I BELIEVE OUR LEAD
DRUMMER WILL BE SPEAKING FOR THE GROUP.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT. MANY OF THE OTHER BOARD
SUPERVISORS MY COUSIN SHERMAN WALKED IN AND SAID EVERYTHING.
BUT I DID HAVE SOME SOME NOTES THAT I WROTE DOWN THERE.
I JUST WANTED TO KIND OF GO OVER.
>> IT MIGHT BE A LOT OF REPEATING BUT I GOT TO SAY
SOMETHING RIGHT? >> MY NAME IS ARLENE GEORGE,
DRUMMER. I'M GOING TO GIVE YOU A BRIEF
HISTORY OF HOW THIS JOURNEY BEGAN IN 1973 A GROUP OF NINE
ACTIVE DUTY AFRICAN-AMERICAN AND ONE CAUCASIAN POLICE
OFFICER WHO WERE MEMBERS OF THE OFFICERS FOR JUSTICE WHICH WAS
A SEPARATE UNION FROM THE POLICE OFFICERS ASSOCIATION
WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF THE FIRM PUBLIC ADVOCATE, A PUBLIC
INTEREST LAW FIRM FILED A SUIT IN U.S. DISTRICT COURT.
PRESIDING JUDGE ROBERT PECKHAM CONTENDING THAT THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT DISCRIMINATED AGAINST
MINORITIES AND WOMEN. SEVERAL ORGANIZATION HAS
ALREADY BEEN MENTIONED. >> JACK PECKHAM THEN FROZE ALL
ENTRY LEVEL HIRING UNTIL CORRECTIVE ACTIONS WERE TAKEN
BY THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I ADVOCATE LAWYERS WERE WHICH CONSIST OF THREE CAPABLE
LAWYERS ROBERT CAN NEITHER LAWS LORD THORNBURY AND ANGELA
BLACKWELL WHO FOUGHT HARD TO DEFEND THIS LAWSUIT AND AS A
RESULT JUDGE PECKHAM HALTED ALL ENTRY LEVEL HIRING IN THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT UNTIL CORRECTIVE MEASURES WERE
IMPLEMENTED TO ADDRESS DISCRIMINATION.
>> SOON AFTER ON SEPTEMBER 3RD, 1974, THE CIVIL SERVICE
COMMISSION SO SAID THAT 1800 WOMEN HAD APPLIED TO TAKE THE
ENTRY LEVEL TEST TO BECOME PATROL OFFICERS.
>> MAY THE 2ND 1975 JUDGE PECKHAM ELIMINATE THE 120 POUND
SANDBAG BUT GAVE US THE 50 POUND SANDBAG WHICH WAS STILL
HARD FROM THE FEET OF THE CORDIALITY TESTS AND BANDED THE
I MEAN ERASED THE HEIGHT REQUIREMENTS FOR RECRUITS
AND ORDERED THAT 60 WOMEN BE HIRED BY THE END OF THE YEAR
JULY 2831 WOMEN ENTER THE 12 WEEK POLICE TRAINING PROGRAM
WHICH WAS MORE WHICH WAS MUCH MORE LONGER BECAUSE THE
TRAINING WAS MORE ON TRYING TO DISCOURAGE THE WOMEN HOPING
THAT WE WOULD RESIGN. >> THERE'S SO MUCH I CAN SAY
REGARDING ACADEMY TRAINING AND THE RESISTANCE THAT WE
RECEIVE BUT THAT WOULD TAKE UP ALL OF THIS TIME.
>> I CAN SAY THAT IT WAS THE HARDEST AND STRESSFUL
EXPERIENCE THAT MOST OF US HAD EVER BEEN THROUGH BUT WE MADE
IT LOOK FOR THE MOVIE IN THE BOOK.
>> LOOK FOR THE MOVIE IN THE BOOK THAT SURELY WILL BE
FORTHCOMING. >> I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE THIS
TIME TO THANK OUR FAMILIES AND FRIENDS WHO CAME OUT TO
SUPPORT US AND FOR ME IT WAS THE PRAYERS OF SO MANY THAT SAW
ME THROUGH. I THANK MY PASTOR RODNEY
LEGGETT WHO FOR BEING HERE MY CHILDREN AND IF I CAN
AND YOU'VE ALREADY ACKNOWLEDGED THE WOMEN BUT WE HAVE SOME OF
OUR MALE CLASSMATES WHO CAME TO SUPPORT US AND I WANT THEM TO
STAND DANNY MOORE. >> IF YOU SAY I CAN RENO
REPRESENTING JAMES MCKEEVER AND MICHAEL MCGILL.
ELLIOT AND WHAT WE WENT THROUGH ,WHAT WE WENT THROUGH IN THE
ACADEMY, THEY HAD TO GO THROUGH THE SAME THING.
>> A LOT OF THEM AND WHAT STAND UP?
MCKEEVER I WAS TELLING THEM HOW HARD IT WAS.
IT WASN'T HARD FOR ME BUT LOOK AT THEM.
IT SHOULDN'T HAVE BEEN HARD FOR BUT IT WAS HARD FOR US SO I
HAVE ONE MORE THING TO SAY. MONDAY WOULD BE MONDAY, JULY
28TH. THE WOMEN OF THE FIRST CLASS
THE PATROL OFFICERS WILL BE CELEBRATING AGAIN A 50 YEAR
ANNIVERSARY. >> THOSE OF US WHO WERE ABLE TO
RETIRED ARE VERY GRATEFUL TO THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT FOR OUR CAREERS AND MOST OF ALL FOR THAT
PENSION THAT COME SO FAITHFULLY EVERY MONTH.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. >> DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, COLLEAGUES.
TODAY WE HONOR A TRUE PILLAR OF OUR COMMUNITY CENTRAL DRUGSTORE
OR A LEGACY BUSINESS THAT HAS BEEN A CORNERSTONE AFTER
EXCELSIOR DISTRICT FOR OVER A CENTURY.
FOUNDED BY WILLIAM BRENNER IN 19 OH EIGHT, CENTRAL
DRUGSTORE HAS BEEN MORE THAN JUST A PHARMACY AND A GENERAL
STORE. >> IT HAS BEEN A PLACE OF
COMPASSION, CARE AND COMMUNITY .
IN THE 1940S D.A. TONELLI BEGAN HIS JOURNEY WITH CENTRAL
DRUGSTORE WHERE HE MET HIS FUTURE WIFE AND COWORKER ALICE
OWSLEY. >> DENAULT TOOK OVER THE STORE
IN 1965 AND DEDICATED HIS LIFE TO SERVING THE COMMUNITY UNTIL
HIS PASSING IN 1991. HIS LEGACY WAS CARRIED FORWARD
BY HIS SON JERRY, WHO STARTED WORKING AT THE STORE AS A YOUNG
GRADUATE IN 1978. TOGETHER WITH HIS MODERATE
OWSLEY WHO WORKED AT THE STORE UNTIL SHE WAS 96 YEARS OLD,
JERRY CONTINUED IT TO UPHOLD THE VALUES AND TRADITIONS THAT
MAKE CENTRAL DRUGSTORE A BELOVED INSTITUTION THE HEART
AND SOUL OF CENTRAL DRUGSTORE HAS ALWAYS BEEN ITS PEOPLE.
>> BESIDES JERRY AND L.C. DEDICATED EMPLOYEES LIKE KATHY
OR MARY TONY FERRETTI, AUGUSTINA ARIANO ROY HENDERSONS
AND PAUL TONY, TONY ALL HAVE BEEN IN TURN HAVE BEEN IN TURN,
HAVE THE HAPPY AND IN TURN GO AND THEY ALL HAVE BEEN VERY
IMPORTANT PART OF ITS OWN SUCCESS.
THEY HAVE SERVED MANY GENERATIONS OF SAN FRANCISCANS
KNOWING THEIR PATIENTS AND CLIENTS BY NAMES
PRESCRIPTIONS TO ORDER AND EVEN THEIR FAMILY MEMBERS.
AT TIME PEOPLE LIBRARIAN ELSIE AND ASTINA OF THEIR CLIENTS
PHARMACISTS AND OTHER TIME THEIR MEDICINE DELIVERY
DELIVERY PERSON AND EVEN SOMETIMES THEIR TEAR PRICE.
>> BUT ALWAYS THEIR VERY TRUSTED FRIEND.
THE STORE PROVIDED FREE MEDICAL ADVICE AND COUNSELOR COUNSELING
TO THOSE WITHOUT HEALTH INSURANCE AND LOW INCOME
FAMILIES EXTENDING THEIR IMPACT FAR BEYOND THE STORES WAS
CENTRAL DRUG STORES HAVE BEEN A STAUNCH SUPPORTER OF LOCAL
ORGANIZATIONS AND SCHOOL INITIATIVES THROUGHOUT DISTRICT
11. >> THEY HIRE LOCAL HIGH HIGH
SCHOOL STUDENTS SUPPORTED THE YMCA SUN STORY JERRY GARCIA DAY
AS A MEMBER OF THE RETAIL CREDIT UNION LOCAL 648 THEN SAW
THE EMPLOYEES RECEIVE GOOD PAY, HEALTH INSURANCE AND PENSION
PLANS. >> THE STORE'S LEGACY IS
REFLECTED IN MANY PEOPLE WHO HAVE WORKED THERE INCLUDING
CUSTOMERS, CHILDREN GRANDCHILDREN'S SOMEWHAT WHO
MET THEIR FUTURE SPOUSES WHILE WORKING AT THE STORE.
>> THE COUNTER AND THE COUNTER AND DISPENSARY AREA ARE ADORNED
WITH PHOTOS OF CENTRAL DRUGSTORES HISTORY CAPTURING
THE MILESTONES AND MEMORIES ITS LONGTIME CLIENTS AND EMPLOYEES.
>> THERE'S PHOTOS DEPICTING WEDDINGS, BABY ANNOUNCEMENTS.
BIRTHDAY GRADUATIONS SYMBOLIZE THE STORE'S DEEP CONNECTION TO
OUR COMMUNITY. >> THE STORE'S CONTRIBUTION TO
THE COMMUNITIES HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED WITH AWARDS FROM
CONGRESSWOMAN NANCY PELOSI AND FORMER SAN FRANCISCO
MAYOR AT THE. >> ON JULY 15, 2025 A CENTRAL
DRUGSTORE OPENED IT AND CLOSED IT ITS DOOR FOR THE LAST TIME
THOUGH THE BUY NEW ON LETTER OF CENTRAL DRUGSTORE WILL NO
LONGER LIGHT UP ITS LEGACY. >> IT'S IMMORTALIZED IT IN THE
HEARTS OF ALL THE COMMUNITY MEMBER IT HAS TOUCHED IN.
THE MURAL ON THE SIDE OF THE STORE'S BUILDING ON SANTA ROSA
AVENUE TITLED THE SAN FRANCISCO YOU SHOULD KNOW.
PAINTED BY CASITA EYES MURALIST IT FEATURED A CENTRAL
DRUGSTORES LOGO A TESTAMENT TO ITS ENDURING IMPACT THE SAN
FRANCISCO THAT WE SHOULD ALL KNOW.
CERTAINLY INCLUDING DEEPLY ROOTED INSTITUTION LIKE CENTRAL
DRUGSTORE. >> TO JERRY ALL THE EMPLOYEES
AND EVERYONE WHO HAS BEEN PART OF CENTRAL DRUGSTORE WHETHER
YOU ARE HERE TODAY OR NOT. CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR
REMARKABLE LEGACY AND YOUR WELL-DESERVED RETIREMENTS.
>> THANK YOU. FOR OVER 100 YEARS OF DEDICATED
SERVICES TO OUR COMMUNITY. YOUR SPIRITS OF SERVICE
INSPIRES US ALL AND I ALSO HAVE SOME THERAPEUTIC RIBBON LEIS
FOR JERRY AND THE OTHER EMPLOYEES WHO CAME TODAY.
THEY ARE EMBRACED BY DISTRICT 11 SENIORS FROM SLOUGH FOR THE
ELDERLY. >> SOME OF THEM HAVE GREATLY
BENEFITED FROM DIFFERENT SERVICES.
>> THEIR LOCAL PHARMACIES LIKE CENTRAL DRUGSTORE HAVE PROVIDED
AND THEY WANT TO SHARE THEIR GRATITUDE TO YOU AND WISH YOU
ALL A HAPPY RETIREMENT TOO. CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU. I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHEN FOR THOSE GLOWING WORDS I SAID AFTER LISTENING TO THAT I
WAS LIKE MAYBE I SHOULD JUST GO BACK AND REOPEN FOR ANOTHER
HUNDRED YEARS AND AND COME BACK IF I COULD.
I MEAN IT WOULD BE GREAT BUT AS TIME GOES BY AND YOU KNOW IT'S
BEEN A GREAT LEGACY I MEAN AT MY AGE IT'S TIME TO RETIRE.
I HAVE NOBODY BEHIND ME AS MY FATHER DID TO CONTINUE THE
BUSINESS. I'D LIKE TO AT THIS TIME THANK
THESE PEOPLE BEHIND ME TONY AUGUSTINA KATHY AND ROY.
>> MY BROTHER PAUL WAS SUPPOSED TO BE HERE BUT OH, WHY DON'T
YOU COME UP TODAY? >> ANYWAY, BUT ALSO PART OF MY
FAMILY. SARAH SITTING OVER HERE IF THEY
WOULD STAND. AND MY BEAUTIFUL WIFE NIKKI IS
HERE IF SHE WOULD STAND. >> BUT ONE LAST THING IS THAT
AS SUPERVISOR CHEN SAID THAT MY PARENTS MET AT THE PHARMACY
IN THE 1940S MY MOTHER STARTED WORKING THERE AT THE AGE OF 16
AND WORKED THERE UNTIL SHE WAS 96.
AND IF THEY HAD MET THERE I MEAN WE WE WOULDN'T BE STANDING
HERE TODAY. SO I JUST NEED TO MENTION THEM
MY COMMENTS DEANO AND ELSIE. GREAT PEOPLE AND ALSO THE
PEOPLE OF THE EXCELSIOR DISTRICT THAT HAVE SUPPORTED US
OVER ALL THESE YEARS AND IT WAS QUITE THE SENTIMENT CLOSING UP
AND ALL THE GOOD WISHES AND PEOPLE COMING OVER
AND THANKING US AND THE NOTES AND JUST ALL THE GRATITUDE IT
REALLY TOUCHES YOUR HEART AND MAKES YOU APPRECIATE NOT
ONLY OUR BUSINESS BUT THE PEOPLE OF THE EXCELSIOR
DISTRICT ARE WONDERFUL PEOPLE, HARDWORKING AND LOYAL.
THANK YOU. TODAY SUPERVISORS FOR YOUR TIME
. >> COME TO STAFF AND THANK YOU
SO MUCH
. >> ALL RIGHT.
NEXT UP WE HAVE DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM HONORED TO COMMEND DARLENE, OUR MENINO.
>> DARLENE, WHERE ARE YOU? THERE YOU ARE.
>> COME ON UP, PLEASE. >> ALL RIGHT, ENOUGH
SOCIALIZING. >> COME ON NOW.
BUT IN ALL SERIOUSNESS, DARLENE ,THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE
AND CONGRATULATIONS ON THE OCCASION OF YOUR RETIREMENT
FOLLOWING AN EXTRAORDINARY 50 YEAR CAREER ACROSS SAN
FRANCISCO'S LEGAL AND PUBLIC SERVICE SECTORS.
>> DARLENE IS A PROUD THIRD GENERATION SAN FRANCISCAN WHOSE
FAMILY LEGACY OF SERVICE RUNS DEEP THROUGH THE SAN FRANCISCO
FIRE AND POLICE DEPARTMENTS. HER GRANDFATHER MICKEY MCDONALD
AND FATHER MICHAEL GRIFFIN BOTH SERVED WITH DISTINCTION IN THE
SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT. HER BROTHER MICKEY GRIFFIN
ALONG WITH HIS TWIN SONS SEAN AND PATRICK PROUDLY SERVED
IN THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT.
>> NOW DARLENE BEGAN HER PROFESSIONAL CAREER AT THE
RAPPAPORT AND LOUIS LAW FIRM WHERE SHE SPENT TEN YEARS
HONING HER SKILLS IN LEGAL ADMINISTRATION.
SHE THEN SERVED 25 YEARS AS OFFICE MANAGER DEROZAN JOHNSON
WHERE SHE HELPED OVERSEE DAILY OPERATIONS AND PLAYED A KEY
ROLE IN THE FIRM'S SUCCESS AND STABILITY.
AND AFTER DECADES IN LEGAL ADMINISTRATION, DARLENE
THANKFULLY BROUGHT HER TALENTS TO THE SAN FRANCISCO EMPLOYEES
RETIREMENT SYSTEM OR S.F. SPURS WHERE SHE SPENT OVER 15 YEARS
SERVING THE PUBLIC AS FIRST, DARLENE SERVED IN DUAL ROLES AS
BOARD SECRETARY AND EXECUTIVE ASSISTANT TO BOTH THE CHIEF
EXECUTIVE OFFICER AND CHIEF INVESTMENT OFFICER.
SHE WAS INSTRUMENTAL IN SUPPORTING THE GOVERNANCE
AND OPERATIONAL LEADERSHIP OF ONE OF THE LARGEST PUBLIC
PENSION SYSTEMS IN THE ENTIRE COUNTRY.
HER RESPONSE ABILITIES RANGED FROM MANAGING HIGH LEVEL
EXECUTIVE COMMUNICATIONS AND COMPLEX SCHEDULES TO
ENSURING TRANSPARENT AND COMPLIANT BOARD MEETINGS.
DARLENE'S ATTENTION TO DETAIL HER PROFESSIONALISM, HER DEEP
INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE MADE HER AN INVALUABLE RESOURCE TO
BOTH THE EXECUTIVE LEADERSHIP AND TO THE BOARD MEMBERS.
IN ALL MY CONVERSATIONS WITH THE CURRENT BOARD MEMBERS
AND SOME PAST BOARD MEMBERS EACH ONE OF THEM SPECIFIC
PACIFICALLY NOTED HOW DISAPPOINTED THEY WERE THAT YOU
WERE RETIRING. >> MOSTLY OUT OF JOY AND OUT OF
GRATITUDE BUT ALSO OUT OF A KNOWLEDGE THAT IT WILL TAKE AN
IMMENSELY TALENTED AND IMMENSELY THOUGHTFUL
INDIVIDUAL TO COME EVEN CLOSE TO FILLING YOUR EXTREMELY LARGE
SHOES. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD.
DARLENE WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR DECADES OF SERVICE
AND FOR ALL THAT YOU HAVE GIVEN TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THE FLOOR IS YOURS. WELL, THIS WAS CERTAINLY AN
UNEXPECTED RECOGNITION AND I AM SO GRATEFUL AND THANKFUL FOR
THOSE KIND WORDS. SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND TWO OTHER
BOARD MEMBERS HERE I'VE HAD A WONDERFUL RUN WITH THE CITY
AND I WILL CHERISH ALL THE TIME AND I THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR. >> AND FINALLY WE HAVE DISTRICT
FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M
HONORED TO RECOGNIZE SOMEONE MANY OF US HERE KNOW NOT JUST
THROUGH HIS TITLES OR HIS JOB BUT THROUGH HIS CHARACTER, HIS
HEART AND HIS DEEP AND CONSISTENT COMMITMENT TO
OUR CITY. MOHAMMAD YASIR, WELCOME TO THE
STAGE. YASIR IS A PUBLIC SERVANT
IN THE TRUEST SENSE OF THE WORD.
>> HE'S NOT THE KIND OF PERSON WHO SEEKS THE SPOTLIGHT BUT
SHOULD. BUT TODAY THAT SPOTLIGHT SHOULD
BE ON HIM. >> IT'S ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL
THAT WE ARE HONORING YASIR TODAY THROUGH THE DURING THE
BOARD'S FIRST RECOGNITION OF SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH. HE HAS WORN MANY HATS FROM HIS
TIME WITH DPW TO A LABOR LEADER COMMUNITY ORGANIZER, FATHER
AND CAREGIVER. >> IN EACH ROLE HE HAS LED WITH
HUMILITY, RESOLVE AND GRACE AND HE PUTS HIS LIFE ON THE
LINE OFTEN EVERY NIGHT AS HE SERVES WITH DEMARK ADDRESSING
OUR FENTANYL CRISIS AND THE OPEN AIR DRUG MARKET IN OUR
STREETS. >> HIS JOURNEY BEGAN WITH HIS
FAMILY IMMIGRATED TO SAN FRANCISCO FROM PAKISTAN
IN 2002. LIKE SO MANY OF US WHO LOVE THE
CITY, HE'S NEVER LEFT. >> AND OVER THE PAST TWO
DECADES HE'S BUILT A LIFE ROOTED IN SERVICE TO HIS
FAMILY, TO HIS COWORKERS, TO HIS NEIGHBORHOOD AND TO THE
BROADER MUSLIM AND SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AT DPW HE AND HIS TEAM ARE WHAT THEY CALL THE GUARDIANS OF
THE PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY. THEY HELP KEEP OUR STREETS SAFE
AND ACCESSIBLE. THAT WORK OFTEN GOES UNSEEN BUT
WE CLEARLY FEEL THE IMPACT OF IT EVERY DAY.
>> WHEN HIS FATHER'S HEALTH BEGAN TO DECLINE, YASIR DID NOT
HESITATE. HE TOOK ON MULTIPLE JOBS TO
SUPPORT HIS FAMILY, EVEN DRIVING AN UBER AT NIGHT WHILE
CONTINUING HIS PUBLIC SERVICE DURING THE DAY.
>> THAT KIND OF SELFLESSNESS ISN'T SOMETHING THAT YOU LEARN
IN A CLASSROOM. IT COMES FROM VALUES PASSED
DOWN THROUGH GENERATIONS. >> VALUES THAT CONTINUE TO BE
EXEMPLIFIED BY HIS WORK. >> IT'S PART OF WHAT MAKES
YASIR SUCH A STEADY, GROUNDED LEADER IN EVERYTHING THAT HE
DOES. >> BEYOND CITY HALL, YASIR HAS
BEEN A POWERFUL ADVOCATE FOR WORKING PEOPLE.
HE SERVES AS THE FIRST MUSLIM AND SOUTH ASIAN CHAPTER
PRESIDENT OF PTA LOCAL 21 AND IS A COMMITTED MEMBER OF
SEIU 2015. WHETHER HE'S NEGOTIATING FOR
OTHERS ORGANIZING EDEN CELEBRATIONS ARE SHOWING UP FOR
STREET VENDORS. >> HE BRINGS HIS WHOLE SELF,
HIS CULTURE, HIS STORY AND HIS DEEP RESPECT FOR OTHERS.
I THINK HE BROUGHT HIS CHILD HERE AS WELL.
>> THAT'S IN WHAT MAKES YASIR EXCEPTIONAL ISN'T JUST WHAT HE
DOES. IT'S HOW HE DOES IT.
WITH A CALM PRESENCE WITH ASSURANCE WOULD THAT
UNMISTAKABLE SMILE? >> YASIR, THANK YOU FOR YOUR
SERVICE AND YOUR LEADERSHIP. YOU REMIND US THAT THE WORK OF
BUILDING A MORE JUST AND INCLUSIVE SAN FRANCISCO
HAPPENS NOT JUST THROUGH POLICY BUT THROUGH CARE AND COMMUNITY
AND THROUGH SHOWING UP. >> I WILL NEVER FORGET OUR
ABILITY TO DEBATE WHETHER PARKLAWN OR SHALIMAR IS BETTER
AND YOU ALWAYS MAKE ME EAT IT BACK ONE SO THE JURY IS OUT.
>> SO THANK YOU YASIR FOR ALL YOUR SERVICE.
AND WITH THAT I KNOW SUPERVISOR CHAN AND SEVERAL OTHER
COLLEAGUES WOULD LIKE TO SAY A COUPLE OF WORDS AND I SUBMIT
THE REST OF MY TIME. >> CONGRATULATIONS.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PERSON AND THANK YOU BOTH SO
MUCH. >> IT'S ALSO MY GREAT PRIVILEGE
TO HIGHLIGHT YASIR DEDICATED COMMUNITY MEMBER AND RESIDENT
OF EXCELSIOR FOR OVER 20 YEARS. HE IS A LOVING SON, CAREGIVER
AND PARENTS AS A STREET INSPECTOR AT DPW HE KEEPS THE
STREETS SAFE FOR RESIDENTS AND VISITORS.
HE IS A FEARLESS LEADER AND ACTIVE MEMBER OF SEIU 2015
AND LOCAL 21 WHERE LOCAL 21 HE WAS THE CHAPTER PERSON IN A FEW
OPERATIONS FOR OVER THREE YEARS.
SERVED ON MULTIPLE BARGAINING TEAMS AND THE POLITICAL ACTION
COMMITTEE IS ONE OF THE FAVORITE CENTERS ON THE BILL.
>> ON THE BULLHORN TO RALLY HIS COWORKERS.
I ALSO WANT TO APPRECIATE YOUR SERVICE WORK WITH THE COUNCIL
ON AMERICAN ISLAMIC RELATIONS WHERE HE HAS WORKED TO BRING
RAMADAN IFTAR MOVES TO THE CITY HALL AND HE'S ALSO THE BOARD
MEMBER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO MUSLIM COMMUNITY CENTER AND THE
SAN FRANCISCO ISLAMIC SCHOOL. SETTING AN EXAMPLE FOR YOUTH
AND HELPING THEM CONNECT TO THEIR IDENTITY AND CELEBRATE
THEIR BACKGROUNDS, IT IS CLEAR THAT YASIR LEADS WITH A
COMMITMENT TO EQUITY AND JUSTICE.
I'M VERY GLAD THAT YOU CONTINUE TO CALL DISTRICT 11 HOME.
THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR WORK FOR CREATING POSITIVE CHANGE IN THE
WORLD. >> THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT M.N. YASIR.
>> THERE'S THERE'S SO MUCH TO SAY BUT I WILL JUST SAY THAT
FOLKS IN THE MISSION HAVE APPRECIATED YOUR SERVICE ANY
TIME YOUR SHIPS HAVE BEEN THERE IN THE PAST SEVERAL YEARS.
YOU KNOW YOU'RE ALWAYS LOOKING OUT FOR OPPORTUNITIES OF
SOLIDARITY WHETHER IT'S ADVOCATING FOR YOUR COWORKERS
FOR BETTER BETTER CONDITIONS ESPECIALLY INSPECTORS WHO ARE
OUT ON THE STREET IN OUR VENDING ECOSYSTEM WHETHER IT IS
THE COMMUNITY ITSELF AND UNDERSTANDING YOU KNOW THAT
OUR SHARED KIND OF HUMANITY AND VULNERABILITY ESPECIALLY
IN THIS MOMENT IS ALSO AN OPPORTUNITY FOR BUILDING
BRIDGES ACROSS CULTURES, ACROSS LANGUAGES.
I THINK THAT'S BEEN FELT A LOT IN THE MISSION IN THE LATINO
COMMUNITY BY YOU. >> AND YOU KNOW, IT'S HARD TO
BELIEVE THAT YOU HAVE THE SAME 24 HOURS IN A DAY BEING A
FATHER AND AN ORGANIZER AND A MANAGER AND SO MUCH MORE A
COMMUNITY ADVOCATE, AN ADVOCATE FOR SOCIAL JUSTICE.
>> SO THIS IS THIS IS TRULY AN HONOR TO RECOGNIZE YOU
AND THANK YOU SO MUCH YASIR. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT BENJAMIN. >> YES, SIR.
I JUST WANT TO SAY ONE CONGRATULATIONS ON AN HONOR
WELL DESERVED. I THINK YOU ARE ONE OF THOSE
LEADERS THAT DON'T WALK AROUND ACTING LIKE YOU'RE THE BOSS BUT
DO EVERYTHING IN A MANNER WITH PROFESSIONALISM, RESPECTFUL BUT
ALSO VERY EFFECTIVE. AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
I'M EXCITED TO SEE YOU GET THIS HONOR THIS AFTERNOON
AND PARTICULARLY DURING THIS MONTH.
AND I JUST WANT TO CONTINUE TO SAY THAT ONE, YOU HAVE MY
SUPPORT ALWAYS IN THE WORK THAT YOU DO.
BUT I WANT TO MAKE SURE AND HOPE THAT YOU CONTINUE TO
BE THE ONE THAT IS OUT THERE ON THE FRONT LINES AND LEADERSHIP
BECAUSE IT'S IMPORTANT TO HAVE SOMEONE WHO REPRESENTS
EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO IN A LEADERSHIP ROLE.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH AND CONGRATULATIONS.
>> MANY CONGRATULATIONS YASIR AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> SUCH AN HONOR. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH, MAHMOOD, FOR CONSIDERING ME AND GIVING
ME THIS HONOR TO STAND HERE WITH MY COMMUNITY.
WE'RE VERY PROUD. >> IT IS IT'S BEEN EMOTIONAL.
>> IT'S BEEN A ROLLER COASTER WHAT YOU DESCRIBED AND THANK
YOU VERY MUCH. SURPRISE.
A CHANCE, SURPRISE. A FUTURE SURPRISE.
AND WALTER, FOR YOUR KIND WORDS.
IT MEANS A LOT. IT MEANS A LOT FOR A PERSON OF
COLOR TO GET RECOGNIZED AND ESPECIALLY WHEN YOU HAVE
MUHAMMAD IN YOUR NAME AND YOU REPRESENT THE IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITY. SO IT REALLY MEANS A LOT FOR
FOR ME AND SUPPORTING THE THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR ALL YOUR
WORK. >> AND I REMEMBER WHEN YOU
CALLED ME AND I REALLY FELT HONORED.
I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL YOUR WORK YOU DO OUT IN THE FIELD
FOR THE COMMUNITY. MY MY LEADERSHIP FROM LOCAL 21
BIANCA PAULINO HERE WITH ALL OUR UNION CHAMPS THANK YOU VERY
MUCH. MY DEPARTMENT LEADERSHIP IS
THERE WITH KHALID SHAW AND MY SUPERVISOR AND MY COWORKERS ARE
PRESENT HERE. >> MY MUSLIM COMMUNITY
LEADERSHIP HOLLY HEJAZI AND OTHERS MY SOUTH ASIAN
COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP. >> I REALLY WANT TO THANK YOU
ALL OF YOU MY FRIEND COMMISSIONERS FROM IMMIGRANT
RIGHTS COMMISSION, MY MISSION AND EXCELSIOR COMMUNITY
LEADERSHIP. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
AND MY FRIENDS FROM COLLEGE BOARD SCHOOL BOARD THANK YOU SO
VERY MUCH. I REALLY APPRECIATE IT AND I
REALLY FEEL AN HONOR TO TO BE HERE.
>> IT'S ALSO A SPECIAL AS I'M GETTING THIS AWARD FROM A
PERSON WHO LOOKED LIKE ME WE WE EAT SAME AND WE HAVE SO MANY
HOBBIES WE EXCHANGE AND IT IS REALLY AN HONOR TO BEING A
FIRST SOUTH ASIAN TO BE HERE TODAY TO GETTING THIS AWARD ON
THIS DAY WITH THE RESOLUTION. SO PLEASE YOU ALL LOVE OUR
CULTURE, OUR FOOD SO ALLOW US TO AND UH EAT BRIYANI WITH YOUR
HANDS. IT IS EVEN BETTER.
>> THANK YOU. ZORA AND THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR INCLUSION. THANK YOU FOR INCLUDING ME
IN THIS WORLD WHEN PEOPLE EXCLUDE OTHERS I ASSURE
EVERYONE THAT I WILL BE KEEP DOING MY WORK OUT IN THE FIELD
WITH THE COMMUNITY AS A PUBLIC SERVANT I ASSURE EVERYONE THEY
ARE. WE KEEP STANDING FOR VULNERABLE
PEOPLE IN OUR MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES.
I ASSURE THAT I'LL BE KEEP RAISING MY VOICE FOR WORKERS
RIGHTS. YOU WILL BE KEEP SEE ME OUTSIDE
AND IN ALL THE THREE HATS AND THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> I APPRECIATE THAT
. ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO
TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. PLEASE CALL ITEMS FOR AVON
AND 48 TOGETHER ITEMS 47 AND 48 WE'RE SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A
RESOLUTION ADOPTED ON MAY 20TH 2025 WHICH COMPRISES THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS TO CONVENE IN THE SETTING AS A COMMITTEE
OF THE WHOLE FOR A PUBLIC HEARING TO ESTABLISH RENEW
AND EXPAND THE PROPERTY BASED BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT
KNOWN AS THE DOGPATCH AND NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL
GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT. ITEM 48 ORDERS THE LEVY
AND COLLECTION OF ASSESSMENTS AGAINST PROPERTY LOCATED
IN THAT DISTRICT FOR A TERM OF 15 YEARS THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST
2040 AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THE PURPOSE OF THIS COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE IS TO HEAR
TESTIMONY ON THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THE PROPERTY
BASED BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT KNOWN AS THE DOGPATCH
AND NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT PURSUANT
TO THE BOARD'S RESOLUTION OF INTENTION ADOPTED MAY 20TH,
2025 AFTER THE PUBLIC HEARING IS CLOSED, THE DEPARTMENT OF
ELECTIONS WILL COUNT ALL BALLOTS SUBMITTED INCLUDED ANY
INCLUDING ANY ADDITIONAL BALLOTS RECEIVED DURING THE
BUSINESS HEARING TODAY AND SUBMIT THE TABULATION TO
THE BOARD LATER IN THE MEETING. MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC MAY VIEW
THE BALLOT TABULATION BY THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS ON THE
BASEMENT LEVEL OF CITY HALL IN ROOM 59 IF TABULATION OF THE
WEIGHTED BALLOTS SHOWS THE MAJORITY PROTEST.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WILL NOT APPROVE ESTABLISHMENT OF
THE DISTRICT OR IMPOSE THE ASSESSMENTS.
IF THERE IS NOT A MAJORITY PROTEST THEN THE BOARD MAY VOTE
TO ESTABLISH THE DISTRICT AND IMPOSE THE ASSESSMENTS.
A MAJORITY PROTEST WILL EXIST IF THE WEIGHTED BALLOTS
SUBMITTED IN OPPOSITION TO THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ASSESSMENT
DISTRICT EXCEED THE WEIGHTED BALLOTS SUBMITTED IN FAVOR OF
THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ASSESSMENT DISTRICT.
BALLOTS ARE WEIGHTED ACCORDING TO THE PROPOSED FINANCIAL
OBLIGATION OF EACH AFFECTED PROPERTY.
AFTER THE HEARING CLOSES THE BALLOTS WILL BE COUNTED AND I
BELIEVE WE HAVE ESTHER LEE HERE FROM PUBLIC WORKS.
OH, BUT FIRST WE HAVE SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH, PRESIDENT MELAMED AND COLLEAGUES, I JUST
WANT TO SPEAK BRIEFLY ABOUT SOMETHING THAT IS VERY VITAL TO
WHAT I BELIEVE OUR CITY AS WELL AS THE DOGPATCH AND PETRO HILL
COMMUNITY. THIS IS THE ONLY GREEN BENEFITS
DISTRICT IN ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO I BELIEVE.
AND IT'S A MODEL FOR HOW COMMUNITIES CAN LEAD THE WAY
IN MAKING OUR NEIGHBORHOODS GREENER, CLEANER AND MORE
LIVABLE FOR MAINTAINING PARKS AND SIDEWALKS TO PLANTING TREES
AND IMPROVING PUBLIC SPACES. THE DOG PATCH GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT HAS DELIVERED REAL RESULTS LED BY THE PEOPLE WHO
LIVE THERE AND SUPPORT OUR CLIMATE GOALS AND IMPROVES
QUALITY OF LIFE AND BUILDS COMMUNITY FROM THE GROUND UP.
AT A TIME WHEN WE NEED MORE GREEN INFRASTRUCTURE, CULTURE
AND EQUITY IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS, I'M GLAD THAT WE
ARE WORKING TO PROTECT AND EXPAND THE WORK OF WHAT THE
GBI REPRESENTS. AND OF COURSE NOT LETTING IT GO
. SO I JUST WANT TO SAY I'M PROUD
TO SUPPORT THE GBD AND I HOPE THAT YOU ALL WILL SUPPORT IT AS
WELL. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON.
AND NOW AS JULIE THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK.
I AM ESTHER LEE, GOVERNMENT AFFAIRS LIAISON WITH SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS. I'M JOINED TODAY BY JAMES
CASSEL. PUBLIC WORKS COMMITTEE PROGRAMS
SUPPORT SPECIALIST AND LIAISON TO THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
WITH ME ALSO IS SHAWN TROTMAN, BOARD PRESIDENT OF THE DOGPATCH
AND NORTHWEST PORTRAYAL HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
AS THE OVERSIGHT AGENCY BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT PUBLIC WORKS EMPLOYEES
PARTNER WITH AMAZING STAFF VOLUNTEER BOARD OF DIRECTORS
AND NEIGHBORHOOD VOLUNTEERS TO ENHANCE OPEN SPACES, PARKS
AND PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAYS IN THE DOGPATCH AND NORTHWEST POTRERO
HILL NEIGHBORHOODS. I'M VERY FORTUNATE TO HAVE
WORKED ON THE GPD RENEWAL LEGISLATION AND TO BE A
RESIDENT OF THE DOGPATCH WHERE MY FAMILY, FRIENDS
AND NEIGHBORS BENEFIT FROM THE BEAUTIFUL OPEN SPACES PARKS,
LANDSCAPING AND THE CARING COMMUNITY CREATED BY THE GREEN
BENEFIT DISTRICT. >> MANY THINGS TO SUPERVISOR
SYMON WALTON AND THE TEN LEGISLATIVE AIDES WHO SUPPORT
OF THE GUARD HAS BEEN UNWAVERING.
ALSO A LOT OF THE HEAVY LIFTING FOR THIS RENEWAL CAME FROM CITY
EMPLOYEES WORKING WITH US TO NAVIGATE THE NUANCES OF
MANAGING A SPECIAL BENEFIT DISTRICT THAT IS GOVERNED BY
STATE AND LOCAL LAWS. >> MUCH GRATITUDE TO CITY
ATTORNEY MANU PRADHAN ALICE LAW PRISCILLA TORV FROM THE
DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS CHRISTINE MCNAIRY FROM THE
ASSESSOR'S OFFICE AND JAMES WHITAKER FROM THE COMPTROLLER'S
OFFICE AND OF COURSE THE CLERKS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THANK YOU FOR KEEPING US ON TRACK WITH THE MANY LEGISLATIVE
DEADLINES AND ACTIONS NEEDED TO RISE TO TODAY'S HEARING.
>> I ALSO WANT TO GIVE MY HEARTFELT GRATITUDE TO THE OPW
TEAM. CHRIS COURAGEOUS AND JACKIE
HAZELWOOD FOR PAVING THE WAY FOR COMMUNITIES LIKE DOGPATCH
AND NORTH WEST POTRERO HILL GUIDI TO CREATE A PATH TO
PRIORITIZING NEIGHBORHOOD FOCUSED SERVICES LIKE URBAN
GREENING, LANDSCAPE CLEANING, SAFETY, GRAFFITI ABATEMENT
AND THE REVITALIZATION OF OPEN SPACES THROUGH PUBLIC PRIVATE
PARTNERSHIPS THAT ARE CBDS AND GUIDES JACKIE AND CHRIS THE
OPW TEAM TRULY ARE THE OGS OF CBD'S ANTI-BDS.
>> I'D LIKE TO ASK SEAN CHOSEN BOARD PRESIDENT OF THE DOGPATCH
AND NORTHWEST PORTUGAL HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT TO COME
TO THE PODIUM TO PRESENT ON THE IMPACT OF THE GBD AND WHAT
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. >> AS SHE JOINS ME MY LAST
WORDS OF GRATITUDE ARE TO THE GBD NONPROFIT.
>> THANK YOU GBD BOARD OF DIRECTORS FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP
AND VISION. >> AND THANK YOU FOR NOT
ALLOWING EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR DONOVAN LACEY TO CHANGE HIS
ANNUAL VACATION TRIP TO BE HERE IN PERSON.
TRUST IS ESSENTIAL IN A HEALTHY AND PRODUCTIVE RELATIONSHIP
BETWEEN A BOARD, AN EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR AND THE ORGANIZATION'S
EFFECTIVENESS TO ACHIEVE THE ORGANIZATION'S GOALS
AND MISSION. IT'S GREAT TO SEE THAT THE
ORGANIZATION WILL STRENGTH AND DEMONSTRATION.
IT'S GREAT TO SEE THAT ORGANIZATIONAL STRENGTH
AND DEMONSTRATED WITH THE DVD. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK DONOVAN
LACY FOR HIS TIRELESS WORK ON THE GBD.
>> IF YOU'VE MET HIM HE'S LIKE A SOLAR POWERED ENERGIZER
BUNNY. HE NEVER STOPS WORKING AND I
THINK WE MOST LIKELY OWE HIS FAMILY AN APOLOGY BECAUSE I CAN
GUARANTEE DONOVAN IS LIVESTREAMING THIS HEARING
RIGHT NOW INSTEAD OF ENJOYING HIS FAMILY VACATION.
JIM AND I WILL BE AVAILABLE AFTER SEAN'S PRESENTATION TO
ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE.
>> SO GOOD AFTERNOON. >> I BROUGHT A OUR PRESENTATION
SO GIVE ME A MOMENT WHEN I TALK .
>> SO OKAY WELL GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
MY NAME IS SEAN FRITZ AND I AM THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF
THE DOGPATCH IN NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT. BEFORE WE GET STARTED I WANT TO
THANK ALSO A FEW PEOPLE FIRST OF ALL THANK YOU TO THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS ESPECIALLY SUPERVISOR WALTON.
THANK YOU TO THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS ESPECIALLY ESTHER
AND JAMIE ARE HERE TODAY AND THANK YOU TO OF COURSE OUR
NEIGHBORS IN OUR COMMUNITY FOR THE SUPPORT OVER THE PAST TEN
YEARS AND THE EXCITEMENT AS WE HOPEFULLY ENTER INTO ANOTHER 15
YEARS. >> SO THIS SLIDE HOLDS A LIE.
YOU'LL SEE ON THE LEFT HAND SIDE A FEW EXAMPLES OF BEFORE
AND AFTER PHOTOS OF OUR PROJECTS.
>> OUR PROJECTS RANGE FROM ANYTHING FROM SMALL TO LARGE
THE TOP ONE YOU SEE WHAT WE'VE DONE WITH AN OVERGROWN SIDEWALK
WHERE WEEDS HAVE TAKEN OVER AND HOW WE'VE ENHANCED IT
AND THEN WE ALSO HAVE SOME FREEWAY OVERPASSES AND SIDE
LOTS TO THE FREEWAYS THAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO ENHANCE ON THE
RIGHT SIDE ARE A FEW STATS THAT I'D LIKE TO HIGHLIGHT AND PART
OF THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT WHAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO BEEN
ABLE TO ACHIEVE IN THE PAST TEN YEARS WHEN WE WERE FIRST
FOUNDED ABOUT TEN YEARS AGO THERE ONLY TWO ACRES OF PUBLIC
GREEN SPACE IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD WITH THE BEAUTY WE HAVE MORE
THAN TRIPLED THAT AMOUNT OF SPACE TO SEVEN ACRES IN HOW
HAVE WE DONE THAT? WHAT'S OUR FUNDING LOOK LIKE?
WELL THROUGH OUR ANNUAL PROPERTY ASSESSMENTS OF ABOUT
$5 MILLION WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO RAISE AN ADDITIONAL $6 MILLION
THROUGH PRIVATE DONATIONS, GRANTS ETC. SO THAT'S ABOUT 21
MILLION DOLLARS DIRECTLY INVESTED INTO OUR COMMUNITY BUY
IN THROUGH THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT SINCE OUR INCEPTION.
LIKE I MENTIONED, WE WERE ESTABLISHED IN 2016 ABOUT TEN
YEARS AGO AND I'M HERE TODAY TO PURSUE ANOTHER 15 YEAR TERM TO
TAKE US THROUGH 2040 AS PART OF THIS RENEWAL WE'VE DECIDED TO
SLIGHTLY INCREASE OUR BOUNDARIES WHICH I'LL TOUCH ON
A LITTLE BIT MORE IN A LATER SLIDE.
BUT ULTIMATELY I'M HERE BECAUSE WE WANT TO CONTINUE THE GREAT
WORK THAT WE'VE DONE AND OVER THE NEXT SEVERAL MINUTES I'LL
TAKE YOU THROUGH HOW WE CREATE ,MAINTAIN AND ENHANCE OUR
PUBLIC SPACES, HOW WE ENGAGE OUR COMMUNITY AND HOW WE
ACTIVATE OUR PARKS. SO HOW DO WE ENGAGE OUR
COMMUNITY? WE CONSISTENTLY HOLD VOLUNTEER
EVENTS. >> THIS INCLUDES PLANTING DAYS
WHICH ON THE BOTTOM TO PICTURES YOU CAN SEE THAT THEY ARE VERY
WELL ATTENDED BY OUR COMMUNITY AND THEN WE ALSO HOLD EVENTS
WITH OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATIONS.
THERE'S A LOT OF ACRONYMS ON THERE.
DOGPATCH NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION AND POTRERO
BOOSTERS NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION AND ONE OF THE
EVENTS THAT WE PARTNER WITH DEANA WITH THE DOGPATCH
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION IS OUR ANNUAL HALLOWEEN SLOW STREET.
WE CALL IT A SPOOKY STROLL. WE WORK ON CLOSING A COUPLE
BLOCKS OF OUR SLOW STREET IN DOGPATCH SO KIDS CAN TRICK
OR TREAT AND ROAM FREELY AND THAT'S THE BOTTOM LEFT
PHOTO THERE. AND THEN ANOTHER WAY THAT WE
ACTIVATE OUR PARKS IN THESE SPACES THAT WE CREATE IS
THROUGH OUR ANNUAL DOGPATCH MUSIC SERIES.
WE ARE DOING IT AGAIN THIS FALL.
IT'S FOUR SEPARATE DAYS IN THE FALL AND ANOTHER EVENT CLOSER
TO EARTH DAY IN THE SPRING WHERE WE HAVE A BAND, A LIVE
BAND PEOPLE COME AND ENJOY THESE SPACES THAT WE'VE CREATED
AND THAT'S THAT TOP LEFT PHOTO THERE.
LOCAL BUSINESSES COME OUT. WE HAVE A FEW MUSEUMS HERE
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD AND IT'S PRETTY WELL ATTENDED.
>> ANOTHER MAJOR PART OF WHAT WE DO IN THE GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT IS MAINTENANCE. WE WORK WITH A LANDSCAPE
MAINTENANCE CONTRACTOR PROVIDING PARK AND OPEN SPACE
MANAGEMENT. >> THIS INCLUDES WEEDING,
PRUNING, WATERING, IRRIGATION MAINTENANCE ETC. AMONG OTHER
THINGS AND THEN AND OFTEN OVERLOOKED BUT IMPORTANT PART
OF WHAT WE DO IS DOG WASTE MAINTENANCE AND PROVIDING
DOGGIE BAGS TO OUR COMMUNITY IN OUR PARKS.
>> THE FUN FACT SINCE THE INCEPTION OF THE DVD WE HAVE
DISTRIBUTED OVER 58,000 DOGGIE BAGS.
>> IT'S ABOUT 160 A DAY IF YOU DO THE MATH AND THAT IS A LOT
OF DOG. ANOTHER ASPECT I WANT TO TALK
TO YOU ABOUT ABOUT THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT AND WHAT WE DO
WE CONTRACT WITH ANOTHER VENDOR AND PART OF WHAT WE DO IS
REMOVE LITTER GARBAGE AND MAKE SURE OUR PARKS AND OUR PLACES,
OUR SIDEWALKS ARE FREE OF LITTER, THEY'RE CLEAN, THEY'RE
ACCESSIBLE AND OUR NEIGHBORS ARE ABLE TO USE THEM.
WE SPARKLING FURNITURE WE MAKE SURE EVERYTHING IS WORKING,
LIGHTING ETC. AND IN DOING THIS WE SUPPLEMENT DPW EFFORTS FOR
CLEANER SPACES FOR ILLEGAL DUMPING, FOR OVERFLOWING
GARBAGE CANS. AND THEN ANOTHER ASPECT OF WHAT
WE DO IS GRAFFITI ABATEMENT. WITHIN TWO DAYS OF IDENTIFYING
GRAFFITI IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD WE HAVE IT REMOVED AND THEN ON TO
THE EXCITING PART OF WHAT THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT DOES WE
AS PART OF THE NEXT 15 YEARS WE JUST WANT TO CONTINUE
DEVELOPING NEW PROJECTS. WE HAVE A VERY ROBUST PROJECT
PIPELINE. WE HAVE A LONG LIST PROBABLY
OVER 20 DIFFERENT PROJECTS BIG AND SMALL THAT WE WOULD LIKE TO
CONTINUE WORKING ON. THEY COULD BE ANYTHING FROM
SIDEWALK GARDENS, NEW LIGHTING BENCHES, THEY COULD BE
COMMUNITY GARDENS AND SO THAT IS WHY I'M HERE TODAY ON THIS
SLIDE I MENTIONED EARLIER AS PART OF THIS RENEWAL THIS NEW
CHARTER FOR 15 YEARS WE ARE SLIGHTLY EXPANDING OUR
BOUNDARIES ON THE LEFT SIDE AND BLUE YOU WILL SEE THE
EXISTING DOGPATCH BOUNDARY AND ON HIGHLIGHT IN THE BOTTOM
LEFT IS THE YELLOW IS THE EXPANSION BOUNDARY AND DOGPATCH
ON THE RIGHT SIDE THE GREEN IS OUR EXISTING NORTHWEST POTRERO
HILL BOUNDARIES AND ON THE BOTTOM IN ORANGE IS OUR
PROPOSED EXPANSION. OUR RENEWAL COMMITTEE SPENT
ABOUT SIX MONTHS DISCUSSING EXPANSION.
DO WE WANT TO EXPAND SHOULD WE EXPAND IS A SUSTAINABLE IS A
VIABLE AND MOST IMPORTANTLY ARE WE WANTED THERE?
DO OUR NEIGHBORS WANT US TO EXPAND INTO THESE AREAS
AND THAT IS HOW WE ENDED UP CHOOSING THESE DIFFERENT
PARCELS TO EXPAND INTO THIS SLIDE SHOWS ALL OF OUR
DIFFERENT PROJECTS PARKS THEY RANGE AGAIN FROM BIG OR SMALL
SOME OF THESE WERE EXISTING MORE THAN TEN YEARS AGO
AND GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT HAS COME IN AND HELPED ENHANCE THEM
AND MAINTAIN THESE PROJECTS BUT REALLY SOMETHING I WANT TO
HIGHLIGHT IN THIS SLIDE IS FREEWAYS.
>> IT IS RARELY LOOKED AT AS A GOOD THING OR CONSIDERED A GOOD
THING WHEN FREEWAYS RUN THROUGH YOUR NEIGHBORHOOD AND IN OUR
AREA WE ACTUALLY HAVE TWO FREEWAYS.
THE GREAT THING THAT THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT DISTRICT HAS
BEEN ABLE TO ACHIEVE IS IS TURN THAT INTO A GOOD THING.
>> A LOT OF THIS LAND ADJACENT TO THE FREEWAYS IS UNABLE TO BE
DEVELOPED AND INSTEAD OF MAKING IT A PLACE TO AVOID WE HAVE
BEEN ABLE TO CREATE PARKS, CREATE THEM SPACES THAT PEOPLE
WANT TO ACTUALLY GATHER IN AND MAKE THEM FEEL WELCOME INTO OUR
COMMUNITY. YOU'LL SEE JUST IF YOU LOOK AT
THE FREEWAYS JUST HOW MANY OF OUR PARKS ARE DIRECTLY ADJACENT
TO THEM AND OF COURSE BUDGET. THIS IS A SNAPSHOT OF THIS
YEAR'S BUDGET YOU'LL SEE OUR FISCAL BUDGET IS ABOUT
$900,000, 75% OF WHICH IS SPENT ON MAINTENANCE AND CAPITAL
IMPROVEMENTS. SO WE TRY TO SPEND AS MUCH AS
WE POSSIBLY CAN DIRECTLY INTO WHAT OUR NEIGHBORS AND OUR
COMMUNITY CAN CAN SEE IN REAL TIME AND AGAIN TO TIE BACK INTO
THAT FIRST SLIDE, THIS IS OUR BUDGET, OUR ASSESSMENTS, WE
TAKE OUR ASSESSMENT DOLLARS AND WE TRY TO TYPICALLY TRIPLE
THAT AMOUNT OF MONEY THROUGH GRANTS AND PRIVATE DONATIONS.
>> AND FINALLY WE WANTED TO SHOW OFF SOME BEAUTIFUL
PICTURES OF OUR PARKS AND WHAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO ACHIEVE OVER
THE PAST TEN YEARS. BUT OVERALL, YOU KNOW, I'M HERE
BECAUSE I'M VERY PROUD TO BE PART OF THE GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT AND THE WORK THAT'S BEEN DONE OVER THE PAST TEN
YEARS AND I HOPE WE GET TO CONTINUE OUR POSITIVE MOMENTUM
FOR ANOTHER 15 AND I'M HERE TO TO ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANY COLLEAGUES IN THE QUEUE SO I THINK THAT WE
CAN GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. MADAM CLERK GREAT.
LET'S OPEN PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THIS HEARING AND EVERY SPEAKER
WILL HAVE TWO MINUTES AND THIS IS NOT GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
THIS IS JUST PUBLIC COMMENT ON THESE ON THESE TWO ITEMS.
>> THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT. HOLD ON A MINUTE.
IS THIS PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THE PUBLIC OR WHAT?
>> I WANT TO KNOW, JEFFREY, THIS IS PUBLIC COMMENT FOR THE
GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT ONLY. WELCOME TO THE FIRST SPEAKER.
>> THIS ONE YES, HI. MY NAME IS CATHERINE DOMINE.
I HAVE LIVED IN DOGPATCH FOR NEARLY 30 YEARS AND HAVE
WATCHED THE COMMUNITY TRANSFORM FROM 800 NEIGHBORS AND 2000
CLIMBING TO OVER 6000 TODAY DOGPATCH WELCOMES GROWTH
AND CHANGE, ESPECIALLY GRASSROOTS NEIGHBORHOOD DRIVEN
PROJECTS. WE ALSO RECOGNIZE WHAT IT TAKES
TO BRING TOGETHER AN EXTREMELY MULTICULTURAL NEIGHBORHOOD MADE
UP OF NEWBORNS, SENIORS AND EVERYONE IN BETWEEN THE GPD
TICKS ALL THESE BOXES A UNIQUE HOMEGROWN GREEN CBD COMBINING
GREEN SPACE STREET ACTIVATIONS AND COMMUNITY BUILDING ALL
ADMINISTERED BY VOLUNTEER BOARD MEMBERS LIKE ME.
WE HAVE ACCOMPLISHED TOO MUCH IN THE PAST TEN YEARS BUT WITH
A STILL GROWING COMMUNITY AND THE GB SUPPORT IT IS MORE
IMPORTANT THAN EVER BEFORE. WE URGE YOUR SUPPORT
AND RENEWAL. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER ON THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
>> YEAH THAT GREEN WITHIN. >> HEAR ANYTHING ABOUT GROWING
FOOD IN THE PARKS? >> WELL OKAY KEEP GOING.
YOU KNOW YOU JUST FEEDING A FOOD FEEDING THE AGENDA OF
PEDOPHILES. THE MORE YOU WATCH THEM THE
MORE YOU BECOME. WANT US TO WATCH OUT?
>> ALL RIGHT. ALL RIGHT.
SO THAT THE BOARD DOES NOT ENDORSE THAT COMMENT.
>> BUT LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
HI, MY NAME'S SUSAN HASLUCK. I'VE LIVED IN DOGPATCH FOR
ABOUT 29 YEARS AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THE GBD IS THE MOST
POSITIVE IMPACT THAT HAS HAPPENED IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
THE WHOLE TIME I'VE LIVED THERE AND THAT'S IN ADDITION TO THE
TIP LINE. SO I JUST HOPE THAT YOU SUPPORT
THIS AS WE DO. THANKS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO, I'M RICHARD ROMERO. I MOVED INTO THE SAN FRANCISCO
AREA ABOUT FOUR YEARS AGO AND ONE OF THE FIRST THINGS I
DID IS I MET WITH MY SUPERVISOR WALTON AND ASKED THEM WHAT
ORGANIZATIONS SHOULD I BE INVOLVED WITH?
AND HE GAVE ME A LIST AND AS A RESULT OF THAT I LEARNED ABOUT
THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT AND I WAS TOTALLY AMAZE IS THAT
THIS CONCEPT OF TAKING UNUSABLE SPACE THAT IS BEEN NEGLECTED
AND TURNED INTO BEAUTIFUL USABLE SPACE FOR PEOPLE TO
ENJOY IS AN INCREDIBLE IDEA AND EVERYONE SHOULD BE DOING IT
. I DO WANT TO SAY THAT THE
COMMUNITY IN WHICH WE THE DISTRICT SERVES HAVE REALLY
TAKEN A REAL GOOD VIEW OF THE OF THE ACCOMPLISHMENTS THAT
THESE DIFFERENT AND SPACE HAVE BEEN TRANSFORMED INTO.
>> I WOULD ENCOURAGE YOU TO TO GO AND VISIT SOME OF THESE
AND YOU WOULD NOT BELIEVE HOW MUCH OF AN IMPACT IT MAKES
IN THE COMMUNITY. I HAVE FOUR GRANDCHILDREN
AND YOU KNOW, LIVING IN AN AREA WHERE THERE'S DEVELOPMENT GOING
ON ALL THE TIME. >> THERE ISN'T VERY MANY OPEN
GREEN SPACES FOR THE KIDS TO TO USE.
SO I WANT TO SAY THAT YOUR SUPPORT WILL MEAN A LOT TO THE
TO OUR COMMUNITY AND THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> YES, I'M ONE OF THE OLDER ONES SHE REPRESENTED WHEN THEY
TAKE CARE OF THE LITTLE ONES AND THE BIG ONES AND EVERYBODY
I'M GOING TO TALK TO YOU ABOUT NORTHWEST POTRERO IN 19 54,
CALTRANS DIVIDED NORTHWEST POTRERO INTO BYE BYE INTO TWO
BY STATE HIGHWAY ONE AND ONE. >> SINCE THEN THE NEIGHBORS
HAVE HAD TO DEAL WITH AND WORKED TO IMPROVE THE GREEN
SPACES THAT PREVIOUSLY HELD HOMES.
>> MAY I ASK YOU TO SPEAK MORE DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE?
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
I LIKE THAT. OKAY.
BENCHES GARDEN PLOT AND PLAZA FALL FALLEN BRIDGE PARK VERMONT
GATEWAY IN ECHO ECHO PATCH AND THE THE PETRO GATEWAY ARE
OPEN SPACES ON CALTRANS PROPERTY THAT WERE EITHER
CREATED BY OR UPGRADED BY THE G B D SINCE 2015 THAT'S THOSE ARE
SOME THINGS YOU SEE WE CONTINUE WE NEED TO CONTINUE MAINTENANCE
AND TO CONTINUE TO IMPROVE THESE OPEN SPACES PARTICULARLY
AROUND THE FREEWAY. THESE AREAS ARE USED BY THE
COMMUNITY FOR PODUNK BLOCK PARTIES, EGGPLANTS AND ENJOYING
THE BEAUTY OF THE OUTDOORS. >> IN ADDITION THE GPD TAKES
CARE OF ADDING TREES TO SIDEWALK GARDENS.
THE GPD IS AN ELECTED BOARD OF DIRECTORS.
DECISIONS ARE MADE BY VOTING AT OPEN MEETINGS BRING IN BRINGING
DRAMATIC DEMOCRATIC PROCESSES INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD PROVIDES
A VALUABLE SOCIAL CONTROL AND SALARY LOCAL FUNDING LOCAL
GOVERNANCE ADVOCACY AND VOLUNTEERISM WELL CREATE A
BEAUTIFUL GREEN OPEN SPACES IN NORTH POTRERO AND THAT'S
WHAT WE'D LIKE YOU TO SUPPORT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON CHAIR
MANAGEMENT AND SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS REBECCA GROVES
AND I'M A PROPERTY OWNER IN DOGPATCH AND A VOLUNTEER
ELECTED BOARD MEMBER OF THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
I'M HERE TODAY TO EXPRESS MY ENTHUSIASTIC SUPPORT FOR
RENEWING THE GBD FOR ANOTHER 15 YEAR TERM.
>> I BECAME AN OWNER A HOMEOWNER IN DOGPATCH FOUR
YEARS AGO AFTER HAVING RENTED FOR MANY YEARS IN THE MISSION
WHEN MY DAUGHTER STARTED PRESCHOOL IN 2020.
WE BIKED HER TO SCHOOL IN DOGPATCH AND FOUND AN
INCREDIBLY WARM AND VIBRANT FAMILY NEIGHBORHOOD SCENE AT
THE WOODS YARD PARK ON 22ND STREET.
A PARK CREATED AND CARED FOR BY THE GBD.
>> WE WERE LUCKY ENOUGH TO SPEND THE PANDEMIC SOCIALIZING
DAILY OUTSIDE WITH OTHER FAMILIES BECAUSE THE GBD HAD
CREATED AND CONTINUED TO MAINTAIN THIS LEAFY GREEN PARK
AND PLAYGROUNDS WHERE THE KIDS AND PARENTS ALL WANTED TO
GATHER TOGETHER. >> NOW I AM FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO
OWN A HOME ON MINNESOTA STREET JUST UP THE STREET FROM WOODS
YARD PARK. THE SIDEWALK ON OUR STREET IS
PLANTED WITH CALIFORNIA NATIVES COURTESY OF THE GBD.
>> I'M SO THANKFUL THAT WE HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO DIRECTLY
SUPPORT THE SERVICES OF THE GBD TO ENSURE THAT OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
GREEN SPACES ARE WELL-DESIGNED, PROPERLY MAINTAINED
AND ACTIVATED WITH COMMUNITY EVENTS THAT OUR WHOLE FAMILY
ENJOYS. I KNOW THAT OUR ASSESSMENT
DOLLARS IMPROVE NOT ONLY OUR DAILY QUALITY OF LIFE OUTDOORS
IN OUR COMMUNITY AND THE SUCCESS OF OUR LOCAL BUSINESSES
BUT ALSO THE OPPORTUNITIES AND THRIVING OF THE DISTRICT AS
A WHOLE. THANK YOU FOR SUPPORTING THE
RENEWAL THE GBD. I HOPE THAT ITS SUCCESS CAN
SERVE AS A MODEL FOR OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER ON THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT RESIDENT
GENTLEMAN SUPERVISORS I'M J.R. HEPLER, PRESIDENT OF THE PATROL
BOOSTERS NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION.
>> I WANT TO UNDERLINE A LITTLE BIT FURTHER THE QUESTION OF WHY
AGREED TO BEGIN WITH. >> WE'VE TALKED ABOUT THE
FREEWAYS AND THE CALTRANS RIGHTS OF WAY THAT SURROUND
THEM. WE'RE ALSO A NEIGHBORHOOD.
THIS IS ENDEMIC TO THE SOUTHEAST SECTOR OF THE CITY
THAT'S POST-INDUSTRIAL AND HAS POST-INDUSTRIAL INFRASTRUCTURE
THAT'S HISTORICALLY BEEN UNDER INVESTIGATION, UNDER INVESTED
IN. WE HAVE CALTRAIN AND THE
CALTRAIN RATES AWAY AND WE HAVE A PLETHORA OF UNACCEPTED
STREETS, PAPER STREETS AND UNACCEPTED CITY RIGHTS
AWAY. PUT TOGETHER THIS IS A RECIPE
FOR BLIGHT IN ABOUT A DECADE AGO THINGS WERE NOT LOOKING
VERY GOOD. HENCE A GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
AND IN THE INTERVENING TEN YEARS THAT GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT HAS WORKED WITH TRANSPARENCY AND FLEXIBILITY.
I'VE LIVED IN THE BENEFIT DISTRICT.
I'VE NEVER BEEN ON THE BOARD. I CURRENTLY DON'T LIVE IN THE
BENEFIT DISTRICT BUT I DO KNOW THAT IT HAS WORKED WELL WITH
OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD GROUPS THAT IT'S BEEN WILLING TO TAKE ON
NEW CHALLENGES AND NEW PROJECTS IN COLLABORATION WITH THE
BROADER COMMUNITY. >> AND SO NOW WE HAVE THESE
IMPROVEMENTS THOSE IMPROVEMENTS NEED MAINTENANCE.
>> THERE'S STILL MORE WORK TO BE DONE BECAUSE THOSE FREEWAYS,
THOSE UNACCEPTED STREETS THEY HAVEN'T GONE AWAY AND WE NEED
TO CONTINUE TO CHIP AWAY AT THOSE MARGINAL USES AND MAKE
THEM AMENITIES FOR THE COMMUNITY.
SO I'M ASKING YOU TO PLEASE REVIEW THE GREEN BENEFIT
DISTRICT FOR ANOTHER 15 YEARS SO THAT WE CAN CONTINUE THE
GOOD WORK THAT THE BENEFIT DISTRICT HAS DONE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ALL RIGHT. THIS IS THE LAST CALL FOR ANY
SPEAKERS ON THE GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
>> ALL RIGHT. SEEING NONE, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND THE HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
THE BALLOTS WILL BE TABULATED AND WE WILL RETURN TO ITEM
NUMBER 48 AFTER THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS REPORTS THE
RESULTS. MEMBERS MAY PROVIDE ADDITIONAL
COMMENTS AT THAT TIME BUT BEFORE WE CONSIDER THE
RESOLUTION TO ESTABLISH MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 40
TWO. >> ADAM, 42, WAS REFERRED
WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE. >> IT'S A RESOLUTION TO OPPOSE
CALIFORNIA STATE SENATE BILL NUMBER 79 HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
TRANSIT ORIENTED DEVELOPMENT INTRODUCED BY SENATOR SCOTT
WIENER UNLESS AMENDED TO GIVE LOCAL GOVERNMENTS ADEQUATE
ABILITY TO FORMULATE LOCAL PLANS THROUGH ITS LOCAL
LEGISLATIVE PROCESS. >> SUPERVISOR.
>> THANK YOU. PRESENT AMENDMENT COLLEAGUES.
I DO ACTUALLY WANT TO FIRST THANK THE LAND USE COMMITTEE
FOR ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW, SENDING THIS TO FULL BOARD SO THAT WE
CAN HAVE THIS DISCUSSION HERE TODAY.
SO FOR THAT I AM GRATEFUL TO HAVE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO ALLOW
THIS TO BE VOTED ON. >> I, I WANT TO SAY THAT THIS
IS I WANT TO START WITH HOW THAT THIS IS PERSONAL FOR ME
AND THEN I'LL GO INTO A LITTLE BIT OF THE POLICY DISCUSSION
HERE AROUND SB 79. AGAIN, THIS IS NOT TO OPPOSE 79
WHATEVER. HOWEVER ULTIMATELY IS BUT IT'S
REALLY TO OPPOSE IT AS IT CURRENTLY WRITTEN.
>> AND ONE FLASHING POINT THAT I WANT TO RAISE FOR YOU IS
REALLY THE DEMOLITION OF RENT CONTROL UNITS.
>> I CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CHINATOWN WHEN I WAS 13 YEARS
OLD, GREW UP IN IN THAT SPACE BECAUSE IT WAS A RENT CONTROL
UNIT. AND TODAY HERE I AM YOU KNOW, I
WENT TO PUBLIC SCHOOL AND I BE ABLE TO THRIVE AND TAKE ROOTS
AND RAISE MY OWN FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I WOULD CONTRIBUTE TO THAT TO THE FACT THAT I HAD A STABLE
HOME IN CHINATOWN AND BECAUSE A HOME THAT MY MOTHER A SINGLE
MOM RAISING TWO TEENAGE KIDS COULD AFFORD.
>> AND THEN YOU KNOW, FAST FORWARD TO 2021 WHEN MY MOTHER
HAD CANCER AND THAT YOU KNOW, WE SHE WAS STAYING IN UCSF
PARNASSUS CAMPUS. WE WERE HER LAST DAYS AND WE
HAD TO IDENTIFY IN A HOSPICE BUT WE COULDN'T FIND A SPACE
WHERE EITHER WE COULD AFFORD OR THAT BE ABLE TO TIMELY MOVE HER
IN THERE. WHAT HAPPENED IN HER LAST DAYS
WAS WE WERE ABLE TO RETURN IN THE VERY SAME APARTMENT THAT
SHE RAISED ME RENT CONTROL UNITS THAT WE COULD AFFORD FOR
HER TO STAY THERE FOR HER LAST DAYS BEFORE SHE PASSED THROUGH
PATHS IN A SPACE WHERE SHE RAISED ME AND MY BROTHER.
SHE LIVED AND WORKED THERE. SHE WORKED ON POWELL STREET FOR
ON STARVING SENIORS AND OF COURSE CHINESE HOSPITAL BEFORE
THAT SHE WAS ABLE TO DEDICATE HER LIFE AND HER COMMUNITY
BUILDING AND EVEN IN HER LAST DAYS IN THE SPACE SHE LOVED
AND CARE FOR ALL THIS I PERSONALLY CONTRIBUTED TO A
RENT CONTROL UNIT, A RENT CONTROL UNIT FOR A FAMILY LIKE
MINE THE SINGLE FAMILY IMMIGRANTS FIRST GENERATION
IMMIGRANT UNITS, FAMILY CAN ACTUALLY STAY AND THRIVE
AND GROW TODAY. AND SO FOR SB 79 BEING THROUGH
ALL THE COMMITTEE AND THANKS TO CHAIR MAL GAR LIKE TRYING TO
REALLY FIGURE OUT SOME CONSENSUS AND URGING AMENDMENTS
THROUGH COMMITTEE BOTH AT THE HOUSING COMMITTEE THAT YOU
KNOW, ASSEMBLY MEMBER MATT HANEY CHAIRED WAS REPRESENTING
US AND THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT COMMITTEE AND THE STATE
ASSEMBLY AGAIN YET THERE WAS NO CONSENSUS THAT COULD ACTUALLY
TO EITHER CARVE OUT SAN FRANCISCO OR TO REALLY FIGURE
OUT A WAY, YOU KNOW, SO THAT WE CAN ACTUALLY IMPLEMENT OUR
LOCAL CONTROL FOR DEMOLITION PROTECTION.
WHAT IT HAS LEFT US IS THAT THE ALLOWANCE FOR A STATE Y
DEMOLITION OF ANY STRUCTURE WOULD TO RENT CONTROL UNITS OR
LESS. THAT'S NOT GOOD ENOUGH FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. I CAN UNDERSTAND MAYBE OTHER
JURISDICTIONS HAVE DIFFERENT SITUATION AND I CAN UNDERSTAND
THAT YOU KNOW THAT IT'S IS DIFFERENT IN ATTRACTING
DIFFERENT IN OTHER COUNTIES THAT ARE IS WEALTHIER BUT
THAT'S NOT THE CASE FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND AS A POLICY MAKER
IN SAN FRANCISCO I HAVE TO FIGHT FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND BUT
IT'S I'M NOT JUST FIGHTING FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
I'M FIGHTING FOR EVERY INDIVIDUAL THAT LIVE IN THAT
RENT CONTROL UNIT, BE A SENIOR AND BE AN IMMIGRANT FAMILY OR
MAYBE NOT EVEN A REAL AMERICAN FAMILY BUT MAYBE AN ARTISAN A
MUSICIAN THAT THEY ARE ABLE TO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND THRIVE TODAY IS BECAUSE THERE IS A RENT CONTROL UNITS
FOR THEM. >> SO WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I
HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT. >> I DO BELIEVE THAT THIS IS A
MOMENT THAT YOU KNOW, SEEING OUR FUTURE WHERE WE'RE HEADING
THIS IS A QUESTION AGAIN AND I APPRECIATE ALL MY COLLEAGUES
AND BECAUSE WE ALL REPRESENT SUCH A DIVERSE CITY
AND DIFFERENT DISTRICT BUT THIS IS A MOMENT IS WHO ARE WE
BUILDING FOR WHAT IS WHO'S GOING TO GET TO STAY IN OUR
CITY AND THRIVE? >> AND FOR ME SINCE 1990 HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AS A 13 YEAR OLD AND TO TODAY AS A
POLICYMAKER, I HOPE THAT YOU KNOW THAT A FAMILY LIKE MINE
CAN STILL BE HERE AND THRIVE 30 YEARS FROM NOW, 40 YEARS FROM
NOW, 50 YEARS FROM NOW. >> AND AND SO I DO HOPE TO HAVE
YOUR SUPPORT. >> AND ONE THING I ALSO WANT TO
HIGHLIGHT FOR YOU IS THAT WITH SB 79 AS IT CURRENTLY STANDS,
THERE IS NO MECHANISM SSM THERE'S ABSOLUTELY NO STATE
MECHANISM THAT ALLOW US TO ACTUALLY HAVE IMPLEMENT IT ON A
LOCAL LEVEL TO REALLY HAVE A TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESS
PROTECTION AND THERE'S NO SUPPORT FROM THE STATE LEVEL
BUT AGAIN LEGISLATIVE TOOLS OR FUNDING SOURCES FOR US TO DO SO
AND FOR THAT I JUST DON'T THINK THAT I CAN SUPPORT SB 79 AS IT
CURRENTLY IS AND THAT I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT THAT WE WILL
OPPOSE 79 UNLESS AMENDED. >> THANK YOU CHAIR MELGAR THANK
YOU SO MUCH. >> PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN SO THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR TRAN FOR THE ROBUST DISCUSSION AT THE LADIES
COMMITTEE WHERE WE HOSTED YOU FOR THIS ITEM.
THIS ITEM CAME OUT OF THE COMMITTEE WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION SO THAT WE COULD HAVE THIS CONVERSATION HERE
AND I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN ABOUT THE PROTECTION OF
RENT CONTROLLED UNITS IN BUILDINGS UP TO UNITS OR
LESS. AND I ALSO THINK THIS IS A
QUESTION OF STRATEGY. I AM NOT READY TO SUPPORT A
LEGISLATION OPPOSING SB 79 TODAY AS WE STILL HAVE SIX MORE
WEEKS WHERE THIS LEGISLATION CAN BE AMENDED.
IN THE PAST MONTH AND A HALF I HAVE BEEN WORKING WITH BOTH
ASSEMBLY MEMBER HANY AND SENATOR WIENER ON
AMENDMENTS TO SB 79 AND EVEN THOUGH WE'RE NOT QUITE THERE
YET ON TWO ISSUES ON THE ISSUE OF RENT CONTROL IN BUILDINGS OF
TWO UNITS OR LESS. AND ALSO ON THE CLEAR LANGUAGE
ON BETTER CLEAR LANGUAGE WHICH IS NOT CURRENTLY SB 79 WHEN IT
COMES TO PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES.
SO AS OF RIGHT NOW WE ACTUALLY HAVE BEEN ABLE TO GET QUITE A
BIT IN BOTH THE HOUSING COMMITTEE, THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT
COMMITTEE AND THE TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE IN SB
79 AGAIN WORKING WITH ASSEMBLY MEMBER HANY IN WIENER AND WITH
A COALITION OF FOLKS IN L.A. AND IN BERKELEY.
SO I THINK THIS IS THE WAY THE PROCESS IS SUPPOSED TO WORK SO
WE'RE NOT QUITE THERE YET BUT I'M NOT READY TO OPPOSE IT TO
DAY AS WE ARE STILL MAKING PROGRESS.
THAT BEING SAID, I THINK THAT IT IS SOMETHING THAT I INVITE
ALL OF YOU WHO HAVE INTEREST IN LAND USE TO LOOK AT AND TO
WEIGH IN. THEY THESE FOLKS IN SACRAMENTO
REPRESENT US OVERALL. THIS IS A LEGISLATION THAT WILL
COVER ALL OF CALIFORNIA. WHAT IT IS MEANT TO DO IS TO
GUIDE DEVELOPMENT AROUND TRANSIT SITES, HIGH TRANSIT
SITES, RAIL AND YOU KNOW, BRT SITES.
AND SO IT IS SOMETHING THAT I THINK WE ALL AGREE SHOULD
HAPPEN IN CALIFORNIA. MILLBRAE, BRISBANE, FRESNO ALL
OF THESE CITIES AROUND CALIFORNIA THAT NEED TO DEVELOP
HOUSING SHOULD DO SO AROUND PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION AND NOT
AROUND FREEWAYS AND NOT AROUND THE WAYS THAT WE HAVE IN THE
PAST LED OUR DEVELOPMENT TO BE CAR CENTRIC.
IT IS SUPPORTING OUR CLIMATE CHANGE GOALS AND ALSO
SUPPORTING RIDERSHIP IN OUR PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS
WHICH WE ALL I THINK AGREE SHOULD HAPPEN NOW HOW IT ALL
INTERSPERSES WITH OUR HOUSING ELEMENT IS THE QUESTION.
AND WE'RE STILL WORKING OUT THE LANGUAGE AND THE DETAILS.
>> AND WHILE I SUPPORT THE TWO FOUNDING TIONAL ELEMENTS OF OUR
HOUSING ELEMENT WHICH ARE THE PRESERVATION OF RENT CONTROLLED
HOUSING AND THE PRESERVATION OF PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES
AND THE LANGUAGE IN SB 79 COULD BE CLEAR AROUND BOTH.
I AM NOT READY TO SAY TODAY THAT I OPPOSE IT UNLESS
AMENDED. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES, I WISH TO SPEAK
IN SUPPORT OF SENATOR WEINER'S AND SPEAK 79 AND I AS
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MENTIONED I DO RESPECT THE RESOLUTION
AND MY COLLEAGUES WHO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION WHICH IS WHY WE
WERE HAPPY TO PASS IT OUT OF COMMITTEE.
SO EVERYONE AT THE FULL BOARD CAN HAVE A DISCUSSION
AND RESPECT THAT WE MAY NOT ALWAYS AGREE BUT I JUST WANTED
TO CENTER THE CONVERSATION AROUND WHAT DOES SB 79 DO AND A
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MENTIONED IT IS THE POSITIVE DIRECTION TO
ALLOW FOR MORE HOMES TO BE BUILT IN THE PARTS OF THE STATE
WHERE WE NEED TO BE BUILDING WHICH IS NEAR MAJOR TRANSIT
STATIONS. >> THE LEGISLATION SPECIFICALLY
ALLOWS FOR BUILDINGS UP TO 75FT TALL NEAR BARTON CALTRAIN
STATIONS AND ALLOWS FOR TRANSIT AGENCIES TO BE MORE EASILY
DEVELOP THEIR OWN LAND. >> THIS WILL HELP SUPPORT THE
TRANSIT SYSTEMS THAT SAN FRANCISCO RELIES ON IN THIS
DIFFICULT FISCAL ENVIRONMENT BY PROVIDING A LONG TERM SOURCE OF
RELIABLE REVENUE. >> IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO
RECOGNIZE HOW SB 79 WAS WRITTEN AND WHAT IT DOES NOT DO.
DUE TO AMENDMENTS IN THE PROCESS THAT BOTH
ASSEMBLYMEMBER MAHANEY AND SENATOR WIENER WORKED ON
TOGETHER, IT IS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT THERE ARE
ADDITIONAL RESTRICTIONS ON DEMOLITION IN THIS LEGISLATION
WHICH ARE SOME OF THE STRONGEST IN STATE LAW AND ALSO DOESN'T
OVERRIDE LOCAL TENANT PROTECTIONS OR LOCAL
AFFORDABILITY REQUIREMENTS MEANING NEW HOMES WILL BE FOR
CURRENT AND FUTURE SAN FRANCISCANS AT ALL INCOME
LEVELS AND NOT JUST AT THE HIGH END.
>> THE REVENUE GENERATED BY INCLUSIONARY HOUSING FEES WILL
HELP INVIGORATE OUR AFFORDABLE HOUSING PIPELINE AS WELL.
>> LASTLY, THE OPTION IN THE LEGISLATION FOR LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS TO CREATE A LOCAL ALTERNATIVE PLAN WILL ALLOW THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT AN OPPORTUNITY TO ENSURE THE
INCREASED IN ZONE CAPACITY FITS INTO THE CITY'S LAND USE
CONTEXT AND IS IN SYNC WITH OUR ONGOING HOUSING ELEMENT
REZONING. SO AGAIN FIRMLY I DO BELIEVE
THAT GROWTH GROWTH NEAR TRANSIT IS AN ESSENTIAL PART OF OUR
VISION FOR AN EQUITABLE AND ENVIRONMENTALLY SUSTAINABLE
URBAN SAN FRANCISCO. AND FOR THAT REASON I AM STILL
SUPPORTING SB 79 AND WILL BE VOTING NO ON THIS RESOLUTION.
>> SURPRISE DISORDER. YES.
COLLEAGUES, THANK YOU FOR THIS DISCUSSION.
I WILL ALSO BE SUPPORTING SB 79 AND REJECTING THIS RESOLUTION.
>> YOU KNOW IN THESE CHAMBERS WE OFTEN SPEAK ABOUT WANTING TO
CREATE MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING, FINDING SOLUTIONS TO TRANSIT
FUNDING AND DOING OUR PART TO FIGHT CLIMATE CHANGE.
SO ALONG COMES A BILL THAT ADDRESSES ALL THREE OF THESE
CRITICAL PRIORITIES. AND YET HERE WE ARE CONSIDERING
OPPOSING IT. IF WE DECIDE TO OPPOSE THIS
LEGISLATION AS A CITY I BELIEVE WE STAND CONTRARY TO ALL OF OUR
STATED ASPIRATIONS. I BELIEVE THAT TRANSIT ORIENTED
VELOPMENT IS ONE OF THE BEST TOOLS WE HAVE TO MEET THE
HOUSING TRANSIT AND CLIMATE NEEDS OF OUR CITY.
BECAUSE WHEN PEOPLE LIVE NEAR WHERE THEY WORK IT HELPS
STRENGTHEN OUR COMMUNITIES, BOOST TRANSIT RIDERSHIP
AND PROTECT THE ENVIRONMENT. OUR TRANSIT SYSTEMS ARE INDEED
IN AN EXTREME FUNDING CRISIS THAT WE ARE ALL WELL AWARE OF.
AND THIS LEGISLATION WOULD GIVE TRANSIT AGENCIES GREATER
ABILITY TO BUILD ON THE LAND THAT THEY OWN WHICH WOULD
PROVIDE DESPERATELY NEEDED REVENUE STREAMS FOR OUR SYSTEMS
WHILE PRODUCING HOUSING FOR OUR COMMUNITIES ON UNDERUTILIZED
LAND. FOR THE PAST 15 YEARS I HAVE
LIVED IN A RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND I'M CURRENTLY RAISING MY FAMILY IN RENT CONTROLLED
APARTMENT THAT WE LOVE. SO I UNDERSTAND THE CONCERNS
AND UNCERTAINTY THAT MANY OF US HAVE ABOUT NEW DEVELOPMENT
AND HOW IT MIGHT IMPACT OUR HOMES AND NEIGHBORHOODS.
I ALSO UNDERSTAND THAT WE ARE GOING THROUGH A COMPLEX
SIGNIFICANT REZONING PROCESS THAT WILL PROVIDE OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS WITH CAPACITY TO ADD MORE HOUSING IN THE COMING
YEARS. BUT LET'S BE CLEAR FIGHTING NEW
HOUSING DOES NOT MAKE OUR CITY MORE AFFORDABLE.
FINDING NEW HOUSING ONLY HELPS ONE GROUP LANDLORDS BECAUSE NO
ONE WINS IN A HOUSING SHORTAGE MORE THAN THEY DO.
THE RESOLUTION BEFORE US ASKS TO OPPOSE UNLESS AMENDED.
SB 79 HAS HAD SIGNIFICANT AMENDMENTS SINCE THIS
RESOLUTION WAS FIRST INTRODUCED.
THESE AMENDMENTS ADDRESS MANY CONCERNS AROUND AFFORDABILITY
REQUIREMENTS AND HOW THIS LAW WOULD INTERACT WITH OUR LOCAL
ZONING PROCESS. >> TO BE VERY CLEAR, THE
LEGISLATION CONTAINS AFFORDABILITY AND DEMOLITION
PROTECTIONS. IT HAS BEEN AMENDED TO INCLUDE
A HIGHER AFFORDABILITY REQUIREMENT THAN CURRENTLY
EXISTS IN THE STATE DENSITY BONUS LAW.
I FIRMLY BELIEVE WE CAN BUILD NEW HOUSING IN RESOURCE
AND TRANSIT RICH NEIGHBORHOODS WHILE PROTECTING TENANTS IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS WE LOVE. SB 79, ESPECIALLY THROUGH THESE
RECENT AMENDMENTS BALANCES ALL OF THESE NEEDS AND SO FOR THESE
REASONS I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THE RESOLUTION WHICH I
BELIEVE TO BE CONTRARY TO OUR HOUSING, TRANSIT AND CLIMATE
GOALS. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR JIM SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
>> I AM A CO-SPONSOR SO I WANT TO ECHO THAT.
I ALSO BELIEVE THAT POLICY THAT'S INCENTIVIZE TRANSIT
ORIENTED DEVELOPMENT CAN BE BENEFICIAL AS THEY REDUCE
COMMUTES, LOWER CARBON EMISSIONS AND REDUCE OUR
RELIANCE ON CARS. >> HOWEVER, I ALSO BELIEVE THAT
OUR POLICIES MUST BE TAILOR. WE CAN INCENTIVIZE DEVELOPMENT
IN AREAS THAT CAN ABSORB IT WITHOUT CAUSING HARMS SUCH AS
AREA WHAT ROBUST EXISTING INFRASTRUCTURE AND LESS
DISPLACEMENT RISK FOR NEIGHBOR WHO ARE FACING DISPLACEMENT.
WE MUST PRIORITIZE ANTI DISPLACEMENT STRATEGY, ROBUST
TENANT PROTECTION AND PROTECTION FOR OUR STOCK OF
RENT CONTROL HOUSING AND SIGNIFICANTLY INVESTING
IN TRULY AFFORDABLE HOUSING. SO OTHERWISE SAN FRANCISCO
WOULD NOT BECOME CONTINUE TO BE AFFORDABLE FOR WORKING FAMILY
WHICH MY DISTRICT IS HEAVILY WORKING FAMILY WHO ARE CONTINUE
TO HOPING TO RAISE THEIR FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ALSO
RETIRE IN AND STATE WITH DIGNITY AND SAFETY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. SO I YOU KNOW I OPPOSE ANY OF
DEPOSIT THAT WOULD LIKELY TO PUSH OUT FAMILY AND BUSINESS
THAT HAVE BUILT THE FABRIC OF THIS COMMUNITY FOR GENERATIONS.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU.
AND AGAIN, YOU KNOW, COLLEAGUES, THANK YOU SO MUCH
FOR YOUR COMMENT TODAY. I WANT TO ALSO SAY THIS I THINK
EVEN OUR LAND USE WHEN IT WAS AT LAND USE COMMITTEE I WELCOME
ANY FEEDBACK AND AMENDMENT AND THE GOAL IS TO SAY THAT
WHAT IS IT THAT WE WOULD LIKE TO WHAT IS IT THAT IF WE HAVE
NO CONSENSUS ABOUT WHAT WE LIKE TO SEE IN SB 979 TO BE AMENDED,
WHAT ARE THE AMENDMENTS THAT WE WOULD LIKE TO SEE SO THAT WE
CAN BE FULLY ON BOARD WITH 79? SO I JUST FIRST WANTED TO SAY
THAT I WELCOME THAT AMENDMENT TO SAY WHAT CAN 79 TO DO BETTER
AND I WILL SUPPORT IT. I THINK THAT WHAT IT'S REALLY
BEFORE US TODAY IS IT'S NOT JUST SB 79 IS ALSO WHAT WE'RE
GOING TO SEE IN THE MAYOR'S PROPOSAL.
ONE IS UP ZONING THE ENTIRE CITY AND IT'S A LAYERS OF
LAYERS OF BOTH STATE LEGISLATION AND HOUSING
ELEMENTS THE MANDATE LAYERING A 79 LAYERING WHAT IS UPCOMING ON
A LOCAL UP ZONING PLAN THAT IS WHERE I'M HEADING TO THINK
ABOUT IT IN A BIG PICTURE. WHAT DOES THAT MEAN ACTUALLY
FOR THE SMALL BUSINESS AND THE TENANTS AND AGING HOMEOWNERS
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND WHAT DOES IT DO ACTUALLY TO THEM TO US
AND AND I THINK THAT TODAY IF WE CEDED THE SPACE TO SAY GO
AHEAD ALLOWING THE DEMOLITION OF EVEN JUST ONE RENT CONTROL
UNITS IN SAN FRANCISCO WITHOUT ANY TYPE OF COMMITMENT TO ALSO
TENANT PROTECTION AND SMALL BUSINESS IT BECOMES THE FLOOR
79 WILL BECOME THE FLOOR FOR UP ZONING IT WILL NOT IT'S NOT A
CEILING IT'S IT BECOMES A FLOOR FOR UP ZONING FOR SAN FRANCISCO
FOR THE UPCOMING UP ZONING PLAN DISCUSSION THAT WE WILL HAVE TO
FACE THIS FALL. SO I DON'T THINK THAT THE FLOOR
I DO NOT FIND ACCEPTABLE AS A FLOOR.
I AM OF COURSE URGING FOR YOUR SUPPORT BUT I KNOW WHERE WE'RE
HEADING TODAY AND FOR THIS REASON I DO ACTUALLY AGAIN WANT
TO THANK THE LAND USE COMMITTEE FOR ALLOWING THIS VOTE TO TAKE
PLACE TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT I WILL NOT
REPEAT IN FULL THE REMARKS OF MY COLLEAGUES SUPERVISORS SADR,
MAHMOOD AND MELGAR BUT I BELIEVE IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE
THAT SB 79 HAS SOME OF THE STATE'S STRONGEST ANTI
DEMOLITION PROTECTIONS OF ANY LAW AND IT DOESN'T OVERRIDE
LOCAL PROTECTIONS INCLUDING ONES THAT WE MAY CONTINUE TO
CONSIDER AS A PART OF THIS HOUSING ELEMENT OVER THE NEXT
SEVERAL MONTHS. >> I ALSO WANT TO NOTE THAT
THIS HAS BEEN RECENTLY AMENDED TO PROVIDE THE ABILITY FOR
LOCAL GOVERNMENTS TO EXEMPT THEMSELVES THROUGH FRANKLY
PRETTY LOW THRESHOLD ALTERNATIVES BUT EVEN MORE SO I
THINK IT'S INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT TO NOTE AS SUPREME SUPERVISOR
MELGAR ALLUDED TO THAT AFFORDABILITY MUST BE A
REGIONAL AND FRANKLY A STATE WIDE APPROACH AND IT CANNOT BE
DONE WITHOUT ROBUST TRANSPORTATION NETWORKS.
>> AND IF WE ARE GOING TO REACH AFFORDABILITY AS A CITY WE NEED
TO DO IT WITH OUR REGIONAL PARTNERS.
WE NEED TO DO WITH OUR STATE PARTNERS AND THAT MEANS HAVING
DENSE HOUSING NEAR TRANSIT WE CANNOT RELY ON AFFORDABILITY ON
OUR OWN NO MATTER HOW MUCH HOUSING WE BUILD.
IF THE COUNTIES AROUND US DON'T ALL ALSO FOLLOW IN THAT WE MUST
SUPPORT THIS IN ORDER TO ENSURE THAT AFFORDABILITY IS A
REGIONAL APPROACH BUILT AROUND TRANSIT.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 40 TWO ON ITEM 42
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO NO SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO SUPERVISOR MANDOLINE NO MIDDLEMAN NO
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR NO SUPERVISOR SADR.
SADR NO SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO.
SUPERVISOR WALTON YES. WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE FOUR EYES AND SEVEN
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS DORSEY AND GAUDIO MAHMOOD MANDEL MEN
MELGAR SADR AND CHERYL VOTING NO THE RESOLUTION IS NOT
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 43 TO 45 TOGETHER ITEMS
43 THROUGH 45 ARE THREE RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO
LIQUOR LICENSES. ITEM 43 DETERMINES THAT THE
ISSUANCE OF A TYPE 42 ON SALE BEER AND WINE LIQUOR LICENSE TO
SBL A LIVING ASSET 2018 LLC DOING BUSINESS AS BLUE STREAM
GALLERY AND WINES LOCATED AT 555 GRANT AVENUE WILL SERVE THE
PUBLIC CONVENIENCE ITEM 44 DETERMINES THAT THE ISSUANCE OF
A TYPE 90 ON SALE GENERAL MUSIC VENUE BEER WINE AND DISTILLED
SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO INTERNATIONAL ART MUSEUM OF
AMERICA LOCATED AT 1025 MARKET STREET WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC
CONVENIENCE AND ITEM 45 THIS RESOLUTION DETERMINES THAT THE
PERSON TO PERSON PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TO TYPE
21 OFF SALE GENERAL BEER WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR
LICENSE TO BARBARY COAST MERCHANTS LLC DOING BUSINESS AS
AMADOR LIQUORS AND WINES LOCATED AT 550 MONTGOMERY
STREET WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE AND REQUESTING THAT
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF EACH LICENSE.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 43 THROUGH 45 SUPERVISOR
DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO IN GAUDIO EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER I FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR ABSENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTZ AND I SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN EYES ON THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 46 ITEM
46 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR THE
APPOINTMENT OF LINDSAY MCALEESE TO THE BUILDING INSPECTION
COMMISSION FOR A TERM ENDING JULY 1ST, 2026.
>> ALL RIGHT. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPT OR THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE HAVE
COMMITTEE REPORTS NEXT. >> YES.
ITEMS 49 THROUGH 63 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE GOVERNMENT
AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE ON THURSDAY, JULY 17TH
AND WE'RE RECOMMENDED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU LIKE ME TO READ ALL
SETTLEMENTS? SURE.
49 THROUGH 63 ITEM 49 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE
SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY PATTERN AS PROOF INC AGAINST
THE CITY FOR 69,500. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES
PETITIONER'S ALLEGATION THAT THE SAN FRANCISCO DISTRICT
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE VIOLATED THE CALIFORNIA PUBLIC RECORDS ACT
ITEM 50 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF A
LAWSUIT FILED BY MARY TRAMMELL AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR
230,000. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES AN
EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE ITEM 51 THIS AUTHORIZES THE SERVICE OF AN
OFFER TO COMPROMISE IN THE LAWSUIT FILED BY RENE OWENS
AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR UP TO 650,000.
THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED WRONGFUL DEATH ON A CITY
SIDEWALK ITEM 52 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY THOMAS WHELAN AND ELEANOR WHALEN AGAINST THE
CITY AND COUNTY FOR 530,000. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED
PROPERTY DAMAGE ARISING FROM A FLOOD ITEM 53.
THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES A PARTIAL SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY RALPH BAUER AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR
400,000 INVOLVING PERSONAL INJURY ON A CITY STREET ITEM 54
THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED
BY RYAN RYAN BLAYLOCK BY AND THROUGH GUARDIAN AD LITEM
HALIMA QUINN AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR 100,000.
THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ON A CITY
SIDEWALK ITEM 55 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY RACHEL SUGIYAMA AGAINST THE CITY FOR
95,000. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED
PERSONAL INJURY FROM A VEHICLE COLLISION ITEM 56.
THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED
BY MARY FELLER AND GORDON FELLER AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR 250,000 INVOLVING ALLEGED A PERSONAL
INJURY ON A CITY SIDEWALK ITEM 57 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES
SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY THE ARCHDIOCESE OF SAN
FRANCISCO PARISH AND SCHOOL JURISTIC PERSONS REAL PROPERTY
SUPPORT CORPORATION AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR 248,000.
THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED PROPERTY DAMAGE AND ECONOMIC
LOSSES ARISING FROM FLOODING CAUSED BY A WATER TRANSMISSION
PIPELINE BREAK ITEM 58 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMEN
OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY FRANK MO FARAH AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR 65,000 INVOLVING ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ARISING
FROM A FALL ON A CITY SIDEWALK ITEM 59 THIS ORDINANCE
AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY UNITED LAYER
LLC AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR 850,000.
THE LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGATIONS OF BREACH OF
CONTRACT ARISING FROM DISPUTED ADDITIONAL COSTS ASSOCIATED
WITH A CO-LOCATION AGREEMENT WHEREBY THE CITY RECEIVED
CERTAIN DATA CENTER SERVICES ITEM 60 THIS ORDINANCE
AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY JAIDEN AVILA
WILLIAMS AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR 80,000 INVOLVING
AN ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY FROM A VEHICLE COLLISION INVOLVING
OFFICERS FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT.
ITEM 61 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY MICHAEL RIVAS. HERMAN REVERSE, LILLIAN RIVAS.
HIBA WILLIAMS, PAUL WILLIAMS YOU WILL HYUN UNION JEREMY
JACKO STANLEY CHOW AND HAROLD HONG AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR 650,000 INVOLVING ALLEGED PROPERTY
DAMAGE TO FOUR HOMES LOCATED ON LAKEFRONT AVENUE IN SAN
FRANCISCO FROM FLOODING ON DECEMBER 31ST 2022.
ITEM 62 THIS ORDINANCE AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY CHERYL WHITFIELD AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR 50,000 INVOLVING AN ALLEGED PERSONAL INJURY ON A
CITY SIDEWALK. AND ITEM 63 THIS ORDINANCE
AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY 2121 PINE
STREET S.F. LLC AT ALL AGAINST THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR
300,000. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES A CLAIM
FOR REFUND OF TRANSFER TAXES, PENALTIES AND INTEREST.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL OH SORRY SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AND DOMAIN COLLEAGUES ,I'M THROUGH DISCUSSION WITH
CITY ATTORNEY. I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT I
DISCLOSE PARTICULARLY AROUND ITEM 57 THE SETTLEMENTS LAWSUIT
WITH THE ARCHDIOCESE OF SAN FRANCISCO, PARIS AND SCHOOL
THAT MY SON ATTEND AN AFFILIATED SCHOOL UNDER THE
ARCHDIOCESE OF SAN FRANCISCO PARISH AND SCHOOL.
THANK YOU, MR. CHAN. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEMS 49 THROUGH 63 SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO AND GAUDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SAUTER SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON HIGH WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN
CHEN I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 64 ITEM 64 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE ON MONDAY JULY 21ST AND WAS
RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT ITEM 64.
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO PROVIDE
CONDITIONS FOR REPAIR AND RELOCATION OF EXISTING NON
COMPLYING STRUCTURES WITHIN REQUIRED YARDS GRANT UNDER
PERMITTED RESIDENTIAL STRUCTURES WITHIN YARDS THAT
WERE CONSTRUCTED BEFORE 2003 NON COMPLYING STATUS AND TO
ALLOW ACCESSORY STRUCTURES UP TO TEN FEET IN HEIGHT
AND 120FT2 WITHIN REQUIRED YARDS TO AMEND THE BUILDING
CODE TO EXEMPT ACCESSORY STRUCTURES UP TO 120FT2 FROM
BUILDING PERMITS AND TO AFFIRM THE SQUARE DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> ALL RIGHT, LET'S TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 65 I WILL FIRST STATE THAT ITEM 65 THROUGH 67 WERE
CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE ON MONDAY JULY 21ST
AND WERE RECOMMENDED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS SPECIFIC TO
ITEM 65. THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATE OF CODE TO ADD THE SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTER
AND EMS BEHAVIORAL HEALTH FOUNDATION TO THE LIST OF
ORGANIZATIONS TO WHICH CITY OFFICERS AND EMPLOYEES MAY MAKE
DONATIONS BY PAYROLL DEDUCTION. >> AND LET'S TAKE THAT SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 66. >> YES ITEMS 66 WAS RECOMMENDED
AS A COMMITTEE REPORT BEARING A NEW TITLE.
IT THE LANGUAGE THAT WAS STRUCK IN COMMITTEE WAS JUST TO REMOVE
IN THE FIRST SENTENCE CHAPTER 14 B IT NOW READS ITEM 66 NOW
READS ORDINANCE WAIVING THE COMPETITIVE SOLICITATION
REQUIREMENTS UNDER 21 CHAPTER 21 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
FOR THE POLICE DEPARTMENT'S PROCUREMENT OF EQUIPMENT,
TECHNOLOGY AND SERVICES TO SUPPORT THE DEPARTMENT'S REAL
TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER USING GIFT FUNDS RECEIVED FROM THE
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE COMMUNITY FOUNDATION.
AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT. NOPE.
NOPE. >> THAT'S A ROLL CALL.
ALL RIGHT. ON ITEM 66 SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WILSON NO SUPERVISOR
CHIN CHIN EYE AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 67
ITEM 67 WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT ALSO WITH A
NEW TITLE. SIMILARLY SIMILARLY STRIKING
THE LANGUAGE CHAPTER 14 B ITEM 67 NOW READS ORDINANCE WAIVING
THE COMPETITIVE SOLICITATION REQUIREMENTS UNDER CHAPTER 21
OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE FOR THE POLICE DEPARTMENT'S
PROCUREMENT OF EQUIPMENT, TECHNOLOGY AND SERVICES FOR THE
REGIONAL VEHICLE INTERDICTION DESK USING GRANT FUNDS FROM THE
UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE.
BUREAU OF JUSTICE ASSISTANCE. >> YES, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 67 SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
MANDEL MAN ALL RIGHT. MANDEL MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON OH WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO
WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO AND THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED
ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR
INTRODUCTIONS. >> DORSEY YOU ARE FIRST UP TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK
COLLEAGUES, I HAVE A RESOLUTION AND AN IN MEMORIAM TODAY.
FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO INITIATE THE
LANDMARKING PROCESS FOR THE MINT MALL AN INVALUABLE
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSET FOR THE SELMA AND FILIPINO COMMUNITIES
BUILT IN 1969 OR 1916 AS A RESIDENTIAL HOTEL.
THE MINT MALL TRANSFERRED TO FULFILL FILIPINO OWNERSHIP
IN THE 1980S. SINCE THEN A LARGE POPULATION
OF FILIPINO RESIDENTS HAS RESIDED IN THE APARTMENTS
IN THE UPPER RESIDENTIAL FLOORS OF THE BUILDING KNOWN AS MINT
HALL AND SUPPORTED BY A HOST OF FILIPINO SMALL BUSINESSES
AND NONPROFITS BELOW IN THE MINT MALL NOTABLE FILIPINO
BUSINESSES AND NONPROFITS PAST AND PRESENT INCLUDED ARE
ARCHIPELAGO BOOKS TEATRO IN TAINAN AND NEW FILIPINOS
RESTAURANT NOW CALLED J TEA RESTAURANT WHICH AS I HAVE SAID
PREVIOUSLY IN THIS CHAMBER'S PUTS MY IRISH ANCESTORS TO
SHAME FOR THE WORLD'S BEST BEEF STEW.
I WOULD BE REMISS NOT ALSO TO MENTION EDDIE'S BARBER
AND BEAUTY SHOP WHERE I OFTEN GET MY HAIRCUT.
MANY OF THESE BUSINESSES AND NONPROFITS ARE AMONG THOSE
THAT SUCCESSFULLY FOUGHT AMONG AGAINST THEIR EVICTION FROM THE
MINT MALL WITH THE HELP OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZERS UNDER THE
MINT MALL ORGANIZING COMMITTEE. THE MINT MALL IS MORE THAN JUST
THE BUSINESSES AND RESIDENCES THAT MAKE UP THE BUILDING.
IT IS THE BEATING HEART AND SENATE CENTER OF GRAVITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S FILIPINO COMMUNITY AND IT'S OFTEN THE
FIRST STOP FOR NEW IMMIGRANTS FROM THE PHILIPPINES.
AT JT RESTAURANT YOU CAN NOT ONLY GET A DELICIOUS HOME
COOKED MEAL THERE, YOU CAN ALSO GET THE SUPPORT AND GUIDANCE
FROM TITA TESS, A DE FACTO SOCIAL WORKER AND COMMUNITY
MATRIARCH WHO LENDS A LOVING HAND TO ANYONE WHO NEEDS IT
AND AS A FELLOW PARISHIONER FROM ST PATRICK'S.
TESS HAS ALSO BEEN A KNOWLEDGEABLE SPIRITUAL ADVISOR
TO ME WHENEVER I NEED TO KNOW WHICH ST TO LIGHT A CANDLE TO
WHICH IS FOR WHICH DESIRED OUTCOME.
THE SENIOR CENTER ACROSS THE HALL OFFERS COMMUNITY HEALTH
SERVICES AND A WELCOMING PLACE FOR OUR COMMUNITY'S ELDERS.
IT'S ALSO A HOST FOR SIGNIFICANT CULTURAL EVENTS
LIKE THE ANNUAL PASCAL'S SOMA AND THE FIRST PARALLEL MAKING
WORKSHOPS FOR THE PAROLE LANTERN FESTIVAL.
THIS LANDMARKING EFFORT FURTHERS THE GOALS OF THE SOMA
PILIPINAS CULTURAL HISTORY, HOUSING AND ECONOMIC
SUSTAINABILITY STRATEGY REPORT OR CHESS REPORT.
THIS REPORT WAS ADOPTED BY THE CITY IN 2022 AND ONE OF THE KEY
STRATEGIES IS TWO LANDMARK BUILDINGS IN SOMA THAT HAVE
CULTURAL AND HISTORIC SIGNIFICANCE TO THE FILIPINO
COMMUNITY. TO BUILD ON THIS AND TO EXPAND
EFFORTS TO IMPLEMENT THE CHESS REPORT SAMA PILIPINAS AND SOM
KEN WORKED WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO CREATE THE CHESS
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IMPLEMENTATION PLAN WHICH
IDENTIFIED THE MALL AS A BUILDING TO BE EXPLORED FOR
HISTORIC LANDMARKING. IN LINE WITH SOM KEN AND SOMA
PILIPINAS PUSH FOR GREATER FILIPINO LANGUAGE ACCESS IN THE
CITY THIS LANDMARK REPORT WILL ALSO BE THE FIRST TO BE WRITTEN
BILINGUALLY IN ENGLISH AND FILIPINO.
THERE ARE MANY INDIVIDUALS WHO PLAYED A ROLE IN THIS THOROUGH
RESEARCH AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT THAT I WOULD LIKE TO
THANK MOSES KHAIRAT FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FROM SOM
KEN ANGELICA CARBONDALE, ZACHARY FREE ALL AND WILFRED
GULLIBLE GALELLA FROM SOMA PILIPINAS RAQUEL VERDUN DIAZ
AND DAVID WU AND FROM THE MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO WERE
INTERVIEWED GENIE THE ABOUT LOWNESS TEST DIAZ ALLEN MANALO
M.S. CANLAS ESTHER AND NYX CARRIE PABLO GRAVEDIGGER
AND LORENZO LA STANA. I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE COMMUNITY TO ADVANCE THIS
LANDMARKING PROCESS. SECOND AND FINALLY I WOULD LIKE
TO ASK THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING TO HONOR THE MEMORY OF
DAN DILLON, A BELOVED SAN FRANCISCAN DEDICATED CIVIC
LEADER AND A LONGTIME PRESENCE IN OUR CITY'S PUBLIC AFFAIRS
COMMUNITY WHO PASSED AWAY EARLIER THIS MONTH.
DAN BROUGHT HIS SOUTHERN CHARM TO SAN FRANCISCO IN THE MID
1990S AND OVER THE LAST THREE DECADES BECAME ONE OF THE MOST
RESPECTED AND ADMIRED FIGURES IN OUR CIVIC LANDSCAPE.
DAN WAS A TRUSTED ADVISOR AND TENACIOUS ADVOCATE
PARTICULARLY ON PERMITTING BUILDING REGULATIONS AND THE
ISSUES THAT IMPACT OUR CITY'S HOSPITALITY AND EVENTS SECTORS.
HE HAS A DEEP UNDERSTANDING OF HOW THE CITY WORKS AND MAYBE
MORE IMPORTANTLY HOW IT COULD WORK BETTER.
DAN Z IMPACTED IMPACT EXTENDED FAR BEYOND CITY HALL.
HE PLAYED A CRITICAL ROLE IN BRINGING WORLD CLASS GOLF
TOURNAMENTS TO SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING THE 2020 PGA
CHAMPIONSHIP TO HARDING PARK, ONE OF THE RARE MAJOR
CHAMPIONSHIPS HELD AT A MUNICIPAL COURSE.
HIS LEADERSHIP ROLES WITH THE PGA TOUR, USGA AND THE OLYMPIC
CLUB WHERE HE SERVED AS PRESIDENT REFLECTED HIS
LIFELONG PASSION FOR SPORTS, FOR COMMUNITY AND FOR BRINGING
PEOPLE TOGETHER MORE THAN FOR HIS RESUME.
HOWEVER, DAN WAS KNOWN FOR HIS WARMTH, HIS HUMOR AND THE
GENUINE JOY HE BROUGHT TO EVERY ROOM HE ENTERED.
HE WAS A KIND, JOVIAL AND DEEPLY LOYAL PERSON FOR THE
CITY AND FOR THOSE HE LOVED. DAN LEAVES BEHIND HIS BELOVED
WIFE CARA ON BEHALF OF A GRATEFUL CITY.
I KNOW WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HER, TO HIS
FAMILY AND FRIENDS AND TO ALL WHO HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF
WORKING WITH DAN OVER THE YEARS.
REST IN PEACE DAN DILLON. MAY HIS MEMORY BE A BLESSING
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM REQUESTING A HEARING TO LEARN
MORE ABOUT THE ROOT CAUSE OF LOW LEVELS OF TRAFFIC
ENFORCEMENT ACROSS OUR CITY. FIRST I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
LEADERSHIP OF TWO OF MY COLLEAGUES ON THIS ISSUE
INCLUDING BOARD PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN OVER THE PAST TWO
YEARS AND SUPERVISOR MEL GARTH'S LEADERSHIP AND VISION
ZERO. I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
SIGNIFICANT AND MEANINGFUL STEPS TO IMPROVE STREET SAFETY
OVER THE PAST DECADE BY THE S.F. MTA IN COLLABORATION WITH
OTHER CITY DEPARTMENTS. BUT THEIR CHANGES CANNOT STOP
FATALITIES ON THEIR OWN WITHOUT CONSISTENT AND VISIBLE
ENFORCEMENT TO ENCOURAGE BEHAVIORAL CHANGE, EVEN THE
BEST PREVENTATIVE INFRASTRUCTURE WILL FALL SHORT
OF ITS INTENDED GOALS. IN 2014 SAN FRANCISCO SET AN
AMBITIOUS GOAL TO ELIMINATE TRAFFIC FATALITIES IN 20 YEARS.
BUT LAST YEAR WE REPORTED ONE OF THE HIGHEST NUMBER OF
TRAFFIC FATALITIES. AT THE SAME TIME, TRAFFIC
CITATIONS HAVE DROPPED BY 95% THE PAST DECADE.
THIS DECREASE IN ENFORCEMENT ENABLES MANY DRIVERS TO SKIRT
TRAFFIC LAWS PUTTING PEDESTRIANS, CYCLISTS AND OTHER
ROAD USERS AT SERIOUS RISK. THAT'S WHY I'M CALLING FOR A
HEARING TO EXAMINE THE ROOT CAUSE OF OUR DECLINING TRAFFIC
ENFORCEMENT AND ITS CONNECTION TO PUBLIC SAFETY.
WE NEED A CLEAR PICTURE OF HOW THE POLICE DEPARTMENT'S TRAFFIC
COMPANY OPERATES TODAY HOW RESOURCES ARE ALLOCATED
AND WHAT PLANS ARE IN PLACE TO REBUILD THIS CRITICAL FUNCTION
WITHIN OUR POLICE DEPARTMENT. THANKS AGAIN PRESIDENT MATLIN
FOR YOUR WILLINGNESS TO COLLABORATE ON THIS ISSUE.
I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING THE CITY
SERVICES AUDITOR WORK WITH SAN FRANCISCO.
SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS TO DEVELOP OBJECTIVE
AND MEASURABLE STANDARDS FOR STREETSCAPE PROJECTS, OPEN
SPACES AND PLANTED MEDIANS. 15 YEARS AGO SAN FRANCISCO
ADOPTED THE BETTER STREETS PLAN A COHESIVE VISION TO ENSURE WE
DESIGNED OUR STREETS FOR VIBRANCY FROM STREET TREES TO
SEATING AND DECORATIVE ELEMENTS TO BEAUTIFUL LANDSCAPING.
THESE STREETSCAPE PROJECTS HELPED COORDINATE MILLIONS OF
CITY INVESTMENTS INTO COMMUNITIES.
THESE INVESTMENTS ALSO HELP PROMOTE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT
AND COMMUNITY IDENTITY AND COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS
THROUGHOUT THE CITY. WE HAVE HUNDREDS OF ACRES OF
CITY MANAGED PUBLIC OPEN SPACES, NATURALIZED AREAS
PLANTED MEDIANS AND LANDSCAPED ASSETS.
THESE SPACES PROVIDE MANY BENEFITS TO OUR RESIDENTS
OFFERING SHADE RETAINING STORMWATER AND REDUCING AIR
POLLUTION. YET ALL TOO OFTEN A WINTER
STORM OR A VEHICLE CRASH TAKES OUT SEVERAL TREES ON A
STREETSCAPE PROJECT OR AN IRRIGATION SYSTEM FAILS.
SUDDENLY EVERYTHING WE INVESTED IN PUBLIC LANDSCAPING
AND INFRASTRUCTURE LOOKS NEGLECTED AND IN NEED OF
REPAIR. IT DOESN'T HAVE TO BE THIS WAY.
WE HAVE SOME OF THE MOST TALENTED AND SKILLFUL WORKERS
ANYWHERE IN THE COUNTRY. I KNOW WE CAN MAINTAIN THE
BEAUTIFUL THINGS WE BUILT AS POLICYMAKERS.
OUR CHALLENGE IS UNDERSTANDING WHAT RESOURCE IS PUBLIC WORKS
NEEDS TO KEEP OUR STREETSCAPES GREEN AND WELL-MAINTAINED.
THIS RESOLUTION IS A FIRST STEP.
IT ASKS THE CITY TO CREATE OBJECTIVE MEASURES
AND MAINTENANCE STANDARDS FOR OUR STREETSCAPES AND LANDSCAPED
AREAS. >> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES AND THE
REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIOLA SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF THE GOLDEN STATE
VALKYRIES AND THEIR EFFORTS ALONG WITH THE WOMEN'S NATIONAL
BASKETBALL PLAYERS ASSOCIATION TO SECURE A FAIR COLLECTIVE
BARGAINING AGREEMENT AND EQUAL COMPENSATION FOR WNBA ATHLETES.
THE BOUNDARIES ARE THE NEWEST FRANCHISE IN THE WNBA AND THEIR
DEBUT SEASON. THEY'VE ALREADY BROKEN RECORDS
WITH TEN STRAIGHT SOLD OUT GAMES AT CHASE CENTER
AND HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF FANS TUNING IN.
>> THEY'RE NOT JUST A TEAM. THEY'RE A MOVEMENT THAT WOMEN'S
PROFESSIONAL SPORTS ARE COMMERCIALLY VIABLE, CULTURALLY
POWERFUL AND HERE TO STAY. >> DESPITE THIS UNDENIABLE
SUCCESS, WNBA PLAYERS STILL EARN JUST A FRACTION OF THEIR
NBA COUNTERPARTS. >> MANY ARE FORCED TO PLAY
OVERSEAS IN THE OFF SEASON RISKING INJURY AND EVEN THEIR
SAFETY JUST TO MAKE ENDS MEET. THESE ATHLETES ARE DOING
EVERYTHING RIGHT SHOWING UP, FILLING STADIUMS, SELLING OUT
JERSEYS AND YET THERE'S STILL BEING UNDERPAID.
LAST YEAR THE WNBA BPA EXERCISED ITS RIGHT TO OPT OUT
OF THE CURRENT BARGAINING AGREEMENT.
AND THIS YEAR PLAYERS ACROSS THE LEAGUE INCLUDING THE
VALKYRIES MADE THEIR DEMANDS VISIBLE AND UNDENIABLE BY
WEARING SHIRTS AT THE ALL-STAR GAME READING QUOTE PAY US WHAT
YOU OWE US. >> THIS RESOLUTION REAFFIRMS
SAN FRANCISCO'S LONGSTANDING LEADERSHIP ON GENDER EQUITY
AND LABOR RIGHTS. IT'S ABOUT BACKING UP OUR
VALUES WITH ACTION SUPPORTING ATHLETES WHO ARE DEMANDING WHAT
EVERY WORKER DESERVES A FAIR CONTRACT THAT REFLECTS THEIR
CONTRIBUTIONS AND THEIR WORTH. >> THE VALKYRIE'S PRESENCE
IN SAN FRANCISCO IS MORE THAN A FRANCHISE.
IT'S A CULTURAL INSTITUTION IN THE MAKING.
IT'S A BEACON TO YOUNG WOMEN AND GIRLS ESPECIALLY IN THE BAY
AREA WHO CAN NOW SEE THEMSELVES REFLECTED ON A PROFESSIONAL
STAGE. BUT VISIBILITY IS NOT ENOUGH.
REPRESENTATION MUST BE MATCHED BY EQUITY.
>> I WANT TO THANK EARLY CO-SPONSORS ON THIS RESOLUTION.
SUPERVISORS MAHMUD DORSEY CHEN MELGAR AND WALTON.
>> I WANT TO THANK THE PLAYERS OF THE VALKYRIES AND THE WNBA
FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP AND COURAGE.
THIS FIGHT IS BIGGER THAN BASKETBALL.
THIS IS ABOUT LABOR JUSTICE, GENDER EQUITY AND THE FUTURE OF
PROFESSIONAL SPORTS. >> I URGE MY COLLEAGUES TO
STAND WITH OUR HOME TEAM WITH WOMEN ATHLETES AND WITH
EVERYONE WHO BELIEVES THAT EQUAL WORK DESERVES EQUAL PAY.
LET'S SEND A MESSAGE LOUD AND CLEAR.
>> PAY THEM WHAT THEY'RE OWED. I ALSO WANT TO INTRODUCE A
RESOLUTION TODAY TO DESIGNATE AUGUST 2ND, 2025 AS PETE
ESCOVEDO DAY IN HONOR OF THE BAY AREA LEGENDARY
PERCUSSIONIST AND RENOWNED VISUAL ARTIST WHO HELPED UPLIFT
LATIN JAZZ ON THE WEST COAST MENTORED BY TITO PUENTE
AND INVITED OUR TOUR WITH THIS NORTHERN COKE BY SANTANA.
PETE WAS HONORED WITH A LATIN GRAMMY LIFETIME ACHIEVEMENT
AWARD IN 2021 ALONGSIDE HIS DAUGHTER SHEILA E PETE ESCOVEDO
TURNED 90 YEARS OLD LAST MONTH AND IS STILL GOING STRONG.
PINA'S BEEN PLAYING MUSIC AND PAINTING SINCE HE WAS
IN HIS EARLY TEENS GROWING UP IN OAKLAND AND HE HAS CREATED A
BODY OF WORK IN BOTH GENRES THAT IS ON ASPIRING.
HE ALSO GREW UP PLAYING AT THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR
LATINO ARTS DRUMMING AND EVENTS FROM THE START OF M.C. CLAY
HISTORY IN THE 1970S. TO THIS DAY PETE'S WORK IS
CELEBRATED RIGHT NOW AT THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER WITH A
COMPREHENSIVE AND MULTIDISCIPLINARY ART
AND MUSIC EXHIBIT THAT RUNS THROUGH AUGUST 2ND, 2025 THE
DAY OF THE CLOSING CEREMONY. I ENCOURAGE YOU ALL TO GO
AND SEE THE BOLD TEXTURED PAINTINGS AS A REPLICA OF HIS
DRUM SET. VIDEOS OF HIS MUSIC IN ACTION
AND MEMORABILIA FROM HIS STORIED CAREER BEFORE THE
EXHIBIT CLOSES. >> I WANT TO THANK MARTINA
AYALA FROM SELAH AND EARLY CO-SPONSOR SUPERVISORS MELGAR
AND WALTON. I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK MR.
ESCOVEDO FOR HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO MUSIC, ART AND CULTURE
IN THE BAY AREA SAN FRANCISCO AND ESPECIALLY DISTRICT NINE.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR AMONG MY COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS
MY HONOR TO INTRODUCE FOR THE FIRST TIME EVER AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO A RESOLUTION DECLARING JULY 18TH
TO AUGUST 17TH AS SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH.
>> SAN FRANCISCO IS HOME TO A VIBRANT AND GROWING SOUTH ASIAN
COMMUNITY INCLUDING BOTH RECENT IMMIGRANTS
AND MULTIGENERATIONAL SOUTH ASIAN AMERICANS WITH ANCESTRAL
ROOTS IN AFGHANISTAN, BANGLADESH, BHUTAN, INDIA, THE
MALDIVES, NEPAL, PAKISTAN AND SRI LANKA EACH CONTRIBUTING
MEANINGFULLY TO THE CITY'S CIVIC, CULTURAL AND ECONOMIC
FABRIC. THE PRESENCE OF SOUTH ASIAN
IMMIGRANTS IN SOUTH ASIAN AMERICANS IN SAN FRANCISCO
PRECEDES THE GOLD RUSH MAKING SIGNIFICANT CONTRIBUTIONS TO
SAN FRANCISCO THROUGH THEIR LEADERSHIP AND WORK IN SMALL
BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY, EDUCATION AND SO MANY OTHER SECTORS.
>> TODAY MEMBERS OF THE SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY LIVE AND WORK
ACROSS OUR CITY CONTRIBUTING TO OUR ECONOMIC VITALITY THROUGH
SMALL BUSINESSES, RESTAURANTS, FAMILY RUN STORES, PROFESSIONAL
SERVICES AND INNOVATION DRIVEN INDUSTRIES WHILE ENRICHING THE
CULTURAL AND CIVIC FABRIC OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THE SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY HAS ALSO FACED SIGNIFICANT
CHALLENGES INCLUDING EXCLUSION UNDER EARLY U.S. IMMIGRATION
LAWS RACIAL AND RELIGIOUS DISCRIMINATION, SURVEILLANCE
AND XENOPHOBIA. MOST NOTABLY IN THE EARLY 1900S
AND THE ONSLAUGHT OF STRUCTURAL ISLAMOPHOBIA AND BROAD RACIST
SENTIMENT FOLLOWING THE ATTACKS OF SEPTEMBER 11TH WHICH DEFINED
AN ENTIRE ERA OF OUR HISTORY AS WELL AS ONGOING ANTI-SIKH
AND ANTI-HINDU DISCRIMINATION IN THAT HAVE IMPACTED SOUTH
ASIAN COMMUNITIES ACROSS LINES OF FAITH AND IDENTITY YET HAS
CONTINUED TO ORGANIZE BUILD COALITIONS AND FIGHT FOR EQUITY
JUSTICE AND FOR CIVIC INCLUSION.
>> SOUTH ASIANS IN SAN FRANCISCO HAVE BEEN AT THE
FOREFRONT OF ADVOCACY FOR IMMIGRANT RIGHTS, GENDER
EQUALITY, LGBTQ I PLUS REPRESENTATION WORKERS
PROTECTIONS AMONGST MANY OTHER ISSUES.
>> SO COLLEAGUES, I HOPE YOU'LL JOIN ME IN RECOGNIZING SOUTH
ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH CELEBRATING THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS
AS VISIBILITY AND LIVED EXPERIENCES OF SO MANY SOUTH
ASIAN RESIDENTS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I HOPE YOU'LL JOIN US WITH THE MAYOR'S PROCLAMATION TOMORROW
AS WELL TOMORROW AFTERNOON. AND LASTLY I WANT TO THANK
COAUTHOR CHAUDHRY FROM THE IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION FOR
HER HELP IN SPONSORING AND WRITING THIS RESOLUTION
AND FOR HER WORK TOMORROW AS WELL.
THE MAYOR'S PROCLAMATION AND SECOND COLLEAGUES I AM
REQUESTING A HEARING TO INVESTIGATE THE CONDITIONS OF A
REENTRY FACILITY AT 111 TAYLOR AND THE ONGOING ROLE OF ITS
OPERATOR ICE CONTRACTOR AND PRIVATE PRISON CORPORATION
GEO GROUP IN SAN FRANCISCO FOLLOWING THE DEATH OF MELVIN
BALOGUN WHILE IN THE FACILITY'S CARE.
>> IT'S HEARTBREAKING TO HEAR WHAT THE BALOGUN FAMILY HAS
EXPERIENCED. >> NO CHILD SHOULD HAVE TO LOSE
A PARENT UNDER SUCH CIRCUMSTANCES AND IT TAKES
GREAT COURAGE AND STRENGTH TO TURN PAIN INTO ACTION
AND ADVOCACY AND I HOPE TO GET ANSWERS.
>> AT LAST WEEK'S REENTRY COUNCIL MEETING WE HEARD OF THE
TRAGIC DEATH OF AN IMMIGRANT AND SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT
MELVIN BALOGUN. UNDER THE CARE OF THE HALFWAY
HOUSE TAYLOR STREET FACILITY, MR. BALOGUN'S CHILDREN SPOKE
OUT TO DEMAND JUSTICE AT LAST WEEK'S REENTRY COUNCIL
RECOUNTING RECEIVING CALLS FROM THEIR FATHER IN DISTRESS
STATING HE WOULD RATHER BE BACK IN PRISON THAN AT THIS
FACILITY. >> AND SHORTLY AFTER HE WAS
FOUND DEAD DECEASED ON THE STREETS OF THE TENDERLOIN.
>> AFTER IDENTIFYING THEIR FATHER'S BODY, THE FAMILY
CONTACTED THEIR FATHER'S PAROLE OFFICER AT GEO GROUP WHO
CLAIMED THAT THEY HAD NO KNOWLEDGE THAT HE HAD LEFT
THEIR FACILITIES. THIS FOLLOWS ESCALATING
CONCERNS RAISED BY COMMUNITY MEMBERS DURING PUBLIC COMMENT
AT THE BOARD OF APPEALS OF NEGLECT ABUSE AND CIVIL RIGHTS
VIOLATIONS AT THE REENTRY FACILITY LOCATED AT 111 TAYLOR
IN THE TENDERLOIN. >> FOR CONTEXT, THE FACILITY AT
111 TAYLOR IS OPERATED BY GEO GROUP, A MULTI-BILLION BILLION
DOLLAR PRIVATE PRISON GROUP HOLDING BILLIONS OF DOLLARS
IN CONTRACTS WITH ICE ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
>> AND THE 111 TAYLOR SITE IS A HISTORIC SIGNIFICANCE TO THE
COMMUNITY AS THE BIRTH OF THE TRANS RESISTANCE DURING THE
COMPTON CAFETERIA RIOT. BUT UNFORTUNATELY IT HAS BEEN
OPERATED BY GEO GROUP AS A HALFWAY HOUSE SINCE ACQUIRING
THE SITE IN 1989. >> GIVEN THE ALARMING CONCERNS
RAISED BY RESIDENTS, THE PURPOSE OF THIS HEARING WILL BE
TO ASK QUESTIONS REGARDING LIVING CONDITIONS AT THE
FACILITY AND INVESTIGATE REPORTS OF CIVIL RIGHTS
VIOLATIONS. LASTLY, AS SUCH IN HONOR OF
MELVIN BALOGUN, I'D LIKE TO ADJOURN OUR MEETING IN HIS
MEMORY IN MEMORIAM. BEFORE COMING TO AMERICA,
MELVIN SPENT HIS EARLY YEARS IN THE PHILIPPINES WHERE HIS
ENERGY, JOY AND FEARLESS SPIRIT WERE IMPOSSIBLE TO MISS.
AS A LITTLE BOY HE WAS FULL OF LIFE, MISCHIEVOUS AND THE MOST
LOVABLE WAY. >> HE WAS ALWAYS GETTING INTO
TROUBLE NOT OUT OF DEFIANCE BUT SIMPLY BECAUSE HE FOLLOWED
WHATEVER BROUGHT HIM JOY. RUNNING BAREFOOT WITH FRIENDS,
CLIMBING TREES IN THE PROVINCE AND EXPLORING EVERY CORNER OF
HIS WORLD, MELVIN WORE HIS SCRAPES AND BRUISES LIKE
TROPHIES. COVERED IN SWEAT AND DIRT.
HE WOULD COME HOME BEAMING AS IF HE HAD PLAYED UNTIL THE SUN
CAME UP. >> HE OFTEN JOKED THAT HE
LEARNED HOW TO RUN FROM TRYING TO AVOID GETTING CASTIGATED.
>> TRUE TO HIS NATURE HE WAS A JOY A NATURAL JOKESTER WHO LOVE
MAKING PEOPLE LAUGH. >> THAT JOY, THAT SENSE OF
FREEDOM AND FUN REMAINED A PART OF HIM EVEN AS HE GREW OLDER.
>> AFTER MANY YEARS OF WAITING, HIS MOTHER MILLIE MADE IT BACK
TO THE PHILIPPINES AFTER ESTABLISHING RESIDENCY IN THE
UNITED STATES. >> AT JUST 11 YEARS OLD.
MELVIN BEGAN A NEW CHAPTER OF LIFE RIGHT HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> HE ATTENDED POTRERO HILL
MIDDLE SCHOOL WHERE HE ADJUSTED TO A NEW COUNTRY WITH
DETERMINATION AND GRADUATED WITH HIS HIGH SCHOOL DIPLOMA
FROM GALILEO HIGH SCHOOL. >> DESPITE THE CHALLENGES HE
KEPT HIS WARMTH, HIS HUMILITY AND HIS GIFT FOR CONNECTING
WITH OTHERS. >> HE WAS ACTIVE, ENERGETIC
AND FULL OF LAUGHTER WITH A QUIET STRENGTH THAT LEFT A
LASTING IMPRESSION. >> HE MADE FRIENDS EASILY
AND ALWAYS FOUND WAYS TO BRING JOY TO THOSE AROUND HIM.
>> HE GAVE GENEROUSLY OF HIMSELF NOT ONLY THROUGH THE
THINGS HE PROVIDED BUT THROUGH THE PERSON HE WAS.
HE SHOWED UP. HE REMEMBERED BIRTHDAYS
AND FAVORITE MEALS. HE OFFERED ADVICE WHEN NEEDED
AND COMFORT WHEN WORDS FELL SHORT.
>> EVEN DURING HARD TIMES HIS CHILDREN NEVER QUESTIONED
WHETHER HE LOVED THEM. >> HIS PRESENCE WAS CONSTANT
AND HIS DEVOTION UNWAVERING. MELVIN WAS THEIR FIRST PLACE.
>> THEIR SAFE SPACE. THEIR BIGGEST SUPPORTER
AND THEIR GREATEST TEACHER IN THE LESSONS THAT MATTERED
MOST LOVE, ENDURANCE, HUMILITY AND JOY.
MAY HIS MEMORY FOREVER BE A BLESSING AND ONE ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT I BELIEVE HIS FAMILY IS HERE AS WELL.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> HOW ARE YOUR SONS? THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM AND THREE PIECES OF
LEGISLATION. I WILL TRY NOT TO TALK TOO MUCH
. I AM TODAY HONORING THE LIFE OF
MAUREEN DOWLING, A REMARKABLE SAN FRANCISCAN AND PROUD
IMMIGRANT FROM IRELAND WHO PASSED AWAY THIS WEEK.
>> BORN IN 1925 IN IRELAND, MAUREEN LIVED A LIFE OF
COURAGE, SERVICE AND GRACE. AT THE AGE OF 17 DURING THE
HEIGHT OF WORLD WAR TWO, SHE BOARDED A SHIP BOUND FOR LONDON
WHERE SHE WORKED FOR YEARS AS A NURSE CARING FOR WOUNDED
SAILORS AND CIVILIANS DURING SOME OF HISTORY'S DARKEST DAYS.
AFTER THE WAR SHE RETURNED HOME TO IRELAND WHERE SHE MET
PATRICK DOWLING, A FELLOW ADVENTURER FROM HER VILLAGE.
THE TWO MARRIED AND BEGAN THEIR JOURNEY TO AMERICA SETTLING
FIRST IN EUREKA VALLEY AND THEN MADE THEIR HOME IN INGLESIDE
TERRACES WHERE THEY RAISED SIX CHILDREN AND BECAME ACTIVE
IN ST STEPHEN'S PARISH. MAUREEN WAS A DEVOTED MOTHER
WHO ENCOURAGED HER CHILDREN TO BE INDEPENDENT AND PURSUE THEIR
DREAMS. SHE WAS A FOUNDING MEMBER OF
THE UNITED IRISH CULTURAL CENTER AND THE PATRICK DOWLING
LIBRARY LEAVING A LEGACY OF COMMUNITY AND CULTURAL PRIDE
THAT WILL ENDURE MANY GENERATIONS.
>> SHE IS SURVIVED BY HER DAUGHTER CECILIA, PATRICIA,
EILEEN, KATHLEEN AND COLLEEN. NINE GRANDCHILDREN, FIVE GREAT
GRANDCHILDREN AND TWO GREAT GREAT GRANDCHILDREN.
ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO, WE'D LIKE TO EXPRESS OUR DEEPEST
CONDOLENCES TO THE DOWNIE FAMILY.
MAY SHE REST IN PEACE. >> COLLEAGUES EARLIER THIS
SPRING I SHARED DRAFTING A REQUEST TO PROVIDE A PROACTIVE
PLAN FOR THE PENDING REZONING PACKAGE THAT IS INTRODUCED BY
THE MAYOR TO THIS BOARD. WE WILL BE CONSIDERING IT
IN THE FALL TO MEET OUR OBLIGATIONS AND COMMITMENTS
IN THE HOUSING ELEMENT. I AM TODAY INTRODUCING THE
FIRST PART OF A REZONING RESPONSE IN READINESS PACKAGE.
AS ONE OF THE SUPERVISORS WHO REPRESENTS THE WEST SIDE WHICH
COMPRISES MOST OF THIS NEWLY ZONED AREA IS IMPORTANT TO ME
THAT WE PROTECT EXISTING RENT CONTROLLED UNITS.
WHILE WE ENCOURAGE SMART DEVELOPMENT OF HOUSING TO MEET
THE DIFFERENT NEEDS OF RESIDENTS ACROSS THE SPECTRUM
IN I BELIEVE WE CAN DO BOTH. >> WE NEED A RANGE OF OPTIONS
THAT I'M SORRY I'M SO SORRY I'M JUST HAVING COMPUTER PROBLEMS
HERE. WE NEED A RANGE OF OPTIONS TO
MEET THE DIFFERENT HOUSING REQUIREMENTS THAT OUR RESIDENTS
NEED. >> A LARGE PART FOR A LARGE
PART OF OUR HISTORY WE HAVE NOT FOCUSED ON ADDING NEW UNITS ON
THE WEST SIDE AFFORDABLE OR OTHERWISE.
AND IT IS NOW THE TIME TO BE CREATIVE IN SERVING THE
DIFFERENT NEEDS OF DIFFERENT HOUSEHOLD.
THE FIRST PIECE OF LEGISLATION THAT I'M BRINGING FORWARD IS AN
EXPANSION OF THE OPTIONS UNDER INCLUSIONARY ORDINANCE FOR THE
WELL-RESOURCED NEIGHBORHOODS SO THAT DEVELOPERS HAVE DIFFERENT
WAYS TO MEET THAT OBLIGATION. DEVELOPERS WILL BE ABLE TO
CHOOSE BETWEEN INCLUDING THE REQUIRED BELOW MARKET RATE
UNITS WITHIN THEIR DEVELOPMENT PAYING THE INCLUSIONARY FEE OR
DEDICATING LAND JUST LIKE WE HAVE IN THE EASTERN
NEIGHBORHOODS PLAN. ANOTHER OPTION ALSO WILL BE TO
MAKE ALL OF THEIR UNITS IN THEIR BUILDINGS SUBJECT TO
RENT CONTROL FROM THE GET GO. I BELIEVE WE NEED TO EXPAND THE
TOOLS TO BRING RENTAL HOUSING TO THE WEST SIDE AS WELL AS
ADDRESS THE REAL PROBLEM THAT OUR RENT CONTROL STOCK IS
DIMINISHING OVER TIME. >> WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
POTENTIALLY CREATE NEW RENT CONTROLLED UNITS WHICH WILL
HELP US SUSTAIN AFFORDABILITY OVER TIME.
>> THE OTHER KEY TO MAKING THIS PLAN WORK IS FINDING WAYS TO
ADD TO OUR AFFORDABLE HOUSING STOCK AND THE FINANCING.
FOR TOO LONG WE HAVE RELIED ON TAX CREDITS AND INCLUSIONARY
FEES FOR MARKET RATE DEVELOPMENTS WHICH ARE SUBJECT
TO THE WHIMS OF THE MARKET. WHAT HAPPENS IS THAT THE
PRODUCTION OF UNITS IS COUNTERCYCLICAL.
WHEN WE HAVE GOOD TIMES IN THE MARKET THOSE FEES ARE BEING
PAID INTO THE FUND BUT THEN LAND BECOMES REALLY EXPENSIVE
AND NONPROFIT DEVELOPERS HAVE TO COMPETE WITH FOR PROFIT
DEVELOPERS FOR THE ACQUISITION OF LAND.
WE NEED NEW FINANCING TOOLS THAT ARE COUNTER-CYCLICAL SO
THAT WE CAN CAPTURE SOME OF THE NEW VALUE OF THE TREES OWN
PROPERTIES TO BENEFIT BUILDING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO EXPRESS INTEREST IN THE
FORMATION OF AN ENHANCED INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCE DISTRICT
FOR WELL-RESOURCED NEIGHBORHOODS FOR AFFORDABLE
HOUSING CREATION THAT ENCOMPASSES THE REUSE OWNED
AREAS. THIS IS A LONG TERM STRATEGY
THAT WILL USE THE INCREMENTAL INCREASES OF FUTURE PROPERTY
TAXES FROM THESE REZONING PROPERTIES TO REINVEST
IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND OTHER INFRASTRUCTURE NEEDS.
>> THERE ARE A LOT OF QUESTIONS ABOUT THIS APPROACH.
WE'VE NEVER DONE IT BEFORE AND IT IS TIME TO BE CREATIVE.
THIS RESOLUTION REQUESTS THE COMPTROLLER AND THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AS
WELL AS THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING TO PROVIDE
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR US THIS FALL TO CRUNCH THE NUMBERS
AND TO EXPLORE OPTIONS WITH US SO THAT WE CAN EXPLORE THIS
FINANCING TOOL TOWARDS OUR COLLECTIVE GOAL.
LASTLY, I AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO ESTABLISH A
SMALL BUSINESS REZONING CONSTRUCTION RELIEF FUND
AND PROGRAM SO THAT WE CAN BE PROACTIVE ABOUT THE POTENTIAL
RELOCATION AND OR CONSTRUCTION IMPACTS WHEN REZONING PROJECTS
COME TO FRUITION. THIS CAME FROM A STUDY I
REQUESTED FROM THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST A YEAR
AND A HALF AGO NOW THAT RECOMMENDED A MORE TARGETED
APPROACH TO PREPARE FOR ANY EFFECTS CAUSED BY DEVELOPMENT.
I WANT TO THANK DIRECTOR KATIE TANG AND HER TEAM FOR THEIR
INPUT AND THE SMALL BUSINESS ADVOCATES WHO HAVE ACTIVELY
CALLED FOR MORE SUPPORT. AGAIN THIS IS ONE OF THE PIECE
MANY PIECES THAT WE ARE DEVELOPING AS WELL AS TOOLS TO
PREVENT THE WHOLESALE WHOLESALE DISPLACEMENT OF OUR BELOVED
SMALL BUSINESS BUSINESSES. WE NEED OUR STATE LEGISLATURE
TO PROVIDE MORE PROTECTIONS AND SUPPORT AS WELL.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR LISTENING TO THIS PACKAGE AND I
EXPECT A ROBUST DISCUSSION WHEN THE TIME COMES SO WE CAN
COLLECTIVELY DEVELOP OUR RESPONSE.
THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. SUPERVISOR SUTTER.
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHIN.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES, I KNOW THERE'S
NO DEBATE WHEN WE SAY THAT LOCAL BUSINESS ARE THE BACKBONE
OF OUR ECONOMY. >> THIS BOARD HAS TIME
AND AGAIN FOUND WAYS TO SUPPORT OUR SMALL BUSINESSES THROUGH
PROGRAMS LIKE FIRST YEAR FREE TO LEGACY BUSINESS
AND NEIGHBORHOOD ANGERING BUSINESS REGISTRY.
AND WE DEDICATE OUR RESOURCES AND SUPPORT TO RECOGNIZE THEM
AND SUPPORT THEM. LOCAL BUSINESS.
OUR COMMUNITY SPACES AS MUCH AS THEY ARE PLACES OF COMMERCE
AND SERVICES WE SUPPORT THEM BECAUSE THEY HAVE GREAT
PRODUCTS AND SERVICES. BUT WE ALL KNOW IT FOR
ESPECIALLY FOR THOSE OF US FORTUNATE TO HAVE NEIGHBOR
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS, WE KNOW THAT IT IS ALL ABOUT THE PEOPLE
THE PEOPLE THAT OPERATE THEM AND MAKE IT WORK.
BUT EVEN AS WE RECOVER FROM PANDEMIC, WE KNOW THAT MANY OF
OUR BUSINESSES AND WORKERS ARE FACING UNCERTAINTY FROM THE
PRESSURE WITH TARIFFS TO THE UPCOMING LOCAL UP ZONING PLAN.
>> SO TO PROVIDE SUPPORT TO OUR BUSINESSES AND WORKERS I'M
ANNOUNCING TWO PIECES OF LEGISLATION TODAY AS A PACKAGE
THAT I HOPE THAT WE CAN SUPPORT OUR LOCAL BUSINESSES
AND WORKERS TO GATHER. THE FIRST IS FOR AN ORDINANCE
TO EXTEND EXISTING INTERIM ZONING CONTROL INTO A PERMANENT
ORDINANCE WHICH WOULD REQUIRE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
WHENEVER A NEW BUSINESS ATTEMPT TO DISPLACE A LEGACY BUSINESS.
AND I ALSO HOPE TO EXPAND IT INTO A NEIGHBORHOOD ANGERING
BUSINESS. THESE MOM AND POP SHOPS MAKE
SAN FRANCISCO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO AND NEIGHBORHOODS
UNIQUE AND ARE WHY SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE SO MUCH PRIDE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT WE LIVE SO MUCH SO THAT SOMETIMES
BECOMES A COMPETITION. INDEED WE KNOW IT.
YET DUE TO STATE LAW PREVENTION WHICH BROADLY DEFINES
COMMERCIAL RENT CONTROL, THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMUNITY
CONTINUES TO FACE ONGOING UNCERTAINTY AND A THREAT OF
DISPLACEMENT OFTEN AT THE WHIM OF RAPIDLY RISING RENT.
A ESPECIALLY AS THE MARKET ANTICIPATES FURTHER REAL ESTATE
SPECULATION. NOW WE ALL KNOW THOUGH WHEN A
BUSINESS IS FACING A TRANSITIONS THE WORKERS ARE
PART OF THE EQUATION. THEY SHOULD BE PART OF THE
EQUATION. THEY FACE THE SAME CHALLENGES
AS THE BUSINESS OWNERS WHEN THEY TRYING TO TRANSITION THEIR
BUSINESS AS WELL. SO THE SECOND PIECE OF
LEGISLATION I WOULD LIKE TO INTRODUCE IS THE WORKERS
OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT TO CREATE A PATHWAY FOR EXISTING
WORKERS TO PURCHASE A BUSINESS AS A COOPERATIVE WHEN THE OWNER
INTENDS TO SELL. THIS LEGISLATION IS A TOOL WILL
HELP CONTINUE TO SUPPORT BUSINESS AND WORKERS AS THEY
FIND WAYS TO TRANSITION THEIR FUTURE.
WE WANT TO EMPOWER OUR WORKERS TO HAVE A COLLABORATIVE
CONVERSATION AND WITH THEIR BUSINESS OWNERS.
WHEN A BUSINESS CLOSES THE NEIGHBORHOOD LOSES A TREASURE
INSTITUTION AND WORKERS ALSO SUFFER.
THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT WILL SUPPORT
LONGTIME BUSINESS OWNERS WITH A SUCCESSION PLAN.
SUPPORT WORKERS AND EMPOWER THEM TO BECOME ENTREPRENEURS
AND STABILIZE OUR BELOVED NEIGHBORHOODS.
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS. >> AGAIN, THESE ARE LEGISLATIVE
TOOLS THAT WE WANT TO PROVIDE BUSINESS AND WORKERS AND REALLY
KEEP THEM WHERE THEY'RE AT SO THAT THEY CAN CONTINUE TO
THRIVE. AND I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
COLLEAGUES WHEN THEY COME BEFORE YOU THIS FALL TO THIS
FALL THIS YEAR AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUPERVISOR CHIN SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. ROLL CALL LAST FOR THE BEST.
>> BEST FOR LAST. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
I HAVE A COUPLE OF RESOLUTIONS AND AN IN MEMORIAM AND IF THAT
IS ALL RIGHT WITH SUPERVISOR DORSEY I WOULD ASK TO BE ADDED
TO HIS IN MEMORIAM FOR DAN DILLON AS WELL.
ALL RIGHT. MY FIRST RESOLUTION COLLEAGUES
AS YOU MAY RECALL BACK IN 2023 DISTRICTS SIX SUPERVISOR MATT
DORSEY AUTHORED A RESOLUTION DECLARING JULY 28TH AND 29TH
TAYLOR SWIFT WEEKEND IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE MISS SWIFT
WAS PERFORMING IN SANTA CLARA. >> NOW TONIGHT THE ONE AND ONLY
LADY GAGA WILL BE BRINGING HER CRITICALLY ACCLAIMED MAYHEM
BALL TOUR TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CHASE CENTER WHERE SHE WILL BE
JOINED BY THOUSANDS OF LITTLE MONSTERS INCLUDING A FEW OF MY
LEGISLATIVE AIDES. AS SHE PERFORMS HER NEW HITS
ABRACADABRA. >> VANISH INTO YOU?
AND HOW BAD DO YOU WANT ME? IT HAS BEEN POINTED OUT THAT IT
WOULD BE A GREAT WRONG FOR THIS BODY HAVING CHOSEN TO RECOGNIZE
MS.. SWIFT FOR HER SANTA CLARA
PERFORMANCES NOT AT THE VERY LEAST.
SIMILARLY TO RECOGNIZE GAGA ON THE OCCASION OF HER SAN
FRANCISCO PERFORMANCES. >> THE RESOLUTION I'M
INTRODUCING TODAY WILL AVOID THAT WRONG BY RECOGNIZING JULY
22ND, 2025 AS LADY GAGA DAY IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. I WANT TO THANK GAGA FOR
BRINGING THE ART OF PERSONAL CHAOS AND MAYHEM TO SAN
FRANCISCO. AND I WANT TO THANK LITTLE
MONSTER CALVIN FOR INSISTING THAT THIS BODY GET THIS RIGHT
ALSO. >> COLLEAGUES, I'M INTRODUCING
A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE AUGUST 4TH THROUGH AUGUST 20TH
THROUGH AUGUST 8TH, 2025 AS NATIONAL HEALTH CENTER WEEK
IN SAN FRANCISCO FORMED IN 1982, THE SAN FRANCISCO
COMMUNITY CLINIC CONSORTIUM IS A SHINING EXAMPLE OF THE
COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER LEGACY BORN OUT OF THE CIVIL RIGHTS
MOVEMENT OF THE 1960S. THESE CENTERS SEEK TO SERVE THE
UNDERSERVED AT A COST THEY CAN AFFORD.
TODAY THE CLINIC A CONSORTIUM IS COMPOSED OF 12 MEMBER
CLINICS THAT TAILOR THEIR SERVICES TO MEET THE UNIQUE
NEEDS OF THE COMMUNITY IN WHICH THEY ARE LOCATED.
SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTERS HAVE DELIVERED
CULTURALLY APPROPRIATE CARE AND IMPROVED LINGUISTIC ACCESS
TO MORE THAN 10% OF THE CITY'S POPULATION.
FOR THEIR PATIENTS THESE CENTERS ARE OFTEN THEIR ONLY
ACCESS TO PRIMARY CARE. THE RESOLUTION ACKNOWLEDGES SAN
FRANCISCO'S HEALTH CENTERS AND THEIR ONGOING EFFORTS TO
DELIVER INDIVIDUALIZED MEDICAL CARE TO THOSE WHO MIGHT NOT
OTHERWISE HAVE IT. EVEN IN EVEN AN INCREASINGLY
CHALLENGING TIMES, I WANT TO THANK JEAN ALON OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO COMMUNITY CLINIC CONSORTIUM FOR WORKING WITH US
ON THIS RESOLUTION. AS WELL AS SUPERVISORS WALTON
MELGAR, CHERYL CHAN CHEN AND ENGARDIO DORSI AND SAUTER
FOR THEIR CO-SPONSORSHIP. AND I WANT TO THANK BRAD PHELPS
IN MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK ON THIS INTRODUCTION.
AND LASTLY, I'M REQUESTING THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF CHRISTOPHER CHARLES BRUNETTI WHO DIED
EARLIER THIS MONTH FAR TOO SOON AT THE AGE OF 54.
CHRISTOPHER WAS BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO TO MARGENE
AND LUBER CANETTI WHO RESIDE IN NOVI VALLEY.
CHRIS ATTENDED SACRED HEART HIGH SCHOOL, SAN FRANCISCO
STATE UNIVERSITY AND GRADUATED FROM UC SANTA CRUZ WITH A
BACHELOR OF ARTS DEGREE IN ENGLISH LITERATURE.
A SAN FRANCISCO KID WHO GREW UP RIDING PUBLIC TRANSIT AND HIS
BICYCLE. HE HE WAS ALWAYS IN MOTION
AND LOVED RUNNING, SAILING AND BIKING.
CHRIS CO-FOUNDED THE TWIN PEAKS CYCLING CLUB AND LOVED COACHING
OTHERS WILLING AND EAGER TO SPREAD HIS KNOWLEDGE AND LOVE
FOR THE SPORT. HE ALSO RODE WITH THE MILLER
CREEK MIDDLE SCHOOL MOUNTAIN BIKING CLUB AND WAS A COACH OF
THE TERRA LINDA HIGH SCHOOL MOUNTAIN BIKING CLUB.
>> CHRIS AND HIS WIFE SARA WERE STRONG SUPPORTERS OF THE
MARINES SAFE ROUTES TO SCHOOLS PROGRAM WHICH TEACHES SAFE
BICYCLING AND PEDESTRIAN SAFETY SKILLS TO MORE THAN 29,000
STUDENTS AND THEIR DAUGHTER LUCIA WAS THE SAFE ROUTES TO
SCHOOL'S BIKE CHAMPION OF THE YEAR.
BEYOND HIS PASSION FOR CYCLING, CHRIS WAS MORE GENERALLY
SOMEONE WHO LIVED HIS LIFE HELPING OTHERS.
HIS WORK IN AUDIOLOGY AND AS A HEARING DEVICE SPECIALIST CAME
NATURALLY FROM HIS ABILITY TO LISTEN, UNDERSTAND AND HELP
THOSE IN NEED. HE WAS OUTGOING, OPTIMISTIC,
HILARIOUS, KIND AND QUICK TO MAKE NEW FRIENDS.
HE IS SURVIVED BY HIS WIFE AND LIFE PARTNER OF 30 YEARS
SARAH. WHEN OUR SKI AND THEIR
DAUGHTERS THIS YEAR AND GINGER REST IN PEACE CHRIS BRING
DANNY. >> MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A
BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMIT .
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. AT THE BEGINNING OF YOUR
COMMENTS DID YOU ASK FOR AN ITEM TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE
FULL BOARD OR ADDED I JUST ASK TO BE ADDED TO DAN DYLAN'S
ADDED TO DAN DYLAN NOTED THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE
INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. I THINK WE CAN GO BACK TO ITEM
48. >> YES.
AND JUST FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE NEW INTO THE CHAMBER, ITEM
48 IS AGAIN BEFORE THE BOARD TO BE CONSIDERED.
THIS ESTABLISHES RENEWS AND EXPANDS THE DOGPATCH
IN NORTH NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT.
>> AND MADAM CLERK CAN YOU READ THE RESULTS OF THE ELECTION?
>> YES. THE RETURNED WEIGHTED BALLOTS
VOTING FOR THE DOGPATCH AND NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL
GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT WAS 60.91% AND THE RETURN WEIGHTED
BALLOTS VOTING AGAINST THE DOGPATCH AND NORTHWEST POTRERO
HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT WAS 39.09%.
FURTHER INDICATING THERE IS NO MAJORITY PROTEST.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. SO AS THERE IS NO MAJORITY
PROTEST CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 48 ON ITEM 48
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDEL MEN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK I THINK THAT TAKES US TO PUBLIC
COMMENTS. >> YES.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG
THE CURTAINS YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED THE
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE ITEM 70 THROUGH 77
AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON TODAY'S PUBLISHED
AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT WILL HAVE BEEN REPORTED
OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE THE
PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT OCCURRED.
>> JUST A SPECIAL NOTE TO THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE HERE TO SPEAK IF
YOU WISH TO SPEAK DURING A GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU
CANNOT SPEAK ON THE BUDGET ITEMS ITEMS FIVE THROUGH 25 NOR
ON ITEM 26 WHICH IS THE LARGE AND COMMERCIAL VEHICLE PARKING
RESTRICTIONS IN THE AS THE PUBLIC TIME FRAME FOR BOTH
ITEMS HAS EXPIRED YOU WILL BE REDIRECTED AND MOVE WILL MOVE
ON TO THE NEXT SPEAKER IF YOU CONTINUE SO WE ARE SETTING THE
TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES. IF YOU WOULD LOOK AT THE PODIUM
YOUR TIMER IS ON THE PODIUM AND YOU CAN SEE WHERE YOU'RE AT
IN YOUR TWO MINUTES. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> OH YES, YOU BET. OKAY.
SO I DON'T KNOW ABOUT BEHIND ME BUT YOU GUILTY YOU JUST SPENT
ANOTHER BEATING ABOUT THE BUSH TO LATE THE PEDOPHILES IN THE
CONTROL OF THE GOVERNMENT SACRIFICE RIGHT OR TELL TOO FEW
MORE KIDS. >> YEAH THAT'S WHAT YOU DID
YEAH RIGHT NOW LIVE OKAY NOW SO THAT'S WHY I DON'T TALK TO YOU.
YOU YOU KNOW WHAT MY ORDERS FROM THESE GUYS ARE IS TO
CHANGE THE COURSE OF HUMANITY WITH THE PRECEDENT SET HERE
IN SOME FRONTS CISCO INCIDENTS. >> OKAY, SO NOW WE CAN'T
ACHIEVE THAT WITHOUT THIS BOOK REVOLUTION I INTRODUCED LEGEND
JERRY WHICH CONSISTS TO REUNITING US HUMAN BEINGS WITH
OUR FELLOW CREATURES ALL OF THEM EVERY SPECIES AND PLANTS
YOU KNOW, LIVING SPACES THAT'S A BIG ONE.
NOW IN ORDER TO DO THAT WE NEED TO DEFINE WHO IS A PEDOPHILE.
>> OH, NUTS. NOW WE KNOW FOR A FACT BECAUSE
THE EVIDENCE JUST HAS BEEN CLEAR ENOUGH QUITE RECENTLY
FROM WASHINGTON DC WE DON'T CARE THAT THERE IS A RING OF
PEDOPHILE CONTROLLING YOU. YEAH.
SO NOW IF YOU PLAY THAT GAME YOU BECOME A PEDOPHILE, YOU
UNDERSTAND? SO YOU DON'T WANT TO DO THAT I
THINK BECAUSE OTHERWISE NO MESSAGE YOU DISGUISE WE'LL GIVE
YOU KNOW MESSY BECAUSE PEDOPHILIC ACTIVITIES IS THE
ONLY CRIME YOU SEE THAT YOU CAN COMMIT WITHOUT ANY ACCUMULATING
CIRCUMSTANCE. >> YOU EITHER FAIL OR YOU ARE
NUTS. THAT'S IT.
SO LAW ENFORCEMENT NOW YOU GUYS HERE IF YOU DON'T UNDERSTAND
THAT THIS IS ADDRESSED TO YOU AS WELL NO MERCY.
UNDERSTAND WHAT NUMBER ONE YOU DON'T COMPLY WITH WHAT YOU ARE
TOLD TO DO. YOU SEE THAT STAGE THEN WE SEE
ARE WE SPEAK UP AND WE CALL OUT THIS BIT OF ICE ENOUGH OH THE
ALL RIGHT, LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
PLEASE WELCOME JEFFREY ALMOND. MR. MADAM AND THIS WAS OUTSIDE
JEFFREY YOU HAVE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD AS A WHOLE.
>> THIS IS A MEETING OUR LITTLE SECTION BECAUSE THIS WAS
OUTSIDE OF MR. AMENDMENT'S OFFICE BY HARVEY MILK
AND INJURY TO ONE IS AN INJURY TO YOUR NOW THE LAST BOARD A
SUPERVISOR PRESENT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND PESKIN HE SAID
THERE WOULD BE A CEASE FIRE I WANT TO HOLD BOARD TO VOTE ON
THAT RIGHT NOW BECAUSE THEY NEED FOOD AND THEY ISRAELIS ARE
KILLING THEM REGARDLESS. SO I WENT TO FULL BOARD TO VOTE
ON THAT RIGHT NOW AND IF YOU CAN'T THE END OF MR. BENJAMIN
MS. STEPPED DOWN AND THAT'S HOW I SEE IT BECAUSE HE WAS AGAINST
THAT WHEN AARON PESKIN AND MATT DORSEY AND STEPHANY'S IN THE
ASSEMBLY AND THAT'S WHAT I LIKE TO SEE HAPPEN RIGHT NOW.
YOU UNDERSTAND ALL OF YOU ARE AND IF YOU CAN'T DO IT NOW THEN
MR. AMENDMENT SHOULD CONSIDER STEPPING DOWN AND THAT'S HOW I
SEE IT. YOU UNDERSTAND THAT ANGELO
CAVIAR. >> DO YOU UNDERSTAND THAT,
JEFFREY THIS IS YOUR TURN TO TELL THE BOARD YOUR FEELINGS
KEEP GOING. >> YOU HAVE NO.
>> I WANT THE FULL BOARD TO VOTE ON THIS RIGHT NOW.
CAN YOU COOPERATE WITH ME? WHAT'S FUNNY ABOUT IT?
IF IT DOESN'T WORK THAT WAY, PLEASE CONTINUE.
A 40S LEFT IF HE YOU CAN'T ABIDE BY MY DESIRE AND I THINK
MR. BENJAMIN SHOULD STEP DOWN. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
HELLO LADIES MANDELMAN. MY NAME IS DAKOTA ROSE.
I AM CO-FOUNDER OF A LOCAL NONPROFIT CALLED TRANS VISIBLE
DIRECTOR OF MARKETING THERE AS WELL AND I'M ALSO A REENTRY
AND RESTORATIVE JUSTICE CONSORT AND I SIT ON THE REENTRY
SUBCOMMITTEE AS WELL IN A CITY I WAS COMPELLED TO COME IN TO
SPEAK TODAY ON BEHALF OF THE TRANS COMMUNITY AND ALL THE
ATROCITIES THAT ARE OCCURRING AT 111 TAYLOR WHICH IS A GEO
CAUGHT BRAND HOUSING DETAINED FACILITY, SMALL PRISON IN OUR
COMMUNITY ABOUT THREE YEARS AGO UPON MY RELEASE FROM PRISON I
WAS ACTUALLY IN 111 TAYLOR AND I WITNESSED QUITE A
SIGNIFICANT AMOUNT OF DYSFUNCTION TO SAY THE LEAST.
ONE IN PARTICULAR WAS MAY 29TH 2023 WHERE A MENTAL HEALTH
PATIENT CLOAKED UNDER PAROLEE WAS SENT THERE AND I WITNESSED
THIS MAN WALK OUT OF THE CARE OF THE GEO COURT REMANDED BY
THE STATE DEPARTMENT OF CALIFORNIA CORRECTIONS AND HE
WALKED INTO CHINATOWN AND STABBED A WOMAN.
THAT'S ONE OF MANY INCIDENTS THAT HAVE OCCURRED AT THIS
FACILITY AND IN MY POSITION HERE IN THIS COMMUNITY AS TRANS
AND AN ACTIVIST, I URGE CITY COUNCIL TO CONSIDER TRANS
AND OR PROPRIETORSHIP OF 111 TAYLOR, ALSO KNOWN AS THE
COMPTON CAFETERIA. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT WEEK.
>> HI. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS MY
NAME IS WILDER AZIZA AND I'M HERE TODAY ON BEHALF OF THE
COMPTON'S COALITION AND IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE FAMILY OF
MELVIN POLIAN. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
FOR INTRODUCING THE HEARING IN ADJOURNING TONIGHT'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF MELVIN I WANTED TO EMPOWER THE ENTIRE BOARD TO
STAND WITH OUR COMMUNITY IN DEMANDING ACCOUNTABILITY
FROM GEO GROUP AT YOUR HEARING THIS FALL, MELVIN DIED AFTER
BEING PLACED AT 111 TAYLOR STREET, A FACILITY OPERATED BY
GEO GROUP THE WORLD'S LARGEST PRIVATE PRISON CORPORATION.
BEFORE HIS PASSING, MELVIN TOLD HIS CHILDREN THAT HE'D RATHER
BE BACK IN PRISON THAN REMAIN AT THAT SO-CALLED REENTRY
CENTER GEO GROUP CLAIMS TO PROVIDE HOUSING AND SERVICES
BUT TIME AND TIME AGAIN THEY PROVIDE NEGLECT, SURVEILLANCE
AND HARM COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND FORMERLY INCARCERATED
PEOPLE HAVE TESTIFIED TO THE PRISON LIKE CONDITIONS RACIST
MISTREATMENT, EXTORTION, SEXUAL MISCONDUCT AND SEXUAL
AND PHYSICAL VIOLENCE AT 111 TAYLOR STREET.
YET THIS CITY HAS CONTINUED TO ALLOW THEM TO OPERATE ON A SITE
OF DEEPEST CALL MEANING TO THE TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY THE
COMPTON'S CAFETERIA RIOT WAS THE FIRST WELL-DOCUMENTED
UPRISING OF TRANS PEOPLE TAKING A STAND AGAINST POLICE
VIOLENCE. WE CANNOT ALLOW A CORPORATION
LIKE GEO GROUP TO PROFIT OFF OF OUR PAIN THEIR BUSINESS IS
IN INCARCERATION NOT CARE. THEIR CONTRACTS WITH ICE CDCR
AND THE F B O P EXPOSE SAN FRANCISCO TO BACK DOOR
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT AND CIVIL RIGHTS VIOLATIONS
IN OUR SANCTUARY CITY. IT IS LONG PAST TIME FOR A FULL
PUBLIC INVESTIGATION AND IT IS TIME TO SHUT THEM DOWN.
>> WE SUPPORT THIS SUBPOENA. WE SUPPORT THE HEARING AND WE
ASK THE BOARD TO TAKE REAL STEPS TOWARD ENDING GEO GROUP'S
PRESENCE IN SAN FRANCISCO SO THAT OUR COMMUNITY CAN SECURE
111 TAYLOR FOR COMMUNITY USE ROOTED IN JUSTICE AND IN
HEALING. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
NICE TO SEE YOU TOO. >> THEY START YES.
OKAY. GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS MOHAN AS YOU BODY
AND I'M DEEPLY HONORED TO STAND BEFORE YOU TODAY AS THE FIRST
AND ONLY AFGHAN AMERICAN LEGISLATIVE AIDE IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF ITEM 74.
LAST YEAR SAN FRANCISCO MADE HISTORY BY PASSING ITS FIRST
RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING AUGUST AS AFRICAN AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH. TODAY I'M PROUD TO RETURN WITH
A RENEWED RESOLUTION FOR AUGUST 2025 MARKING THE SECOND TIME
OUR CITY FORMALLY HONORS THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF AFRICAN
AMERICANS. THIS CONTINUED RECOGNITION
REFLECTS SAN FRANCISCO'S EVOLVING COMMITMENT TO
INCLUSION AND JUSTICE. AND I WANT TO SINCERELY THANK
ALL 11 SUPERVISORS WHO CO-SPONSORED THIS RESOLUTION
AND A HEARTFELT GRATITUDE TO MY SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR MATT
DORSEY WHOSE STEADFAST COMMITMENT AND UNWAVERING
SUPPORT HAVE BEEN A BEACON OF HOPE AND SOLIDARITY FOR MY
COMMUNITY. AS A PROUD MEMBER OF THE AFGHAN
DIASPORA, I'VE SEEN FIRSTHAND THE STRENGTH AND BRILLIANCE
THAT AFGHANS BRING TO THE CITY FROM BUSINESS OWNERS TO PUBLIC
SERVANTS TO HEALTH CARE WORKERS TO LAWYERS.
>> AFGHAN AMERICANS ARE AN INTEGRAL PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S FABRIC ROOTED NOT JUST IN SURVIVAL BUT
IN CONTRIBUTIONS, INNOVATIONS AND CARE.
THIS RESOLUTION IS NOT JUST CEREMONIAL.
IT'S PERSONAL. IT'S FOR THE PARENTS WHO'VE
LAID THE FOUNDATION FOR A BRIGHTER FUTURE.
IT'S FOR THE REFUGEES WHO CAME DRIVEN BY RESILIENCE AND A HOPE
FOR A BETTER FUTURE. AND AS FOR THE AFGHAN AMERICANS
WHO HAVE LIVED HERE FOR DECADES WITHOUT EVER SEEING THEMSELVES
REFLECTED IN THE DECISIONS THAT ARE MADE IN THIS DOME, THIS IS
MORE THAN A SYMBOLIC GESTURE. IT'S A REAFFIRMATION OF
BELONGING. IT'S A RECOGNITION THAT
REPRESENTATION TRANSFORMS NOT ONLY HOW WE ARE SEEN BUT WHAT
CAN BECOME POSSIBLE. THANK YOU ONCE AGAIN TO THIS
AMAZING BOARD AND HERE'S TO HAVING AN AMAZING AFRICAN
AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH. >> THANK YOU, MOHAMMED SOMEBODY
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT WEEK.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS GOOD ROTI CHAUDHRY
CONTINUOUS AND I SERVE AS THE VICE CHAIR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION. AND I'M THE FIRST SOUTH ASIAN
TO BE APPOINTED TO IT. I'M SPEAKING TODAY IN MY
PERSONAL CAPACITY AND STRONG SUPPORT OF THE SOUTH ASIAN
AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH RESOLUTION.
AS AN IMMIGRANT FROM INDIA TODAY FEELS EXCEPTIONALLY
PERSONAL FOR SO MANY OF US. OUR IDENTITIES HAVE LIVED
QUIETLY IN THE FOOD WE SHARE, THE WAY WE EAT OUR FOOD, THE
IMMIGRANT JOURNEYS WE HAVE HAD ,THE LANGUAGES WE SPEAK AT
HOME. THE HOLIDAYS WE CELEBRATE
BEHIND CLOSED DOORS BUT RARELY HAVE THEY BEEN SEEN, NAMED OR
AFFIRMED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT.
THIS RESOLUTION BEGINS TO CHANGE THAT.
IT TELLS THE SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY THAT YOU BELONG
IN THE STORY OF SAN FRANCISCO NOT JUST SOCIALLY OR
ECONOMICALLY BUT CIVICALLY. >> I'VE HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF
WORKING WITH SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND HIS TEAM ON THIS EFFORT.
AND I KNOW FIRSTHAND HOW DEEPLY MEANINGFUL THIS IS TO THE SOUTH
ASIANS OF THIS CITY. >> IT OPENS THE DOOR TO CITY
SPONSORED CULTURAL PROGRESS JAMMING LANGUAGE ACCESS FOR OUR
ELDERS AND VISIBILITY FOR YOUNG PEOPLE WHO HAVE NEVER SEEN
THEIR HERITAGE REFLECTED AT THE CITY LEVEL.
RESOLUTIONS LIKE THIS SHAPE PRECEDENT.
THEY'RE NOT JUST SYMBOLIC. THEY DEFINE WHO GETS REMEMBERED
,WHOSE EXPERIENCES MATTER AND WHO IS INVITED INTO THE
FUTURE WE'RE ALL BUILDING TOGETHER.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH, SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR
INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION. >> I URGE YOU ALL TO PASS THIS
RESOLUTION UNANIMOUSLY. LET THIS BE MORE THAN A
MILESTONE. LET IT BE THE START OF A DEEPER
PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN SAN FRANCISCO AND ITS SOUTH ASIAN
RESIDENTS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, COMMISSIONER CHOWDHURY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. HI.
HELLO. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS HOPE WILLIAMS. I AM A DISTRICT EIGHT RESIDENT
AND DIRECTOR OF LEGISLATIVE ADVOCACY FOR THE SUSTAINABLE
ECONOMIES LAW CENTER. >> I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHAN TUTTLE LAW GROUP, SEIU U H W UFC W LOCAL FIVE AND BENJIE
KAPLAN SHOP STEWARD FOR GREEN APPLE BOOKS FOR CO-DEVELOPING
THE WORK ROBERT OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT WITH THE LAW
CENTER I'M SPEAKING TODAY IN STRONG SUPPORT OF THE
PROPOSED ORDINANCE WHICH WOULD GIVE WORKERS THE FIRST
OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE WHEN THE BUSINESS GOES UP FOR SALE
WHEN I BELIEVE LOCAL BUSINESSES PUT UP FOR SALE THE EMPLOYEES
THE PEOPLE WHO KNOW HOW IT RUNS, WHO BUILT RELATIONSHIPS
WITH CUSTOMERS AND WHO'VE CONTRIBUTED THEIR LABOR FOR
YEARS SHOULD HAVE THE FIRST OPPORTUNITY TO CARRY IT
FORWARD. THIS ORDINANCE GIVES WORKERS A
REAL SHOT AT OWNERSHIP. THIS ORDINANCE GIVES THEM THE
TOOLS TO DO JUST THAT AND IT CREATES A PATHWAY FOR WORKER
COOPERATIVES, PROVIDES CRITICAL LEGAL AND FINANCIAL SUPPORT
AND ENSURES THAT EVERY BUSINESS HAS A UNION.
THOSE RIGHTS REMAIN PROTECTED. IT HONORS THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF
LONGTIME BUSINESS OWNERS BY PRESERVING THEIR LEGACY AND IT
HELPS KEEP SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS ROOTED
IN PEOPLE NOT JUST PROFITS. >> THIS ORDINANCE IS A
COMMUNITY CENTERED APPROACH TO PREVENTING SPECULATION, ASSET
STRIPPING AND DISPLACEMENT IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THIS IS ABOUT ECONOMIC DEMOCRACY.
>> IT'S ABOUT BUILDING WEALTH FROM THE BOTTOM UP AND IT'S
ABOUT MAKING SURE WORKERS AND NEIGHBORHOODS HAVE A VOICE
IN WHAT HAPPENS WHEN OWNERSHIP CHANGES HANDS.
PLEASE SUPPORT THIS VITAL LEGISLATION.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU COMMISSIONER WILLIAMS
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. HELLO ESTEEMED SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS MOUSSA TAREK WITH CARE THE COUNCIL ON
AMERICAN-ISLAMIC RELATIONS AND WE WANT TO EXPRESS OUR
STRONG SUPPORT FOR THE RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING SOUTH
ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I WANT TO START ON A PERSONAL NOTE.
I WAS BORN IN PAKISTAN COMING TO THE UNITED STATES AS A FIRST
GENERATION IMMIGRANT. OVER THE YEARS MY FAMILY
ESTABLISHED OUR ROOTS IN OUR LIFE HERE AND SINCE 2010 WE
HAVE RESIDED HERE IN THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA PROUDLY THIS
RECOGNITION IS ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL AS A CHILD OF
PAKISTANI IMMIGRANT PARENTS WHO MADE A GREAT MANY SACRIFICES TO
PROVIDE MY BROTHERS AND I A LIFE HERE.
I WOULDN'T BE HERE SPEAKING TO YOU ALL TODAY WITHOUT THEIR
STRENGTH. LOVE, GUIDANCE AND VALUES.
THIS IS A STORY SHARED BY MANY OF MY SOUTH ASIAN-AMERICAN
BROTHERS, SISTERS AND SIBLINGS AND I STAND BEFORE YOU TODAY AS
A PROUD PAKISTANI AMERICAN SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN A
BEACON FOR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES SOUTH ASIAN
AMERICAN IMMIGRANTS IN PARTICULAR HAVE PLANTED
THEIR ROOTS IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR OVER A CENTURY.
TOMORROW YOU HAVE THE CHANCE TO BECOME THE FIRST MAJOR U.S.
CITY TO OFFICIALLY HONOR THE RICH CULTURAL, POLITICAL
AND ECONOMIC IMPACT OF THE SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
THIS INCLUDES MUSLIM, DALIT, SIKH, TAMIL, BENGALI, NEPALI,
INDO CARIBBEAN AND OTHER VOICES WHO ARE TOO OFTEN RACED EVEN
WITHIN SOUTH ASIAN SPACES. WE ARE IMMENSELY GRATEFUL TO
YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND COMMISSIONER KUNDRA.
TELL US JODY FOR LEADING THIS EFFORT ESPECIALLY IN A TIME
WHERE I WAS SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITIES ARE FACING
INCREASED FEAR, HATE DISCRIMINATION AND ERASURE.
I URGE THE BOARD TO UNANIMOUS YOU UNANIMOUSLY SUPPORT THIS
RESOLUTION TOMORROW AND CELEBRATE THE IMMENSE
CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND BEYOND. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND SIR, THAT ITEM WAS JUST
NEWLY INTRODUCED THIS AFTERNOON.
SO IT'S NOT GOING TO BE APPROVED UNTIL NEXT WEEK.
>> PLEASE WELCOME. >> HI, MY NAME IS BENJI KAPLAN.
I WORK AT GREEN APPLE BOOKS A LEGACY BUSINESS BASED
IN DISTRICT ONE AND HAS OTHER LOCATIONS AROUND THE CITY.
WE ARE UNIONIZED WITH UFC LOCAL FIVE AND I'M A DISTRICT ONE
RESIDENT AND ALSO HELPED DRAFT THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO
PURCHASE ACT. SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN
FOR BRINGING THE PROPOSAL FORWARD.
>> A GREEN APPLE WE'VE BEEN FORTUNATE TO HAVE ONLY ONE
TRANSFER OF OWNERSHIP SINCE THE STORE OPENED IN 1967 OR THE
CURRENT OWNERS OR FORMER EMPLOYEES WHO'VE BEEN GOOD
STEWARDS OF WHAT IS MORE THAN A STORE MORE THAN A NEIGHBORHOOD
INSTITUTION, AN ARTS HUB MORE THAN A MUST VISIT TOURIST
DESTINATION BUT ALSO THE HOME OF THREE DOZEN WORKING CLASS
RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING ME.
>> NOT EVERY SMALL BUSINESS HAS SUCH A VIBRANT LEGACY TO
PROTECT BUT ALL HAVE WORKERS WHO NO CARE ABOUT AND ARE THEIR
RESPECTIVE BUSINESSES. THIS ACT OFFERS A PROTECTION
FROM THE SPECULATION, THE ASSET STRIPPING AND THE DISPLACEMENT
THAT THREATENS COMMUNITIES WHEN A SMALL BUSINESS CLOSES WORKERS
LIKE ME CAN POOL OUR RESOURCES AND BUY THE BUSINESSES WE'VE
HELPED BUILD. >> SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS LIKE
OURS HAVE THE COMMUNITY AT HEART BUT WHEN PROPERTY VALUES
RISE OR OWNERSHIP CHANGES, WORKERS CAN BE LEFT BEHIND
THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS RISK LOSING THEIR SOUL.
>> THIS IS A POWERFUL INTERVENTION THAT GIVES WORKERS
NOT OUTSIDE INVESTORS THE FIRST CHANCE TO PURCHASE AND OWN
THESE BUSINESSES WITH LEGAL AND FINANCIAL SUPPORT PLUS
STRONG PROTECTIONS FOR UNION WORKERS.
>> THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT IS A PRACTICAL
AND PRINCIPLED RESPONSE TO A REAL CRISIS AND I URGE YOU TO
MOVE IT FORWARD. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS DEVA HAUSER AND I'M
A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT NINE AND ONE OF SO MANY SOUTH
ASIAN-AMERICANS HERE IN THE BAY AREA.
MY FAMILY'S FROM INDIA. I'M HERE TO THANK YOU FOR
RECOGNIZING SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SOUTH ASIAN CULTURE HAS
SHAPED THE BAY AREA FOR DECADES AT LEAST SINCE OUR CLASSICAL
MUSIC AND SPIRITUAL PRACTICES ARRIVED IN THE 1960S.
>> YET IT HAS TAKEN OVER 60 YEARS TO FINALLY HAVE OUR VERY
FIRST SOUTH ASIAN SUPERVISOR HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
SUPERVISOR BILAL MAHMOOD WHO WE HAVE TO THANK FOR THIS
RESOLUTION. >> AS AN INDIAN AMERICAN I FEEL
OUR SUBGROUP INHABITS A COMPLEX AND LITTLE UNDERSTOOD SPACE
IN THE COUNTRY. WE'RE HELD UP AS A MODEL
MINORITY A DESIGNATION THAT PITS US AGAINST COMMUNITIES,
OTHER COMMUNITIES OF COLOR IN A CIVILIZATION BUILT ON $45
TRILLION WORTH OF WEALTH STOLEN FROM OUR MOTHER LANDS OVER
CENTURIES OF COLONIAL RULE WE ARE RATED THE WEALTHIEST
SUBGROUP IN THE U.S. WHICH SHOULD REALLY BE SEEN AS A
TESTAMENT TO THE BRUTAL AND INEQUITABLE FILTERING
PROCESS BY WHICH INDIANS ARE ALLOWED TO BECOME AMERICANS.
MOST COME HERE ON HB ONE H1-B SKILLED WORKER VISAS.
THEY WERE BEFORE THEY WERE WORKING 60 TO 70 HOURS TO KEEP
THEIR SILICON VALLEY TECH JOBS. AS LOSING IT WOULD PUT THEM ON
A TIMER FOR DEPORTATION. THEY WERE AMONG MILLIONS OF
INDIAN STUDENTS FIGHTING TO BE TOP OF THEIR CLASS IN A
COMPETITIVE SYSTEM THAT PERPETUATES ITS OWN DEEP ROOTED
SYSTEMIC INEQUALITIES. MEANWHILE, ECONOMIC REFUGEES
AND THOSE FACING CASTE AND RELIGIOUS DISCRIMINATION
ARE PLENTIFUL AMONG THOSE WHO SEEK AMERICAN CITIZENSHIP.
YET THEY'RE JUST A SMALL FRACTION OF INDIANS ALLOWED
INTO THIS COUNTRY BY SUPPORTING THIS RESOLUTION.
>> YOU AFFIRM THAT SOUTH ASIAN-AMERICAN STORIES
AND CONTRIBUTIONS ARE INTEGRAL TO OUR CITY NOT JUST OUR MUSIC
BUT ALSO OUR VOICES NOT JUST OUR FOOD BUT ALSO OUR HISTORIES
NOT JUST OUR WORK BUT ALSO THE WELL-BEING AND THE WELL-BEING
OF OUR COMMUNITIES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
I'M PAULA EISNER, A TRANSACTIONAL ATTORNEY
SPECIALIZING IN COOPERATIVES. MY LAW FIRM TUTTLE LAW GROUP IS
BASED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. AS SOMEBODY WHO HELPED DRAFT
THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT, I THANK
SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR BRINGING THIS FORWARD.
WOLPERT GIVES WORKERS THE RIGHT TO PURCHASE THEIR BUSINESSES AT
MARKET VALUE BEFORE SALE TO THIRD PARTIES CREATES NEW
OPPORTUNITIES FOR MAJORITY GROUPS OF WORKERS TO PURCHASE
THEIR BUSINESSES AND INCENTIVIZES COOPERATIVE
CONVERSIONS. >> WOLPERT BUILDS ON S.F. SCOPE
FOR THE COMMUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT AS WELL AS EXISTING
CALIFORNIA COOPERATIVE LAW WHOPPER ISN'T JUST GOOD PUBLIC
POLICY WELL BUT WILL BE A GAME CHANGER STABILIZING
COMMUNITIES, EMPLOYMENT AND THE CITY'S TAX BASE WORKERS TAX
BASE STABILIZATION EFFECTS MAY MAKE WAPA A REVENUE GENERATING
ORDINANCE. >> WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
TAKE ACTION TO PROTECT THE CITY'S ECONOMY AT A CRUCIAL
HISTORIC MOMENT A GENERATION OF SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS ARE
RETIRING AND SPECULATIVE BUYERS WITH NO TIES TO THE CITY EXERT
OUTSIZE INFLUENCE ON THE CITY'S WORKERS ECONOMY AND CULTURE.
>> EXTRACTIVE PRACTICES SUCH AS ASSET STRIPPING THREATEN
WORKERS AND THE CITY. >> RIGHT NOW OWNERS CAN SELL A
BUSINESS FOR PARTS WITHOUT CONSIDERATION FOR THE WORKERS
OR THE ROLE THAT BUSINESS HAS IN THE CITY.
WALKER OFFERS ANOTHER PATH FOR THE CITY WHERE WORKERS HAVE THE
NOTICE FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE AND ENFORCEABLE RIGHTS TO
PURCHASE THE BUSINESSES THEY'VE HELPED BUILD BEFORE THEY ARE
SOLD TO THIRD PARTIES. >> LOPEZ COOPERATIVE CONVERSION
INCENTIVES AND TECHNICAL SUPPORT WILL FACILITATE ALL
TRANSITIONS TO COOPERATIVE EMPLOYEE OWNERSHIP EMPOWERING
WORKERS, SAVING CITY JOBS AND ALLOWING OWNERS TO RETIRE
WITH DIGNITY KNOWING THEIR LEGACY IS IN GOOD HANDS.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR BRINGING THIS PROPOSAL
FORWARD AND I URGE YOU ALL TO SUPPORT THIS PROPOSAL TO KEEP
OWNERSHIP LOCAL. I YIELD MY TIME AND ALSO
SUPPORT JUSTICE FOR MELVIN. I'M TRAGIC TO HEAR THAT THIS
WAS DONE FOR PROFIT. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
I HAVE SOMETHING. >> GOOD EVENING.
MY NAME IS JOY GEORGE AND I INTERN WITH THE SUSTAINABLE
ECONOMIES LAW CENTER. >> I'M HERE TO STRONGLY SUPPORT
THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO PROTECT ACT A PROPOSED
ORDINANCE THAT WAS DRAFTED BY MY TEAM AND I AND IN GRATITUDE
I THANK SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR BRINGING THIS FORWARD.
>> SAN FRANCISCO IS A CITY THAT ASPIRES TO BE A LANDING PLACE
FOR INNOVATION, CREATIVITY AND COMMUNITY.
>> HOWEVER, AT A TIME WHERE MANY OF THE CITY'S
REVITALIZATION EFFORTS ARE CENTERED ON ATTRACTING NEW
BUSINESSES, THE WORKERS OF MANY SMALL BUSINESSES THAT CURRENTLY
OPERATE IN THE CITY FACE INCREASING INSECURITY BECAUSE
THE SMALL BUSINESS LANDSCAPE IS SHIFTING FAST, LONGTIME OWNERS
ARE RETIRING AND TOO OFTEN THEIR LEGACY IS LOST TO CHAIN
TAKEOVERS OR SPECULATIVE BUYERS WITH NO TIES TO THE COMMUNITY.
THIS HARMS NOT ONLY SAN FRANCISCANS WHO LOSE PIECES OF
THEIR CULTURAL AND ECONOMIC FABRIC BUT IT MAKES IT HARDER
FOR WORKERS WHO RUN THE CITY TO STAY IN THE CITY.
I AM IN SUPPORT OF LOBO BECAUSE I BELIEVE THAT SUPPORTING
WORKER SELF-DETERMINATION IS COMMON SENSE POLICY GIVING
WORKERS THE OPPORTUNITY TO ORGANIZE THEMSELVES, RAISE
CAPITAL AND BY THEIR WORKPLACES IS EXACTLY THE TYPE OF
INNOVATION NEEDED TO KEEP SAN FRANCISCANS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THIS ORDINANCE REINFORCES A VISION OF NEIGHBORHOOD
STABILIZATION WHERE STOREFRONTS DON'T FLIP EVERY FEW YEARS
AND WORKING CLASS COMMUNITIES CAN REMAIN ROOTED.
>> IT ENSURES THAT LAND USE AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT MOVE
TOGETHER TO PRESERVE LOCAL CHARACTER WELL BUT ALSO SUPPORT
BUSINESS SUCCESSION PLANNING IN A MEANINGFUL WAY.
>> IT LETS SMALL BUSINESSES THEIR OWNERS RETIRE WITH
DIGNITY KNOWING THEIR LIFE'S WORK WILL CONTINUE IN THE HANDS
OF PEOPLE THEY TRUST THEIR WORKERS.
I URGE YOU TO CONSIDER THIS ORDINANCE SERIOUSLY BECAUSE
ECONOMIC RESILIENCE SHOULD BE A TOP PRIORITY FOR THIS BOARD.
>> WORKER OWNED BUSINESSES ARE MORE STABLE, MORE EQUITABLE
AND MORE INVESTED IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS THEY SERVE.
WOBA IS A TOOL TO STRENGTHEN SAN FRANCISCO'S ECONOMY FROM
THE BOTTOM UP. YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THIS MATTER
IS WELCOMED AND I KNOW WILL SHAPE SAN FRANCISCO'S FUTURE
FOR THE BETTER. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND WE'LL COME TO OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> HELLO SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS NADIR AMON. I AM A DISTRICT ONE RESIDENT
AND I AM HERE TO COMMENT ON THE SOUTH ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH
RESOLUTION. >> THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD FOR INTRODUCING THE RESOLUTION AND TO CUADRAT
CHAUDHARY COUNTLESS FOR WORKING ON THIS EFFORT WITH HIS OFFICE
OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS AS SOMEONE OF THIS HERITAGE IT IS
FRUSTRATING THAT SOUTH ASIANS ARE OFTEN FLATTENED INTO TEXAS
TECH EXCLUSIVE ARCHETYPES OF THE ENGINEER OR THE C-SUITE
EXECUTIVE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WE ARE SO MUCH MORE THAN THAT
AND SOUTH ASIAN HISTORY WITHIN SAN FRANCISCO IS DEEP AND RICH
IN VARIATION SO I THOUGHT I WOULD COME HERE AND SHARE SOME
SOUTH ASIAN S.F. HISTORY THAT YOU MAY NOT KNOW ABOUT ONE
DURING WORLD WAR TWO GUJARAT THE HOTEL WORKERS DEMONSTRATED
SOLIDARITY WITH THEIR JAPANESE EMPLOYERS AT THE TIME THE US
GOVERNMENT TURNED AGAINST ITS OWN CITIZENS AND HELD THEM
IN INTERNMENT CAMPS. >> THOSE WORKERS BECAME
CARETAKERS OF THE BUSINESSES UNTIL THEIR EMPLOYERS RETURNED
HOME TO THE HINDUSTAN HAD OTHER PARTY A REVOLUTIONARY
ANTI-COLONIAL MOVEMENT IN THE EARLY 1900S FOCUSED ON
LIBERATING SOUTH ASIA FROM BRITISH RULE HAD A NUMBER OF
MEETING PLACES THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO AND PRINTED ITS
NEWSLETTER RIGHT HERE ON VALENCIA STREET AND THREE
CECCONI A NONPROFIT REPRESENTING LGBTQ PLUS PEOPLE
OF SOUTH ASIAN DESCENT WAS FOUNDED IN SAN FRANCISCO
IN 1986 AND IS THE OLDEST GROUP OF ITS KIND IN THE WORLD.
AND THAT'S JUST SCRATCHING THE SURFACE.
WE ARE ACTIVISTS AND ARTISTS DOCTORS AND HEALERS, WORKERS,
RESTAURATEURS, SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS AND MUCH, MUCH MORE WHO
ARE A CORE PART OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ANDREW JASON DE
LEON. I AM MELVIN BALDWIN'S ELDEST
CHILD AND ONLY SON. I HAVE WORKED IN OUR CITY
AND COMMUNITY BASED PROGRAM TO SUPPORT SYSTEMS INVOLVED
FAMILIES LIKE MINE. I'VE SEEN FIRSTHAND THE BEAUTY
AND THE JOY THAT HAPPENS WHEN WE CENTER COMMUNITY HEALING,
LOVE AND SUPPORT. JULY 14TH WAS OUR FATHER'S
BIRTHDAY BUT HIS FINAL WORDS WILL HAUNT ME FOREVER.
ON JULY 13TH HE WAS UNRAVELING AFTER BEING TRANSFERRED FROM
THE STATE HOSPITAL IN THE TASK, CORDERO TO THE PRIVATELY RUN
111 TAYLOR STREET FACILITY RUN BY GEO GROUP HE CALLED US HIS
VOICE CRACKING BREATH SHALLOW. I'M ANXIOUS, HE SAID.
I'M SCARED, HE SAID I'D RATHER GO BACK TO JAIL THAN STAY HERE
. HE SOUNDED LIKE A MAN CORNERED
LIKE SOMEONE DROWNING WITH NO HAND REACHING BACK.
>> I CALLED THE 111 TAYLOR FACILITY THREE TIMES BEGGING
FOR A WELLNESS CHECK. THEY HUNG UP ON ME THREE TIMES
BEFORE I WAS ABLE TO COMPLETE A SENTENCE AROUND 3:30 A.M. THE
NEXT DAY MY DAD WAS FOUND DEAD ON THE PAVEMENT NEAR TO 25.
TAYLOR JUST ONE BLOCK FROM THE BUILDING WHERE HE SAID HE WAS
TOO AFRAID TO SLEEP. NOT ONLY DO WE HAVE TO GRIEVE
OUR FATHER'S DEATH, WE MUST NOW SEEK ANSWERS ON HIS BEHALF.
I FIND IT HARD TO SLEEP. FOOD HAS LOST HIS FLAVOR.
MUSIC NOW SOUNDS MUTED HOW I UNDERSTAND A PUBLIC GOOD IS
BASED AROUND A SAN FRANCISCO THAT IS ROOTED NOT ONLY
IN TRAUMA INFORMED SYSTEMS BUT HEALING CENTERED SUPPORT AROUND
THE IDEA THAT PROGRAMS ARE MEANT TO AFFIRM THE INNATE
HUMAN DIGNITY THAT EXISTS WITHIN US ALL.
>> THE PROGRAM AT 111 TAYLOR IS INCONGRUENT WITH THIS IDEA OF
THE PUBLIC GOOD. IT IS MY DEEPEST HOPE THAT
IN THE INTEREST OF THE PUBLIC GOOD THAT THE MORAL ARC OF SAN
FRANCISCO WILL BEND TOWARD JUSTICE.
AND AS WE CONTINUE TO RAISE PUBLIC CONSCIOUSNESS AROUND THE
SUFFERING THAT THOSE THOSE LIVING AT 111 TAYLOR THAT
IN DUE TIME THE SPACE BE TRANSFORMED TO ONE THAT CENTERS
COMMUNITY HEALING, LOVE AND SUPPORT OUR COMMUNITIES
DESERVE BETTER. >> OUR FAMILIES DESERVE BETTER.
OUR DAD DESERVED BETTER. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD JUSTICE TO MELVIN THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO TO THE MEMBERS OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ANIKA, MY BYLINE. I AM ONE OF MELVIN BROWN'S
CHILDREN TODAY I JUST WANT TO SPEAK ABOUT WHO MY DAD WAS AS A
PERSON NOT AS A STATISTIC, NOT AS A MAN WITH A RECORD, NOT AS
SOMEONE WHO FELL THROUGH THE CRACKS OF THE SYSTEM BUT AS MY
FATHER AND AS A HUMAN BEING. >> MY DAD WAS SOMEONE WHO LOVED
DEEPLY EVEN IF HE DIDN'T ALWAYS KNOW HOW TO SHOW IT THE WAY THE
WORLD EXPECTED HIM TO. HE WAS FUNNY.
HE WAS GENTLE WHEN HE WANTED TO BE AND HE HAD A CHILDLIKE
SPIRIT THAT WOULD SHINE THROUGH ESPECIALLY WHEN HE WAS WITH US
HIS KIDS. HE WAS IMPERFECT BUT HE WAS
PRESENT. HE SHOWED UP IN THE SMALL WAYS
THAT MATTERED. WHEN WE WERE LITTLE HE WOULD
TAKE US AROUND SAN FRANCISCO SUCH AS TO PLACES LIKE
CHINATOWN AND UBER GOING TO HE WAS TRYING TO GIVE US THE
MEMORIES HE NEVER HAD GROWING UP.
>> I REMEMBER HIM TRYING TO TEACH ME HOW TO SHOOT FREE
THROWS AT THE PARK EVEN WAKING UP EARLY FOR MORNING JOGS
TOGETHER. HE DIDN'T HAVE MUCH BUT HE GAVE
WHAT HE COULD HIS TIME, HIS STORIES, HIS SMILE.
>> HE BORROWED THINGS. MOST PEOPLE DIDN'T SEE BIPOLAR
DISORDER, DEPRESSION, SCHIZOPHRENIA.
BUT EVEN WHEN ALL OF THAT HE TRIED TO PROTECT US FROM IT.
HE SMILED WHEN HE WAS HURTING HE CALLED US WHEN HE WAS
INCARCERATED JUST TO SAY HI OR CHECK IN.
HIS VOICE WAS COMFORT. HE MADE MISTAKES?
YES. >> BUT HE NEVER GAVE UP ON
BEING A FATHER. HE NEVER WALKED AWAY FROM US.
>> HE STAYED IN OUR LIVES. HE KEPT CALLING, KEPT CARING,
KEPT TRYING. HE WAS BRAVE EVEN WHEN HE WAS
SCARED AND THOUGH HE CARRIED SO MUCH PAIN HE CARRIED IT QUIETLY
BECAUSE HE DIDN'T WANT TO TOUCH US.
THAT WAS MY DAD NOT A PERFECT MAN BUT A MAN WHO LOVED HIS
CHILDREN AND TRIED EVERY SINGLE DAY TO BE BETTER THAN THEN WHAT
THE WORLD TOLD HIM HE WAS. AND THAT WILL ALWAYS MEAN
SOMETHING TO ME. >> I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO SHARE A
VOICEMAIL I HAD GOT FROM WHEN HE WAS MA'AM AND I JUST WANT TO
SAY ONE THING I GUESS ARE WHENEVER YOU CHECK THESE
MESSAGES I WANT TO SAY HI. I DON'T I LOVE YOU CHECKING UP
ON MY THANK YOU FOR SHOPPING BUDDY.
>> EVERYONE WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
YEAH. OH SORRY.
>> HI. I'M MILANA.
ISABELLA. BILL ALLEN.
I'M THE YOUNGEST DAUGHTER OF MELVIN BILL ALLEN AROUND LAST
YEAR ON JULY 24TH 2020 FOR A FEW DAYS FROM BEFORE MY
BIRTHDAY MY DAD SENT ME A LETTER I WAS ABOUT TO TURN 17.
>> IT READ HI MILANA. >> HI.
I MEANT I'M MISSING YOUR BIRTHDAY AGAIN SO I'M READY
THIS LETTER SO I HAVE PROOF OR YOU HAVE PROOFS THAT I DIDN'T
FORGET. >> I WANTED TO DO SOMETHING
LIKE IN THE LETTER LIKE WRITE YOU A POEM BECAUSE I REMEMBER
THAT YOU LIKE LIKE ME MAKING YOU THINGS.
I TRIED TO THINK OF ONE AND NOTHING'S COMING OUT RIGHT
NOW. MAYBE I'M JUST NOT GOOD AT IT
OR I'M NOT TRYING HARD ENOUGH SO I STOPPED TRYING TO
ACCOMPLISH THAT. MAYBE LATER I'LL WRITE ONE
IN YOUR OTHER BIRTHDAY I DID THINK OF SOMETHING THAT YOU
MIGHT LIKE BY CHANCE IF YOU LET ME DO IT.
WE'LL TALK DETAILS LATER WHEN I GET OUT BUT I'M TOLD IT MIGHT
BE BE SOONER THAN I THOUGHT. HAPPY 17TH BIRTHDAY, MILANA.
JUST IN CASE I DON'T GET THE CHANCE TO GREET YOU ON THE DAY
I LOVE YOU, DADDY. >> THAT WAS THE LAST BIRTHDAY
LETTER THAT I WILL EVER GET FROM HIM.
HE BELIEVED HE WAS GETTING OUT SOON HE HAD HOPE HIS PUTTING
SOMETHING NOT JUST A GIFT BUT A CHANCE TO FINALLY SHOW UP
IN PERSON TO BE MORE THAN A VOICE ON THE PHONE OR WORDS ON
A PAPER. HE JUST WANTED TO BE MY DAD
AGAIN. NOW MY BIRTHDAY'S COMING UP
THIS WEEK. THIS TIME I'M TURNING 18 DON'T
DOGWOOD MO MY OLD SOUL HE SHOULD HAVE BEEN HERE FOR WHAT
WE BOTH HOPED IT FOR IT THINK ABOUT WHAT COULD HAVE BEEN IF
WHAT OLIVIA TAYLOR HAD DONE WELL IT CLAIMED TO DO IF THEY
TREATED HIM LIKE SOMEONE FIGHTING FOR HIS KIDS NOT
SOMEONE TO CHECK OFF A LIST IF THEY ACTUALLY HELPED HIM HEAL
INSTEAD OF LETTING HIM SLIP THROUGH THE CRACKS MAYBE HE'D
BE HERE. MAYBE WE'D BE PLANNING
SOMETHING TOGETHER FOR OUR BIRTHDAYS.
MAYBE I WOULDN'T BE STANDING HERE WITH NOTHING BUT HIS
HANDWRITING IN MEMORY OF A PROMISE HE'LL NEVER BE.
>> HE WHO NEVER. HELLO.
HE NEVER GOT THE CHANCE TO KEEP.
HE WANTED TO DO SOMETHING FOR ME WHEN HE GOT OUT HE NEVER GOT
THE CHANCE. >> I STILL HAVE THE MAN.
THANK YOU FOR SHARING YOUR THOUGHTS.
THE BOARD WILL CONVEY THEIR CONDOLENCES TO YOUR FAMILY AT
THE CONCLUSION OF THIS MEETING TODAY.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
FIRST I JUST WANTED TO SAY HOW BRAVE THESE CHILDREN ARE TO
SPEAK UP HERE. AND I WANTED TO SUPPORT THEM
IN THAT. MY NAME IS DR. DAN CABELLA.
I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF COMPTON'S X COALITION, ALSO A PUBLIC
HEALTH SCIENTIST AND SCHOLAR AND ALSO A SURVIVOR OF A FATHER
WHO DIED WHEN I WAS ABOUT SEVEN YEARS OLD.
TWO SIMILAR CONDITIONS THAT WERE HAPPENING AT 111 TAYLOR
THAT MOTIVATED ME TO DO THE WORK THAT I DO.
>> SO RUTH WILSON GILMORE REMINDS US WHERE LIFE IS
PRECIOUS LIFE IS PRECIOUS. THAT'S NOT JUST A MORAL IDEAL.
THAT'S A MATERIAL MEASURE OF HOW OUR SYSTEMS OPERATE AND WHO
THEY ARE BUILT TO PROTECT OR DISCARD.
OVER THE LAST SEVERAL WEEKS WE HAVE HEARD REPEATED COMPLAINTS
ABOUT OVERCROWDING, EXPLOITATION AND THE UNSAFE
DEHUMANIZING CONDITIONS AT 111 TAYLOR.
THESE WARNINGS WERE NOT HYPOTHETICAL.
THEY WERE URGENT. AND NOW MELVIN BULLEN IS DEAD.
MELVIN WAS A YOUNG 44 YEARS OLD.
HE HAD BEEN WORKING TOWARD SOBRIETY.
HE HAD SURVIVED INCARCERATION, PSYCHIATRIC CONFINEMENT AND WAS
TRYING TO REBUILD HIS FAMILY SO THAT HE DID NOT WANT TO RETURN
TO THE TENDERLOIN. BUT HE WAS PLACED AT 111
TAYLOR, A SITE OPERATED BY GEO GROUP, A CORPORATION WITH LONG
VIOLENT RECORD OF PROFITING FROM INCARCERATION
IN IMMIGRATION DETENTION. WE MAY NOT KNOW YET IF GEO
GROUP'S SPECIFIC PROCEDURES DIRECTLY CAUSED MELVIN'S DEATH.
BUT WE KNOW THIS HE WAS MADE VULNERABLE BY A SYSTEM THAT
TREATS CERTAIN LIVES AS A DISPOSABLE.
THE FACT THAT A MAN CAN COME OUT OF PRISON AS BE PLACED IN A
CERTAIN ENVIRONMENT AND BE SENT THERE ANYWAY ONLY TO DIE WITHIN
DAYS SHOULD MAKE US ALL ASHAMED.
AND IT SHOULD ALSO COMPEL US TO ACT.
SUBPOENAS ARE A START BUT WE NEED MORE THAN OVERSIGHT.
WE NEED DIVESTMENT FROM CARCERAL HOUSING, AN INVESTMENT
IN COMMUNITY LED CARE, HOUSING AND HEALING.
MELVIN'S LIFE WAS PRECIOUS. LET'S ACT LIKE IT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO. MY NAME IS LEAH MCKEEVER 1186.
PLEASE FORGIVE ME IF I CAN'T FINISH THIS.
UM, MELVIN DIDN'T EVEN SURVIVE A MONTH THAT WENT 11 TAYLOR.
YOUR POLICIES ON MENTAL HEALTH SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER
AND PEOPLE IN CRISIS ARE KILLING PEOPLE.
AND THEY KILLED MELVIN. THE BOARD AND MAYORS HAVE ONLY
BEEN ESCALATING CARCERAL POLICIES.
THEY'RE NOT WORKING. IF THEY WERE, MELVIN WOULD BE
ALIVE TODAY AND HE SHOULD BE. WE SPEND OUR LIVES WATCHING OUR
DEBT CYCLE THROUGH INCARCERATE ATION AND UNTREATED ADDICTION
IN THIS CITY. ONE OF HIS CHILDREN SAID HIS
DEATH IS NOT AN ISOLATED TRAGEDY BUT PART OF A LARGER
PATTERN OF INSTITUTIONAL FAILURE THAT THIS IS THE END OF
THE QUOTE THE GEO GROUP PEOPLE RUNNING WANT TO LIVE IN TAYLOR
STREET CONTINUE TO HANG UP ON ALVIN'S FAMILY'S CALLS BECAUSE
DU GROUP HAS NEVER FACED CONSEQUENCES FOR THEIR CRIMES
AGAINST HUMANITY. AND IF YOU THINK I'M
EXAGGERATING THEY'RE A MAN DYING.
A PREVENTABLE DEATH IS A CRIME TO ME.
>> TOTALLY UNAWARE I WAS UNAWARE LAST WEEK AT THE BOARD
OF APPEALS TRIAL OR WHATEVER YOU CALL IT THAT THE BOARD
PRESIDENT WAS APPOINTED BY BIDEN TO BE THE PRINCIPAL LEGAL
ADVISOR TO THE DIRECTOR OF IMMIGRATION AND CUSTOMS
ENFORCEMENT ICE IN 2021. DID THAT INFLUENCE ANY OF THE
BOARD'S VOTES? I DON'T KNOW HOW MANY LIVES
MUST BE SACRIFICED TO GEO GROUP TO CITY HALL BEFORE THIS STOPS
. >> WE DEMAND JUSTICE FOR
MELVIN. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO SUPERVISORS. FIRST OFF I JUST WANT TO SAY
JUSTICE FOR MELVIN AND CONDOLENCES TO THE FAMILY
LOST MY FATHER NOT TOO LONG AGO AND I CAN'T IMAGINE WHAT YOU'RE
GOING THROUGH BUT JUST KNOW GOD IS WITH YOU AND HE'S GOING TO
AID YOU. ON ANOTHER NOTE, MY NAME IS
ASEEL THERA. I SERVE AS A MEMBER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION AND I'M HERE IN MY
PERSONAL CAPACITY AS A PROUD DISTRICT SIX RESIDENT.
I ALSO WANTED TO STAND IN SOLIDARITY OF OUR SOUTH
ASIAN COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND SUPPORT THE SOUTH ASIAN
HERITAGE MONTH RESOLUTION. SOUTH ASIAN AMERICANS HAVE LONG
BEEN A VITAL FORCE IN SAN FRANCISCO FROM BUILDING BELOVED
SMALL BUSINESSES TO LEADING FIGHTS FOR JUSTICE HOUSING
WORKERS RIGHTS AND EDUCATION. THIS COMMUNITY CONTINUES TO BE
A BACKBONE OF OUR CITY'S CULTURE AND CIVIC LIFE
AND THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS DESERVE MORE THAN JUST RECOGNITION.
THEY DESERVE LONG TERM INVESTMENT AND VISIBILITY.
AND ON A PERSONAL NOTE, AS SOMEONE WHO GREW UP ON THE
TENDERLOIN, ONE OF MY GUILTY PLEASURES SINCE I WAS A LITTLE
KID WAS GOING TO JONES AND GARY STREET AND HAVING TO CHOOSE
FROM CHUTNEY SHALAMAR OR PAC ONE FOR THEIR DELICIOUS NAAN.
IT'S MOMENTS IT'S SMALL MOMENTS LIKE THAT GROWING UP IN THE TIO
THAT MADE ME THERE THAT REMINDED ME OF HOW DEEPLY SOUTH
ASIAN CULTURE HAS SHAPED THE SAN FRANCISCO I CALL HOME.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND OUR VICE-CHAIR FROM THE
IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION FOR AUTHORING THIS RESOLUTION FOR
MAKING HISTORY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU COMMISSIONER SILVEIRA FOR YOUR COMMENTS TODAY.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON RESPECTIVE
BOARD MEMBERS. MY NAME IS SHAHIN SHEIKH
AND I'M A PROUD SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN MUSLIM DAUGHTER TO
IMMIGRANTS AND INDIAN IMMIGRANT PARENTS.
SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE AND A LIFELONG PUBLIC SERVANT WITH 28
YEARS MY CAREER STARTED RIGHT HERE IN THE BASEMENT AT
ELECTIONS DEPARTMENT. I CURRENTLY SERVE AS A SECURITY
OPERATIONS INTELLIGENCE MANAGER AT SFM TODAY.
I RISE TODAY IN STRONG SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR MAHMOUD'S
RESOLUTION AND JUST SEEING SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO IN ONE SENTENCE GIVES ME GOOSEBUMPS.
>> I THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP
AND FOR YOUR PROUD REPRESENTATION AS A FIRST
MUSLIM AND SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN .
I RAISED THREE BOYS IN SAN FRANCISCO IN SAN FRANCISCO
IN SUPERVISOR CHEN'S DISTRICT, AMAZING DISTRICT AND WE HAVE
BEEN PART OF PUBLIC SCHOOL FOR 18 YEARS FROM ROOFTOP TO LOCAL
HIGH SCHOOL. >> AND WHEN MY KIDS WERE TEASED
FOR WEARING CURRY JERSEY BECAUSE THEY WERE INDIAN
AND ASKED WHERE WERE THE NON I DECIDED TO DO EXACTLY THAT.
I DECIDED TO HOST AND HAND OUT PARTIES AT THEIR SCHOOL AND I
MADE SURE THAT WE SERVED NAAN AND CHICKEN TIKKA MASALA TO ALL
THE KIDS. >> I SPENT OVER SIX YEARS
VOLUNTEERING AT SAN FRANCISCO'S LAMAZE SCHOOL AND WHERE I
SERVED ON THE BOARD. I'M ALSO HONORED TO BE FIRST
FEMALE COORDINATOR AT AMERICAN SOCIETY ASSOCIATION AND THEN
SIT ON CITY HALL IFTAAR AS WELL A COMMITTEE.
SO ALL THESE ARE ROOTED DEEPLY ROOTED IN SERVICE AS WELL AS
SOUTH ASIAN TRADITIONS. I URGE THE BOARD TO ADOPT THE
RESOLUTION AND SHOW THAT SAN FRANCISCO NOT ONLY WELCOMES ITS
SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITIES BUT IT CELEBRATES US.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS WALTER ASENSIO. I'M A RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO
FIREFIGHTER AND CURRENTLY SERVE AS THE PRESIDENT OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTER AND EMS BEHAVIORAL HEALTH FOUNDATION.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> I REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR SUPPORT IN THE AMENDMENT TO THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AT RS 50 MEMBERS TO DONATE TO OUR
FOUNDATION TO PAYROLL DEDUCTION .
>> YOUR SUPPORT REFLECTS A STRONG COMMITMENT IN PASSING
YOUR TIME, SIR. OH, FORGIVE ME BUT THAT ITEM
HAS ALREADY BEEN HEARD IN COMMITTEE AND THE PUBLIC
COMMENT PERIOD HAS EXPIRED. >> OH, I APOLOGIZE.
I JUST WANT TO THANK THE BOARD. I DIDN'T I WAS TOLD TO WAIT
TILL 69. >> THANK YOU.
I APOLOGIZE BUT THANK YOU. THANK YOU KINDLY.
THANK YOU FOR COMING HERE TODAY.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> AS A VIEWER, PLEASE THIS
ITEM HERE MR. RIGHT. >> YES.
BEFORE I EVEN BEGIN YOUR TIME. THAT ITEM IS NOT ELIGIBLE FOR
PUBLIC COMMENT OR A COMMENT THAT I WANT TO PUT ON THE
RECORD. SO WHEN YOU GET TO IT YOU
ALREADY HAVE FACTS COMING FROM THE PUBLIC.
>> MR.. MR. RIGHT.
PLEASE DON'T TALK ABOUT THAT ITEM.
IT IS NOT ELIGIBLE FOR PUBLIC COMMENT THAT HAS BEEN THROUGH
COMMITTEE BUT YOU'VE GOT SITUATIONS WHERE YOU COULDN'T
FUNDS FOR THE HOMELESS PROGRAMS AND BY THE SAME RESPONSE YOU
ALSO TAKEN AWAY FUNDS FOR TEMPORARY HOUSING.
THAT'S NOT FAIR. IT SHOWS A TOTAL DISREGARD FOR
THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE AND YOU GOT A PATTERN OF DOING
IT. FIRST OF ALL, WHERE'S THAT $24
MILLION THAT WAS SUPPOSED TO BE FOR THE HOMELESS PEOPLE THAT
GAVIN NEWSOM NEWSOM THE NUISANCE IS SUPPOSED TO BE
OVERSEEING. >> WE NEVER HEARD NOTHING ELSE
ABOUT IT WHEN HE WAS PUT IN CHECKED AND CONFRONTED WITH
THE FACTS THAT THE PROGRAM IS MISSING $24 MILLION NONE OF YOU
NEVER SAY ANYTHING ABOUT THAT. THEN YOU WANT TO TAKE AWAY FROM
FUNDS THAT'S TARGETED FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE YOU
ALWAYS HARASS AND SHOW A TOTAL DISREGARD FOR THE INTERESTS OF
THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE LIVING IN THEIR VANS.
AND THERE ARE THESE YOU TELL THEM THEY CAN ONLY PARK FOR
THREE HOURS AND THEN THEY HAVE TO MOVE AND DRIVE AROUND
AND TRY TO FIND ANOTHER PLACE TO DEPART.
>> THAT'S DISGUSTING. YOU KNOW GOODWILL.
THEY CAN'T MOVE AROUND AND LIVE LIKE THAT.
YOU DON'T FOLLOW YOUR OWN RULES AND REGULATIONS OF THE CHARTER
RULE 14 SAYS 15% OF ALL HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES COMES OUT OF THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE ON HOUSING IS SUPPOSED TO BE FOR VERY LOW
AND LOW INCOME BRACKET PEOPLE AND THOSE ARE THE PEOPLE THAT'S
HOMELESS ON THE STREET AND THEN YOU TURN AROUND AND SAID THE
REQUIREMENT TO BE A TENANT IN THE BUILDING NOW TO EACH
AND EVERY OPPORTUNITY THAT COMES OUT OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
ON HOUSING HIGHER 80 TO 90% OF THE AM I IN ABOUT
MISAPPROPRIATION OF FUNDS. WHAT IS MAYOR GAVIN NEWSOM
AND HIS WIFE DOING WRITING A BOOK ON THAT CRITICAL RACE
THEORY AND SELLING IT TO THE UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT,
GETTING PAID $1.5 MILLION? THAT'S DISGUSTING.
THAT'S TOTALLY DISCUSSED. ALL THAT MONEY SHOULD BE CLAWED
BACK AND PUT BACK INTO THE HOME IS FINE, THANK YOU.
>> MR. RIGHT FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING. MY NAME IS ANTHONY TAPIA AND I
STAND BEFORE YOU TO REMIND YOU OF THE PRIVILEGE THAT YOU HAVE
TO SERVE AS SUPERVISORS TO A CITY THAT HAS BEEN A
REPRESENTATION OF HOPE AND LIBERATION TO THE WORLD.
IN AUGUST OF 1966 A RIOT BROKE OUT WHEN POLICE OFFICERS KEPT
HARASSING TRANS WOMEN SEEKING REFUGE.
THAT SIGHT STARTED A REVOLUTION AND THAT GAVE ME
AND MANY OF YOU THE RIGHT TO EXPRESS YOURSELVES AND YOUR
MOST AUTHENTIC SELVES. THAT SIGHT IS NOW THAT SIGHT
NOW HOUSES A FOR PROFIT PRISON THAT HAS CONTINUED TO INFLICT
VIOLENCE ON THOSE WHO SEEK HOPE AND LIBERATION.
>> MELVIN SHOULD HAVE HAD HOPED TO SEE HIS CHILDREN ONCE MORE.
MELVIN SHOULD HAVE HAD THE CHANCE TO PLAN A BIRTHDAY FOR
HIS DAUGHTER. >> WE SEE WE SPEAK BEFORE YOU
TO SEEK JUSTICE AND DEMAND THAT YOU STOP BEING ACCOMPLISHED
THROUGH THE NEGLIGENCE OF GEO GROUP.
>> WE DEMAND ACCOUNTABILITY. WE DEMAND AN END TO THESE
INHUMANE CONDITIONS AND WE DEMAND THAT THE CITY TAKE
ACTION NOW. WE SAY THEIR NAMES.
WE SAY MELVIN PUT THE ONES NAME AND WE WILL NOT STOP UNTIL GEO
GROUP IS HELD ACCOUNTABLE. I'VE HAD THE PRIVILEGE
AND HONOR OF GROWING UP IN SAN FRANCISCO.
MY FAMILY IT'S A FAMILY OF IMMIGRANTS.
WE ESCAPED HORRIBLE CONDITIONS AND WE CAME HERE SEEKING A
BETTER LIFE. >> MANY PEOPLE I'M SURE YOU ALL
HEAR THIS EVERY DAY TALKING TO THE PEOPLE IN YOUR DISTRICTS
THAT COME HERE SEEKING A BETTER LIFE.
HOW MANY MORE PEOPLE DO WE HAVE TO LOSE?
HOW MANY MORE TIMES DO WE HAVE TO WALK ACROSS THE BUILDING
WHERE PEOPLE ARE LITERALLY ASKING FOR HELP TO END THEIR
NAMES? AND REMEMBER WE ARE HERE.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
WE'LL HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. >> THANK YOU.
I'M READING THIS COMMENT ON BEHALF OF ANOTHER SOUTH ASIAN
MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC SIKA CHAKRABARTI.
MY NAME IS SAIKAT CHAKRABARTI. I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT
EIGHT AND I'M COMMENTING IN SUPPORT OF THE SOUTH ASIAN
AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MEHMOOD
AND VICE-CHAIRMAN TELUS CHAUDHRY.
>> MA'AM, CAN I PAUSE YOUR TIME PLEASE?
I BELIEVE YOU HAVE ALREADY ADDRESSED THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT. >> YES I HAVE.
IT IS TWO MINUTES PER PERSON ALTHOUGH YOU'RE PROVIDING
COMMENTS FROM ANOTHER PERSON. IF YOU'RE WANTING TO SUBMIT
THAT LANGUAGE TO US WE'LL PUT IT IN THE MINUTES.
BUT E YOUR TWO MINUTES HAS ALREADY EXPIRED.
THANK YOU KINDLY. THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT, MARK, YOU'RE UP TO FAMOUS CHRISTIANS DIED THIS
MONTH. >> JIMMY SWAGGART AND I'M GLAD
HE'S DEAD. TELL YOU THE TRUTH, HE BROUGHT
A LOT OF HE DRUG GOD'S NAME IN THE MUD, YOU KNOW, AND THEN
JOHN MACARTHUR WHO WAS A CHRISTIAN AND HE YOU KNOW, THE
EARLY CHRISTIANS COULD RAISE THE DEAD AND HONESTLY IF WE
COULD STILL DO THAT, I'D RAISE JOHN BUT I'D LEAVE JIMMY DEAD.
AND YOU KNOW, AFTER HE HAD THE I WOULD HAVE WENT IN THERE, YOU
KNOW, AND TOLD HIM HEY, YOU NEED TO GET A JOB.
>> YOU STEP DOWN, YOU CAN GO TO CHURCH, YOU CAN SING THE SONGS
,YOU CAN PUT MONEY IN THE PLATE BUT IT'S NOT RIGHT.
YOU KNOW. AND A LOT OF PEOPLE OVER THE
YEARS HAVE BROUGHT UP JIMMY SWAGGART, YOU KNOW, AND YOU ARE
SAVED BY GRACE AND IF HE WAS SAVED HE WAS SAVED.
BUT I PERSONALLY DON'T THINK HE WAS.
NOW LAST TIME I WAS HERE WE TALKED A LITTLE BIT ABOUT THE
2300 DAYS AND DANIEL CHAPTER EIGHT WHICH IS ACTUALLY 2300
YEARS AND IT'S INTERESTING BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT THEY CALL A
LUNAR A SOLAR LUNAR THING WHERE THEY COME TOGETHER AND DANIEL
COULD NOT HAVE KNOWN THIS BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T HAVE THE
INSTRUMENTS TO DETERMINE A TRUE SOLAR YEAR AND A TRUE LUNAR
MONTH THAT EVERY 2300 YEARS IT COMES TOGETHER SEE.
SO AGAIN, SHOWING THAT GOD STARTED THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA THAT 2300 YEARS DID END IN 1776.
IT'S AMAZING. IT REALLY IS.
AND SO I DON'T KNOW IF YOU HEARD STUART RHODES TODAY ON
INFOWARS. THEY TRIED TO RIG THE ELECTION
AND THEY GOT CAUGHT AND THERE SHOULD BE VERY SEVERE
CONSEQUENCES FOR THAT. YOU KNOW WHEN WE CAUGHT HILLARY
CLINTON THEY SAID YOU KNOW WHAT, LET'S NOT LET'S NOT GO
TOO FAR HERE. IT'S THE EX-WIFE OF A
PRESIDENT. AND I THOUGHT IT WAS SORT OF
TERRIBLE THEY LET HER OFF THE HOOK AND ARE VERY HAPPY I DID.
BUT IT'S TIME TO START AFTER WHAT THEY DID TO ME AND WHETHER
IT'S RIGHT OR WRONG, IT'S TIME TO GO AFTER PEOPLE.
OBAMA'S BEEN QUITE DIRECTLY SO PEOPLE SAY OH YOU KNOW GROUPS
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS VERY WELL.
>> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME.
>> I HAVE SOME COPIES FOR MY NAME IS JIM MCAFEE.
>> YES WE'LL COME COLLECT THEM FROM YOU ONE FOR EACH MEMBER OF
THE BOARD AND THE CLERK. >> I'LL JUST I'LL JUST READ YOU
UNTIL THOSE WERE GOES OFF. THIS IS ABOUT FACILITY REPORTED
INCIDENTS AT LAGUNA HONDA. 12 ALLEGATIONS OF ABUSE INJURY
OF UNKNOWN ORIGIN ONE ONE INVESTIGATION AND NOT STARTED
BY CDP H OTHER TWO RESIDENT ONE ONE INVESTIGATION NOT STARTED
BY CPA. >> RESIDENT TWO RESIDENT ABUSE
FIVE FIVE INVESTIGATIONS NOT STARTED BY CDP H STAFF TWO
RESIDENT FOUR FOUR INVESTIGATIONS NOT STARTED BY
CDP H MISAPPROPRIATE OCEAN OF RESIDENT PROPERTY ONE ONE
INVESTIGATION NOT SUPPORTED BY CDP H.
MAJOR INJURY TO TWO INVESTIGATIONS NOT STARTED BY
CPR H TWO DISEASE OUTBREAK ONE ONE INVESTIGATION NOT STARTED
BY CDP H. POTENTIAL PRIVACY BREACH ONE
ONE INVESTIGATION NOT STARTED BY CPR H TWO AN ANONYMOUS
COMPLAINT SAID N NO DEFICIENCIES WELL THEY PICKED
OUT SEVEN THAT HAD NOTICED DEFICIENCIES.
WHAT A COINCIDENCE THREE PENDING OUTCOMES DETERMINED
PAGE OVER AND YOU DISCOVER THAT THERE ARE 40 SIX FACILITY
RELATED INCIDENTS PENDING STEVE INVESTIGATIONS NO DOCUMENT
REQUESTS OR CALL OR VISIT. >> NOW THIS GOES ON MONTH AFTER
MONTH AFTER MONTH. >> THEY WILL NEVER REPORT A
DEFICIENCY. WHAT ARE ALL THESE PEOPLE
MAKING THESE REPORTS? >> ARE THEY ALL LYING?
IS THAT WHAT WE'RE TO BELIEVE? >> THEY'RE ALL MAKING THIS UP.
NO DEFICIENCY IS FOR ANY REPORTS EVER.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
MY NAME AND PHONE NUMBER IS ON THIS PAPER.
IF YOU WANT TO CALL ME AND FIND OUT MORE ABOUT LAGUNA HONDA,
YOU'RE WELCOME TO MY DOMESTIC PARTNERS AND THE CHIEF MEDICAL
OFFICER IS CURRENTLY HOLDING EVIDENCE OF IT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. MCAFEE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE. >> HELLO.
I AM READING ON BEHALF OF SHAUKAT CHAKRABARTI.
HE SAYS MY NAME IS SHAUKAT KABBANI BHARTI I'M A RESIDENT
OF DISTRICT EIGHT AND I'M COMMENTING IN SUPPORT OF THE
RESOLUTION PROPOSED BY SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AND VICE
CHAIR CONTROL IS CHOWDHURY SAN FRANCISCO EVEN AS A YOUNG KID
AND TEXAS IS A CITY THAT VALUES ALL THE DIFFERENT THREADS THAT
MAKE UP THE QUILT THAT IS AMERICA.
>> WE'RE A CITY WHERE WE BELIEVE ANYONE CAN COME HERE
AND BE SAN FRANCISCAN WHILE ALSO BEING ASIAN, HISPANIC,
BLACK, FILIPINO, VIETNAMESE OR SOUTH ASIAN.
AND THAT'S ESPECIALLY IMPORTANT IN A TIME WHERE A COMPETING
NARRATIVE OF AMERICA IS BEING PUSHED ON US A NARRATIVE THAT
THESE IDENTITIES MAKE US UN-AMERICAN.
WELL, THAT NARRATIVE IS ITSELF UN-AMERICAN AND I'M SO PROUD
THAT SAN FRANCISCO BY FIGHTING TO INCLUDE MORE AND MORE IN OUR
SOCIETY IS BEING MORE AMERICAN THAN OUR PRESIDENT IS TODAY.
I'M PROUD THAT WE ARE THE FIRST CITY IN THE NATION TO DECLARE A
SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH.
IT'S AN AFFIRMATION THAT SOUTH ASIANS BELONG IN THIS CITY
AND THIS COUNTRY AND WE ARE A PART OF ITS FABRIC.
BUT I DO HAVE ONE SMALL RECOMMENDATION AS WE CELEBRATE
THIS MONTH AND YEARS AHEAD SOMETIMES WE TEND TO CELEBRATE
THE STANDOUTS AND HIGH ACHIEVERS AND WE CELEBRATE
SOUTH ASIAN AMERICAN CULTURE AND THERE'S NOTHING WRONG WITH
THAT. I DON'T WANT TO TAKE ANYTHING
AWAY FROM THOSE WHO HAVE ACHIEVED SO MUCH BUT I JUST
WANT TO MAKE SURE WE DON'T ALSO LOSE SIGHT OF THE VERY REAL
ISSUES FACING SOUTH ASIAN-AMERICANS TODAY AS WELL.
OUR COMMUNITY IS ONE WHERE WEALTH AND INCOME DISPARITY IS
HIGHER THAN ALMOST ANY OTHER COMMUNITY IN AMERICA.
WE STILL HAVE ISSUES OF CASTE DISCRIMINATION IN THIS COUNTRY
I'M SAD TO SAY WHICH WE MUST ROOT OUT DR. AMBEDKAR, THE
FATHER OF THE INDIAN CONSTITUTION, TOLD US WE MUST
BEGIN BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE INEQUALITY THAT EXISTS AND WORK
TO UPLIFT THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN KEPT AT THE BOTTOM.
POLITICAL DEMOCRACY CANNOT LAST UNLESS THERE LIES AT THE BASE
OF IT SOCIAL DEMOCRACY IN AMERICA FDR SAID THE TEST OF
OUR PROGRESS ISN'T WHETHER WE ADD MORE TO THE ABUNDANCE OF
THOSE WHO HAVE MUCH. IT'S WHETHER WE PROVIDE ENOUGH
FOR THOSE WHO HAVE TOO LITTLE. I HOPE WE TAKE THE SPIRIT OF
THESE THINKERS FORWARD WITH US IN THE CITY AND IN OUR SOUTH
ASIAN COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> ALL RIGHT.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS BESIDES THIS GENTLEMAN WHO WANT
TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> PLEASE DO STEP UP IN LINE. MR. SLEEPER.
ALL RIGHT. WELCOME, SIR.
PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD AND BOARD MEMBERS.
MY NAME IS RICHARD ASKEW PETERSON.
I'M HERE TO TALK ON TWO REPORTS THAT HAVE BEEN REPORTED IN THE
CHRONICLE AS WELL AS THE EXAMINER AND THIS IS ON THE
PLAN TO SAVE MUNI BY USING PARSONS TAXES.
NOW THIS IS THE MOST UNFAIR TYPE OF LEGISLATION FOR
TAXATION THAT I KNOW THERE ARE OFTEN OTHER TYPES OF TAP TAXES
YOU COULD USE JUST A GENERAL PROPERTY TAX THAT WOULD TAX
EVERYBODY EVENLY AS MRS. MOSELEY HAS SAID THAT IT'S
REALLY UNFAIR. ESSENTIALLY THE CHASE CENTER IS
ON ONE PARCEL. IT'S GOING TO BE TAXED TO SAY
$100 AND THE HOUSE OUT IN THE AVENUES IS GOING TO BE TAXED AS
A $100 PARCEL. TAXES ARE VERY UNFAIR AND THIS
IS GOING TO START A WAR BETWEEN THE EAST SIDE AND THE WEST SIDE
DOWNTOWN VERSUS THE BURBS. THE WEST SIDE SHOULD NOT BE
PAYING FOR WHAT DOWNTOWN WANTS OR WHAT DOWNTOWN CAN GET AWAY
WITH. THE MILLENNIAL TOWER IS SITTING
ON ONE OR MAYBE 2 TO 2 PARCELS. I'M DIVIDING MY LOT.
I'M GOING TO BE HAVING TWO PARCELS.
I'LL BE PAYING AS MUCH AS THE MY LITTLE TOWER OR THE
SALESFORCE TOWER BILLION DOLLAR PLACES.
SO ANYWAY I HOPE THE THE WORKING GROUP IS UNION LEADERS
TRANSIT ADVOCATES, CHAMBER OF COMMERCE MEMBERS, CITY
SUPERVISORS, TOP STAFF, THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND WHAT THEY'RE
LACKING ARE HOMEOWNERS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> OUR YOU GUYS GAVE AWAY $4
MILLION IN SETTLEMENTS BEFORE TODAY.
ITS AGENDA BEGAN FOR SIDEWALK FALLS AMONG OTHER SETTLEMENTS
FOR CATHOLICS INSTEAD. >> YES, I'LL JUST PARSE YOUR
TIME THE SETTLEMENTS ON TODAY'S AGENDA ARE NOT ELIGIBLE FOR
PUBLIC COMMENT. >> UNDERSTOOD.
THAT'S THE ONLY SENTENCE I HAVE TO SAY.
BUT A MINUTE 52 SECONDS. >> I'LL BEGIN YOUR TIME.
I'M JUST STATING FOR FOR WHAT THEY'RE AND IT'S IMPORTANT THAT
PEOPLE KNOW WHAT THEIR YEAH I WISH YOU JUST WOULDN'T HAVE
INTERRUPTED ME BECAUSE I THINK I NEED TO START MY TIME OVER
BUT FOR SIDEWALK FALLS AMONG OTHER SETTLEMENTS FOR CATHOLIC
INSTITUTIONS EXPERIENCING FLOOD DAMAGE THAT HAVE YET TO SETTLE
CASES OF SEXUAL PERVERSION IN MY OWN EXPERIENCE HAVING A
PRIEST OFFER ME $500 TO ME OFF AND ANOTHER CLERGY TAKING
PICTURES OF ME IN MY SLEEP WHEN I WAS SUPPOSED TO BE IN A SAFE
PLACE. I'VE ADDITIONALLY YET TO
ACKNOWLEDGE MYSELF BEING STRANGLED FOR 35 MINUTES TO
FACE ADDITIONAL BATTERIES BY OFFICERS SUCH AS THOMAS ON
MAYOR LEARY SECURITY DETAIL ATTEMPTING TO DIE MY RIGHTS AT
CITY HALL DESPITE BEING AN AMERICAN CITIZEN AND NOT A
FOREIGN ONE MATTERS THAT HE WON'T BE CHARGED WITH A CRIME
FOR BECAUSE LAWS CONSISTENTLY ONLY APPLY TO SOME.
YOU CAN OF COURSE MURDER WITHOUT CONSEQUENCE IF YOU'VE
GOT A BADGE YOU CAN SEXUALLY PRAY ON ANY YOU WISH IF YOU
HAVE ENOUGH DOLLARS WITHOUT CONSEQUENCE WE WELL KNOW TO
BOARD PRESIDENT TO YOU WANT TO RECOGNIZE LADY GAGA A
MILLIONAIRE THAT NEEDS NOTHING BUT YOU DON'T WANT TO RECOGNIZE
YOUR OWN RESIDENT SPENDING FOUR MONTHS IN CUSTODY FOR TAKING
DOWN A CURTAIN STAPLED TO THE WALL WITH ON IT.
THE INDIVIDUAL DYING IN THE HALFWAY HOUSE OF THE ICE
DETENTION FACILITY AT 111 TAYLOR IS RECOGNIZED, OF COURSE
AFTER BEING DEAD WANTING TO MAKE EVERYTHING POLITICAL BUT
YOU'VE GOT TO RESPOND TO SAN FRANCISCANS LIVING WITH
IN THEIR PANTS FOR A WEEK AT A TIME IN SAN FRANCISCO COUNTY
JAILS AND JAIL RAN AND OWNED BY SAN FRANCISCO WITH NO LESS THAN
30 MENTAL HEALTH SECURITY AND HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONALS
SIMPLY WALKING BY NO LESS THAN 30 QUOTE UNQUOTE PROFESSIONALS
IT'S 40 MILLIONS OF DOLLARS WHILE OFF OUR CITY.
ONE OF THEM THAT WALKED BY STANDING RIGHT HERE FOR THE
PAST SIX MONTHS I'VE WOKEN UP TO SOMEONE THAT GETS EVERYTHING
FOR FREE CALLING ME A OUTSIDE MY WINDOW ALL HOURS WITH THREE
SECURITY OFFICERS WITHIN 50 YARDS OF WHERE THE THREATS
REGULARLY OCCUR. ADDITIONALLY EARNING A SALARY
WELL NOT ABLE TO PROVIDE PEACE AT 3 A.M. AND ANOTHER RESIDENT
MR. SLEEPER YOUR TIME CONCLUDED CONCLUDED BEST IN MY OWN HOME
WITH COCKROACHES AND RODENTS OUTSIDE OF WALKING SHADE IN THE
HALLWAY EVERY DAY SHANE YOUR TIME IS COMPLETE 18 HUNDRED
DOLLARS A MONTH TO LIVE IN. SHANE SO IF YOU WANT TO
RECOGNIZE SOME ISSUES LET US KNOW.
>> SHANE GET ON THAT BUILDING. SHANE GET A HOLD OF YOURSELF I
MIGHT THAT TO FORCE ME TO LIVE IN CONDITIONS.
>> SHANE CALLING OUT SHANE DAWSON IN MY HALLWAY.
>> TAKE IT EASY WHAT IT'S DOING TO MY MENTAL HEALTH AND YOU
WANT TO BE RIGHT FOR FUNDING? I'LL BE GET THE OUT OF ALL
RIGHT. THE BOARD DOES NOT ENDORSE
THOSE COMMENTS, MRS. BROWN. >> SO BECAUSE I WANT TO BURY
YOUR HANDS SHAKING YOUR WALL AND GET A PASS.
>> MRS. BROWN, THIS IS THE MAN NOT FOLLOWING NATURE.
MRS. BROWN, PLEASE COME TOWARDS THE PODIUM.
SO I'M HERE TO WHERE I WAS JUST LISTENING TO A LOT OF THE
PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT THEIR LOVED ONES BEING LOST AND THEIR
FATHERS AND THEIR FAMILIES AND THEIR SUFFERING FROM
TRAUMA. I JUST WANT TO ALSO SAY THAT ON
PLEASE LISTEN TO ME AND GET OFF YOUR PHONES AND ON NEXT MONTH
AUGUST 14TH WILL BE THE ANNIVERSARY IN THE DEATH OF THE
MURDER OF MY SON AUGUST 14TH I COME HERE WITH MY GRANDCHILDREN
WHICH IS WILL BE WHICH IS THEIR UNCLE.
THIS IS THESE ARE THE HIS NIECES.
THEY'RE FIVE YEARS OLD. SO THIS IS WHAT I HAVE TO DEAL
WITH THAT THEY DON'T HAVE THEIR UNCLE AROUND.
MY SON WAS SHOT 30 TIMES WITH A SEMIAUTOMATIC GUNS ON AUGUST
14TH AND I'M STILL SEEKING JUSTICE FOR MY CHILD AND I ASK
THAT EACH SUPERVISOR PLEASE COME ON AUGUST 14TH AND COME
AND SUPPORT US MOTHERS ABOUT UNSOLVED HOMICIDES.
>> I WANT TO THANK MATT DARCY FOR HELP IMPLEMENTING THE
POLICY ON WAYS TO PAY TIPSTERS TO COME FORTH.
I AM STILL ASKING FOR THE MAYOR TO COME AND SUPPORT US
MOTHERS. HE NEEDS TO DO THAT.
HE NEEDS TO KNOW THAT HE NEEDS TO STAND UP FOR US ALSO TO
BRING AWARENESS AND TO BRING UP SOMETHING ABOUT THAT POLICY
AND LET THE WORLD KNOW THAT THERE IS WAY TO PAY TIPSTERS SO
OUR CASES CAN GET SOLVED. >> I'M A MOTHER WHO IS STILL
SUFFERING. THE BODY KEEPS THE SCORE.
I AM I'M A STRONG MOTHER BUT I STILL I JUST WAS UP AT THE
GRAVE THE OTHER DAY TALKING TO MY SON AND SAYING THAT I'M
NEVER GOING TO GIVE UP ON YOU SON MOM IN MOMMY IS STILL HERE.
I'M NEVER GIVING UP ON MY SON AND I WANT EACH ONE OF YOU TO
KNOW THAT HE LIVED WITH HIS MOTHER AND FATHER.
HE HAD A MOTHER AND FATHER AT HOME TO RAISE HIM.
IT WAS A TWO PARENT FAMILY AND THIS SYSTEM AND THIS WORLD
TOOK HIM FROM ME. >> SO PLEASE COME IN.
THANK YOU, MRS. BROWN, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL
HER FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE
AGENDA ITEMS 7377 ITEM 70 THROUGH 77 WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE A UNANIMOUS VOTE
IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING
TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE
SUPERVISOR DORSEY REPORT ITEM 74 74 AND I AM THINKING WE
MIGHT NEED TO PULL 70 AND 71. >> YES.
ALL RIGHT. ANY OTHERS?
OKAY SO WE'RE PULLING 7071 AND 74 AND MADAM CLERK COULD
YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE BALANCE OF THE ITEMS?
>> YES. ON 72, 73, 75, 76 AND 77
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU. OH BY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
GENTLEMEN I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED
AND THEN MADAM CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 70?
>> ITEM 70 IS ON SECOND APPEARANCE.
IT IS NO LONGER UNANIMOUS. IT HAS AN EIGHT VOTE THRESHOLD
ITEM 70 IS A MOTION TO ADOPT FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE
BOARD'S DISAPPROVAL OF PLANNING COMMISSION MOTION NUMBER 21 727
APPROVING A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR THE PROPOSED
PROJECT AT 3400 LAGUNA STREET. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 70 AND 71 MR. PRESIDENT, MY GROUP TOGETHER
ITEM SEVEN I DIDN'T CALL 70 ONE THE ITEM 71 IS ON SECOND
APPEARANCE. IT'S NO LONGER UNANIMOUS.
IT HAS AN EIGHT BOTH THRESHOLD. THIS IS A MOTION ADOPTING
FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE BOARD'S DISAPPROVAL OF THE
DECISION OF THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION BY ITS
MOTION NUMBER 494 TO APPROVE A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 3400 LAGUNA STREET.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 70
AND 71. >> ITEM 70 AND 71 SUPERVISOR
DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MILKER MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO
WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN VOTING NO THE MOTIONS ARE APPROVED MADAM
CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 74 ITEM 74 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO DECLARE THE MONTH OF AUGUST 2025 AS AFGHAN-AMERICAN
HERITAGE MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES
WITH ITEM 74 I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT IN DECLARING AUGUST
2025 AS AFGHAN-AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> THIS MEASURE OFFERS US AN
IMPORTANT OPPORTUNITY TO FORMALLY RECOGNIZE
AND CELEBRATE THE MANY CULTURAL, CIVIC AND ECONOMIC
CONTRIBUTION THAT AFGHAN AMERICANS HAVE MADE TO THE
FABRIC OF OUR CITY. AFGHAN AMERICANS CAN CONTRIBUTE
TO EVERY FACET OF LIFE IN SAN FRANCISCO FROM SMALL BUSINESS
OWNERS AND ARTISTS TO EDUCATORS ,HEALTH CARE WORKERS
AND PUBLIC SERVANTS THEY'RE AN INTEGRAL PART OF WHAT MAKES OUR
CITY VIBRANT. AS THE SUPERVISOR REPRESENTING
DISTRICT SIX HOME TO MANY OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST DIVERSE
AND RESILIENT COMMUNITIES, IT'S ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL TO ME TO
BRING THIS RESOLUTION FORWARD. OUR OFFICE IS PROUD TO HAVE
MOHANA SOMEBODY ON OUR TEAM A DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVANT,
THOUGHTFUL, THOUGHTFUL POLICY ADVISOR AND FORCEFUL ADVOCATE
FOR EQUITY, BELONGING AND JUSTICE AND THE BOARD'S
FIRST AND ONLY AFGHAN-AMERICAN LEGISLATIVE AIDE AS THE
DAUGHTER OF REFUGEES AND A STRONG VOICE FOR HER COMMUNITY,
MOHANA HAS BEEN INSTRUMENTAL IN ADVANCING SOME OF OUR
OFFICE'S MOST IMPORTANT WORK ON PUBLIC SAFETY AND COMMUNITY
HEALING WHETHER SHE'S ORGANIZING CULTURAL EVENTS AT
CITY HALL, SUPPORTING CONSTITUENTS IN MOMENTS OF
CRISIS OR AMPLIFYING VOICES THAT TOO OFTEN GO UNHEARD.
MOHAMMED LEADS WITH BOTH COMPASSION AND CONVICTION.
WE'RE LUCKY TO HAVE HER IN SAN FRANCISCO IS BETTER FOR HER
SERVICE THIS MONTH. GIVE US A CHANCE TO REFLECT ON
THE RICHNESS OF AFGHAN CULTURE AND THE RESILIENCE OF THE
AFGHAN AND DIASPORA MANY OF WHOM HAVE FACED DISPLACEMENT,
CONFLICT AND LOSS YET CONTINUE TO CONTRIBUTE TO OUR CITY WITH
REMARKABLE GENEROSITY AND GRACE AS WE RECOGNIZE AFGHAN AMERICAN
HERITAGE MONTH MAY WE ALSO RECOMMIT TO BUILDING A CITY
THAT HONORS IMMIGRANT STORIES, EMBRACES DIVERSITY IS A
STRENGTH AND ENSURES EVERY COMMUNITY HAS A SEAT AT THE
TABLE. I ALSO LOOK FORWARD TO
CELEBRATING HOPEFULLY WITH AS MANY OF YOU AS POSSIBLE THE
SECOND ANNUAL AFRICAN AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH CELEBRATION NEXT
MONTH AN EVENT THAT BRINGS TOGETHER FAMILIES, COMMUNITY
LEADERS AND NEIGHBORS TO UPLIFT UPLIFT AFGHAN VOICES
AND CULTURE IN THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR DORSEY
MADAM CLERK, YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 74.
>> ITEM 74 SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR
AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MY POINT I'M NOT MUCH I'M A SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
HIGH MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
ARE ELEVENSES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NO IMPERATIVE ITEMS TO REPORT.
ALL RIGHT. COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND SUPERVISOR AMANDA MANDOLIN
FOR THE LATE MR. DAN DILLON ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN
FOR THE LATE MR. CHRISTOPHER CHARLES BRAGG PRAGATI ON BEHALF
OF SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR THE LATE MS. MAUREEN DOWLING AND ON
BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR OF MY WARD FOR THE LATE MR. MELVIN BOOLA,
ONE OF MY COLLEAGUES. I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE
END OF OUR AGENDA. MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THANK YOU, DEPUTIES. AS THERE'S NO FURTHER BUSINESS
WE ARE ADJOURNED